<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="main.xsl"?>
<html>
  <head>
    <title>Warhammer Examples</title>
    <meta charset="UTF-8" />
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="https://fonts.googleapis.com/css?family=Merriweather"/>
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="main.css"/>
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="gf.css"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <div class="main">
      <div class="title">Warhammer Examples</div>
      
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="assess">General Assessments</h1>
        <p>
          Most Fantasy RPG games, as a rule set have many
          genre-specific rules, that will not interest us here.  As an
          example take Insanity Points in War Hammer 2.  We are only
          interested in resolving skill rolls and conflicts in
          general.  We leave the genre rules untouched.  As another
          example, the guild structure can be added on top.  The rules
          can also be applied to large groups of non-fantasy settings,
          possibly augmented by skills in the same spirit.
        </p>
        <p>
          When applying our meta-rule &#8212; <em>10 points difference
          grant a <n10/>:<n1/> chance of winning</em> &#8212; we find
          that many games, for example Warhammer, Harnmaster,
          Runequest, and Rolemaster provide approximately 4 levels.
          There are a lot of generalizations happening here, but
          basically these levels are at <n5/>%, <em>34</em>%,
          <em>84</em>% and <em>95</em>%.  The most activity being in
          the middle range, we conclude that a +<n5/>% bonus should be
          a +<n1/> in our skill charts.  Of course, at the edge of the
          scale, such a bonus is vastly more important.  The
          purpose of these rules is to weed out such discrepencies.
        </p>
        <p>
          We <em>normalize</em> any skill with respect to an
          uneducated, uncivilized, but healthy human of about 20-30
          years of age without any training whatsoever.  He has no
          equipment and only simple clothing.  He is called the
          &#8220;N&#8221;ormalized &#8220;N&#8221;obody, <em>NN</em>
          for short.
        </p>
        <p>
          This following table provides an "exact" reference for
          conversion of classical percentage-based skill levels. The
          extensions beyound <n5/>% and <em>95</em>% are relatively
          arbitrary. The rarely come into play and turn out needlessly
          complicated if correctly applied.
        </p>
        <table>
          <caption>Table 1</caption>
          <tr>
            <th>0</th><th>1</th><th>2</th><th>3</th><th>4</th>
            <th>5</th><th>6</th><th>7</th><th>8</th><th>9</th>
            <th>10</th><th>11</th><th>12</th><th>13</th><th>14</th>
            <th>15</th><th>16</th><th>17</th><th>18</th><th>19</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>-0.5</td><td>-0.4</td><td>-0.3</td><td>-0.2</td><td>-0.1</td>
            <td>0.00</td><td>0.08</td><td>0.16</td><td>0.22</td><td>0.27</td>
            <td>0.32</td><td>0.37</td><td>0.41</td><td>0.45</td><td>0.49</td>
            <td>0.53</td><td>0.56</td><td>0.59</td><td>0.62</td><td>0.65</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>20</th><th>21</th><th>22</th><th>23</th><th>24</th>
            <th>25</th><th>26</th><th>27</th><th>28</th><th>29</th>
            <th>30</th><th>31</th><th>32</th><th>33</th><th>34</th>
            <th>35</th><th>36</th><th>37</th><th>38</th><th>39</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>0.68</td><td>0.70</td><td>0.73</td><td>0.75</td><td>0.78</td>
            <td>0.80</td><td>0.82</td><td>0.85</td><td>0.87</td><td>0.89</td>
            <td>0.91</td><td>0.93</td><td>0.95</td><td>0.97</td><td>0.99</td>
            <td>1.01</td><td>1.03</td><td>1.05</td><td>1.07</td><td>1.08</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>40</th><th>41</th><th>42</th><th>43</th><th>44</th>
            <th>45</th><th>46</th><th>47</th><th>48</th><th>49</th>
            <th>50</th><th>51</th><th>52</th><th>53</th><th>54</th>
            <th>55</th><th>56</th><th>57</th><th>58</th><th>59</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>1.10</td><td>1.12</td><td>1.14</td><td>1.16</td><td>1.17</td>
            <td>1.19</td><td>1.21</td><td>1.23</td><td>1.24</td><td>1.26</td>
            <td>1.28</td><td>1.30</td><td>1.31</td><td>1.33</td><td>1.35</td>
            <td>1.37</td><td>1.38</td><td>1.40</td><td>1.42</td><td>1.44</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>60</th><th>61</th><th>62</th><th>63</th><th>64</th>
            <th>65</th><th>66</th><th>67</th><th>68</th><th>69</th>
            <th>70</th><th>71</th><th>72</th><th>73</th><th>74</th>
            <th>75</th><th>76</th><th>77</th><th>78</th><th>79</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>1.45</td><td>1.47</td><td>1.49</td><td>1.51</td><td>1.53</td>
            <td>1.55</td><td>1.57</td><td>1.59</td><td>1.61</td><td>1.63</td>
            <td>1.65</td><td>1.67</td><td>1.69</td><td>1.71</td><td>1.73</td>
            <td>1.76</td><td>1.78</td><td>1.80</td><td>1.83</td><td>1.85</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>80</th><th>81</th><th>82</th><th>83</th><th>84</th>
            <th>85</th><th>86</th><th>87</th><th>88</th><th>89</th>
            <th>90</th><th>91</th><th>92</th><th>93</th><th>94</th>
            <th>95</th><th>96</th><th>97</th><th>98</th><th>99</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>1.88</td><td>1.91</td><td>1.94</td><td>1.97</td><td>2.00</td>
            <td>2.03</td><td>2.07</td><td>2.10</td><td>2.14</td><td>2.19</td>
            <td>2.23</td><td>2.28</td><td>2.34</td><td>2.40</td><td>2.47</td>
            <td>2.55</td><td>2.65</td><td>2.75</td><td>2.85</td><td>2.95</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h3 id="precis">Precision</h3>
        <p>
          Precision depends on the context, but principally you should
          not be more exact than <n10/>%. (No more than one decimal
          point.)  As smallest units we will use the second, the gramm
          and the centimeter.
        </p>
        <h3 id="precis">Operations</h3>
        <p>
          The concrete play of the numbers (<em>operations</em>) must
          be given in a section with examples.  This depends on the
          style of play. Also the need for such examples depends on
          the style of play.  Where situations are estimated in the
          same manner by all participants, no reference to tables or
          calculations are needed. Rolling the estimated chances
          according to the general rules would be sufficent.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="skills">Skills</h1>
        <p>
          Skill Tests can be given descriptive levels, here we choose
          <em>Very Easy&#160;(-20), Easy&#160;(-10), Average&#160;(0),
          Hard&#160;(10), Very Hard&#160;(20), Extremely
          Hard&#160;(30)</em>.  Note that any difference of <n20/> or
          more is regularly not worth rolling.
        </p>
        <p>
          Skills listed explicitely are explained in descriptive terms
          for their levels.  Many skills are grouped; where practical,
          they can be separated or more can be created as speciality of a more
          generic skill.  Sometimes skills strad
        </p>
        <p>
          Many skills, even skill groups are not listed, becaiuse
          their descriptions would simply consist in comparisons with
          other skill uses.  For instance, <em>Concealment</em> and
          <em>Search</em> are opposed to each other or a
          <em>Combat</em> skill group would compare uses against each
          other.  Where such comparison is sufficient to describe a
          skill, it is omitted.
        </p>
        <h3 id="acare">Care</h3>
        <p>
          This is intended for <em>Animal Care</em>, but can also be
          applied to humans as <em>Healing</em>, adapted accordingly.
        </p>
        <ul class="explain">
          <li>
            <b>Level 0:</b> NN knows the uses and obvious differences
            between domestic animals.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 10:</b> With this level, proper food for an
            animal are known.  The well-being can be discerned and
            fostered.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 20:</b> Common illnesses of the various domestic
            animals are known, as well treatment thereof.  Moods can
            easily be subdued or provoked.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 30:</b> Caring for animals is second nature.
            Esoteric conditions can be detected and possibly treated.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <h3 id="charm">Charm</h3>
        <p>
          Understanding animals or humans as a skill works in the same
          scales, even though the mechanisms are different.  Some
          applications of the skill require additional "investments",
          for example providing food or mutual touch.  These skills
          can be used without consciously (actively) doing so.
        </p>
        <ul class="explain">
          <li>
            <b>Level 0:</b> For NN befriending a subject without
            outside aid is a game of chance.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 10:</b> At this level, understanding the
            situation from the subjects point of view can be
            leveraged.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 20:</b> Empathy for the subject can be projected
            to it, appealing to the subject's unconscious.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 30:</b> Instinctively foreseeing reactions of the
            subject to various potential actions you can adjust your
            actual action accordingly.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <h3 id="out">Outdoor</h3>
        <p>
          This includes <em>Tracking, Survival</em>, or
          <em>Trapping</em>.
        </p>
        <ul class="explain">
          <li>
            <b>Level 0:</b> NN can detect obvious natural markings.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 10:</b> Perceive common wilderness markings and
            use connections between them.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 20:</b> Small, older, and irregular signs are
            observed and used, behavior of inhabitants guessed at.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 30:</b> Almost all markings, even miniscule and
            ephemeral, are noticed.  Reasonable estimates of behavior
            of other denizens of the area are at your disposal.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <h3 id="know">Knowledge</h3>
        <p>
          All knowledge skills work in the same manner, regardless of
          how difficult it is to achieve a certain level of expertise.
          Keep in mind the meta-rule from the introduction.
          <em>Evaluate, Navigation, Plant Biology, Animal Biology,
          Medicine, Alchemy, Gamble, Mechanics, Languages, Scripts,
          Etiquette, Art</em>, and <em>Music</em> are knowledge
          skills.  Note that not applications of knowledge are without
          danger.  For example, using sleight-of-hand in a game of
          chance is usually considered unfair.  Hiding such skill
          application often is a different skill.
        </p>
        <ul class="explain">
          <li>
            <b>Level 0:</b> NN barely knows that a domain for such
            knowledge exists.  With some luck, he can guess whether a
            general topic belongs to that domain or not.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 10:</b> With this level, the basic concepts are
            known, the more esoteric concepts have been heard of but
            cannot be applied.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 20:</b> All concepts of the domain are known and
            can be applied with confidence.  There are only a few
            topics escaping the grasps of this expert.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 30:</b> Mastery of the subject matter as far as
            humanly possible.  Genuine research or creation of new
            substance is possible.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <h3 id="sport">Sports</h3>
        <p>
          <em>Swim, Drive, Sail, Row, Climb</em>, and <em>Running</em>
          all fall in this category.
        </p>
        <ul class="explain">
          <li>
            <b>Level 0:</b> NN knows what the discipline is about and
            knows his limits.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 10:</b> Any equipment or common techniques can be
            used as intended.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 20:</b> Improved equipment or special techniques
            can be used towards advantage.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 30:</b> New equipment or techniques may be
            invented (usually applying only to special cases.)
          </li>
        </ul>
        <h3 id="craft">Crafts</h3>
        <p>
          Just as Knowledge skills, crafting skills come in many
          varieties.  For example, <em>Drawing, Music, Acting, Animal
          Training, Artisanry, Juweler, Engineering, Masonry, Leather
          working, Smithing</em>, or <em>Clothier.</em>
        </p>
        <ul class="explain">
          <li>
            <b>Level 0:</b> NN knows, what type of tools are needed
            for the craft.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 10:</b> Journeyman level, most tasks can be
            accomplished routinely.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 20:</b> Mastery of the craft, can accomplish all
            complex tasks of the craft.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 30:</b> reknown expert in the craft, may invent
            new techniques or tools.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <h3 id="craft">Combat</h3>
        <p>
          Appropriate separate skills are available for different weapon groups.
        </p>
        <ul class="explain">
          <li>
            <b>Level 0:</b> NN knows, which weapons are appropriate
            for the skill and will not injure himself with them.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 10:</b> Handles the weapon with ease and knows
            its tactics.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 20:</b> Professional soldiers with veteran
            experience.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 30:</b> Legendary mastery of the weapon,
            including specialized tactics.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="talent">Talents</h1>
        <p>
          Talents, also known as Feats or Traits, constitute modfiers
          to (single or different) skill rolls that apply under
          special circumstances. A s with Skills, Talents may overlap
          and sometimes appl to the same situations.
        </p>
        <h3 id="senses">Senses</h3>
        <p>
	        These talents include <em>Better Hearing, Nightvision, Sharp
	        eyes, Instinctive Orientation</em> and <em>Sixth Sense</em>.
	        These generally improve reaction skills.
        </p>
        <h3 id="physic">Physical Features</h3>
        <p>
          Typical examples are: <em>Ambidextrous, Flexible, Wings,
          Frightening, Reflexes, Natural Weapons</em>, and
          <em>Resistance against Poisons</em>.  Usually these also
          only apply to sports-like skills.
        </p>
        <h3 id="senses">Mental Features</h3>
        <p>
          This section contains <em>Fearless, Haggler, Fury,
          Meditation</em>, or <em>Total Recall</em>.  Depending on the
          mental state, these can range affect any skill but each
          talent only has a limited range.
        </p>
        <h3 id="senses">Boosts</h3>
        <p>
          Boosts are only valid for a limited time under certain
          conditions, but can otherwise fall in any of the other
          categories. <em>Frenzy</em>, <em>Flee</em> are typical
          examples.
        </p>
      </div>
    </div>
  </body>
  <!--
      Würfelergebnisse sind stets geheim und werden einzeln, d.h. nach
          einzelnen Progressionswürfeln, offenbart, um die möglichen
          Dauern ab einer Minimaldauer festzustellen bzw, zu verlängern.
    <p>
      In der oben stehenden Tabelle wird für eine gegebene Dauer
      ermittelt, wie man zu der Dauer aufschliesst, die bei 10 Punkten
      schlechterer Fertigkeit erreicht würde.  Die Tabelle läßt sich
      natürlich auch rückwärts lesen.  Es wird empfohlen, auf
      sinnvolle Einheiten zu kürzen und grundsätzlich abzurunden
      bzw. abzuschneiden, um zu kleine und krumme Zeiteinheiten zu
      vermeiden.  In der Tat sind die Zahlen nur auf zwei Stellen
      genau ermittelt; die letzte Zeile gibt die Formel für genauere
      Berechnungen und andere Anfang- und Enddauer.
    </p>
    <h3>Teilerfolge am Beispiel Kampf</h3>
    <p>
      Teilerfolge sind Erfolge, die vor dem eigentlichen Erfolg
      eintreten.  Umgekehrt sind Mehrerfolge Erfolge, die aufgrund
      einer Glücksträhne weitere günstige Ergebnisse zeitigen.  Die
      Begriffe sind komplementär.  (Der Erfolg ist ein Übererfolg
      eines Teilerfolgs.) Diese sollten für oft verwendete Aktionen
      vorgefertigt werden.
    </p>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">Stufe</td>
        <td class="mark">Erfolg</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">0</td><td>Demonstration der Ernsthaftigkeit</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">3</td><td>Erstes Blut oder Bluterguss</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">6</td><td>Schwere Verletzung</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">9</td><td>Kampfunfähigkeit</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">12</td><td>Physische Vernichtung</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <h3>Multiple Dimensionen</h3>
    <p>
      In vielen Situationen wird es darauf ankommen, einen Erfolg in
      mehreren Dimensionen zu ermitteln.  Das geschieht durch
      unabhängige Ermittlung in jeder Dimension.
    </p>
    <p>
      Dimensionen werden auch in anderer Hinsicht als
      <em>unabhängig</em> betrachtet, um das Spiel zu vereinfachen.
      So kann eine Dimension gegen eine andere additiv aufgerechnet
      werden.  Das heißt beispielsweise, ein besseres Ergebnis lässt
      sich durch längere Dauer erkaufen.
    </p>
    <h2>Umkehrung</h2>
    <p>
      Häufig sind mit mehr Würfelergebnissen die Ziele früher erreicht
      als mit wenigen. Nehmen wir an, bei einer Fertigkeit läge bei
      <em>0</em> der Stoppwurf bei <em>30s</em> Dauer liegt, bei
      <em>10</em> bei <em>10s</em> und bei 20 bei <em>1s</em>.  Nun
      läge die Fähigkeit des <em>aktiven</em> bei <em>10</em> und die
      des <em>passiven</em> bei <em>0</em>. Zu erwarten wäre also eine
      Dauer von <em>10s</em>. Legt in diesem Fall der aktive Teil vor
      und kommt bei einer (beispielsweise) <em>7</em> aus, so ist sein
      bestmögliches Ergebnis gemäß Tabelle <em>2s</em>. Sobald diese
      Zeit verstrichen ist, beginnt der <em>passive</em> Teil zu
      würfeln, bis eine neue Zeiteinheit erreicht ist oder die Serie
      beendet ist.  Auf diese Art kommt das Ende der Serie zum
      richtigen Zeitpunkt.
    </p>
    <h3>Doppelte Umkehrung</h3>
    <p>
      Bei manchen (verallgemeinerten) Fertigkeiten, wie zum Beispiel
      zur Heilung von Wunden und Krankheiten ist die Umkehrung in
      mehreren Dimensionen gelegentlich sinnvoll, also sowohl
      zeitlich, um die Dauer der Krankheit in der richtigen Richtung
      zu entwickeln, als auch die Schwere des Endergebnisses, um in
      Richtung vollständiger Genesung zu "zielen".
    </p>
    <h2>Überschussvermeidung</h2>
    <p>
      Gelegentlich ist es sinnvoll, keine Übererfolge zu erzielen,
      dafür eine erhöhte Schwierigkeit in Kauf zu nehmen.  Solange
      nicht spezielle Regeln zutreffen, gilt, dass jede
      Schwierigkeitserhöhung um Eins, die von vornherein angenommen
      wird, zu einer (zusätzlichen) Verzögerung des Übererfolgs um
      eins führt.  Im obigen Beispiel wird die Stufe des <em>Ersten
      Bluts</em> um 2 Punkte erhöht, um zu untenstehender Erfolgsliste
      zu kommen.
    </p>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">Stufe</td>
        <td class="mark">Neue Stufe</td>
        <td class="mark">Erfolg</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">0</td>
        <td>2</td>
        <td>Demonstration der Ernsthaftigkeit</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">3</td>
        <td>5</td>
        <td>Erstes Blut oder Bluterguss</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">6</td>
        <td>10</td>
        <td>Schwere Verletzung</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">9</td>
        <td>13</td>
        <td>Kampfunfähigkeit</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">12</td>
        <td>16</td>
        <td>Physische Vernichtung</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <h2>Kampf</h2>
    <p>
      Es dauert 10 Sekunden, bis NN einem anderen NN seine
      Ernsthaftigkeit demonstriert.  Die Zeitskala ist offensichtlich,
      wie auch die Erfolgsstärke.  Die Genauigkeit bedeutet, ein Ziel
      der entsprechenden Größe wird getroffen.  Bei kleinen Zielen,
      oder Misserfolgen ist es nicht unwahrscheinlich, ein anderes
      (Nicht-)Ziel entsprechend zu treffen.
    </p>
    <h3>Zeit</h3>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">Stufe</td>
        <td class="mark">Zeit</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">-20</td><td>100s</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">-10</td><td>30s</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">0</td><td>10s</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">10</td><td>3s</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">20</td><td>1s</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <h3>Genauigkeit</h3>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">Stufe</td>
        <td class="mark">Treffergröße</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">-20</td><td>1000% (NN)</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">-10</td><td>300% (NN)</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">0</td><td>100% (NN)</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">10</td><td>30% (NN)</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">20</td><td>10% (NN)</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <h3>Stärke</h3>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">Stufe</td>
        <td class="mark">Erfolg</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">0</td><td>Demonstration der Ernsthaftigkeit</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">3</td><td>Erstes Blut oder Bluterguss</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">6</td><td>Schwere Verletzung</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">9</td><td>Kampfunfähigkeit</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="mark">12</td><td>Physische Vernichtung</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  -->
</html>
