<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="main.xsl"?>
<html xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">
  <head>
    <title>Rules for H&#226;rnworld</title>
    <meta charset="UTF-8" />
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="https://fonts.googleapis.com/css?family=Merriweather"/>
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="main.css"/>
    <link rel="stylesheet" media="print" href="mainp.css"/>
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="harn.css"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <div class="main">
      <div class="title">Rules for H&#226;rnworld</div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="rules">Basic Rules</h1>
        <p>
          This is a set of rules, which represent the aspects dealt
          with in the HM3 rule book.  It is difficult to distinguish
          between in-world and out-world rules in HM3 as published.
          Since our aim is to simplify, we will not rewrite all rules
          accordingly, but rather rather stay with the rules as
          written.  When appropriate we mention the distinction
          between in- and out-world.
        </p>
        <h4>Justification</h4>
        <p>
          Sometimes people ask, why rewrite the rules, if the way that
          they adjucate situations changes only slightly and this only
          adds another layer of complexity.  In fact, we add a layer
          of simplification.  The benefit of better scaling and other
          issues that are better addressed warrant the effort.  The
          previous versions of the rules, however, clouded that,
          because we attempted to rewrite them so as to look
          <em>original</em>.  This is no longer attempted, but we only
          explain how these met-rules are applied.
        </p>
        <h4>Probabilities</h4>
        <p>
          This describes the main out-world rule.  A new type of roll
          is introduced, the stop roll.  You roll a d5 until you get a
          1 and then count the number of dice that did not show up a
          1.  That is the same as the number of dice you actually
          rolled minus one.  This roll is made by the active
          character, or more generally, the actor.  It will generate
          positive numbers (or zero) and is termed the
          <em>positive</em> roll and abbreviated as <em>p5</em>.
          Example: Peter rolls 5, 3, 8, 10, 2 (in that order) on a
          d10.  He simulates the d5 by taking the result of a d10,
          halving it and rounding up.  He thus rolled 3, 2, 4, 5, 1,
          on a d5 effectively.  His p5 roll would be a 4.
        </p>
        <p>
          Of course, there is a <em>negative</em> roll that is
          associated with the passive resistance or the impediment.
          It is handled in the same way but the negative value is
          taken instead.  Thus in the above example, we would take -4
          as result of a negative roll; therefore we can simply denote
          the roll as -p5.  These two numbers (from different rolls)
          are added.  The result will be a whole number, called
          <em>n5</em> (n for neutral).  More examples are provided in
          the generic ruleset.  We only repeat the main table for
          convenience.
        </p>
        <include id="$Basic"/>
        <p>
          The general rules also talk about adding skills.  We repeat
          the table provided in that ruleset and also have an
          automated formula here (Html only) when more precise values
          are requested.
        </p>
        <script>
          function f() {
            var s11 = document.getElementById("r1-s1").value;
            var s12 = document.getElementById("r1-s2").value;
            var m1 = Math.max(s11,s12);
            var d1 = m1 - Math.min(s11,s12);
            var re1 = 5  * Math.log(1 + Math.exp(-d1 * Math.LN2 / 5.0)) / Math.LN2;
            document.getElementById("r1-r5").value = Math.round(10 * (re1 + m1)) / 10;
            var s21 = document.getElementById("r2-s1").value;
            var s22 = document.getElementById("r2-s2").value;
            var m2 = Math.max(s21,s22);
            var d2 = m2 - Math.min(s21,s22);
            var re2 = 5  * Math.log(1 + Math.exp(-d2 * Math.LN2 / 5.0)) / Math.LN2;
            document.getElementById("r2-r5").value = Math.round(10 * (re2 + m2)) / 10;
            var s31 = document.getElementById("r3-s1").value;
            var s32 = document.getElementById("r3-s2").value;
            var m3 = Math.max(s31,s32);
            var d3 = m3 - Math.min(s31,s32);
            var re3 = 5  * Math.log(1 + Math.exp(-d3 * Math.LN2 / 5.0)) / Math.LN2;
            document.getElementById("r3-r5").value = Math.round(10 * (re3 + m3)) / 10;
          }
        </script>
        <include id="$Calculate"/>
        <p>
          When using the tables, take the two numbers and use the
          (positive) difference of the two in the first row, to read
          off a result in the second, and add this result to the
          bigger to get the end result.  Looking at the tables, you
          see the reduction in effectiveness when adding smaller
          numbers to higher ones.  Sometimes, to ease writing, we
          denote addition of skill (or task) numbers with
          +<sub>5</sub>, e.g. <em>1 +<sub>5</sub> 2</em>.  This is
          called 5-Addition, because <em>0 +<sub>5</sub> 0 = 5</em>.
        </p>
        <include id="$Calculate-2"/>
        <h3 id="s3kills">Overview</h3>
        <p>
          Whenever we have ML, SB or other technical terms, we append
          an U to distinguish the Universal rules, from the
          classic. E.g. MLU and SBU.  You can calculate MLU as ML *
          0.4.  The basic 50/50 chance of success on a skill roll is
          with an ML of 50%, i.e. an MLU of 20. Thus the most basic
          task difficulty - all other things being equal - should be
          set to 20.
        </p>
        <p>
          Skills govern all activities, from combat to spell-casting.
          All skills are rated on an open scale starting from zero
          (0), with only 10% reaching 10 points more.  This general
          situation is in-world knowledge.  But this is also identical
          with the p5 system of rolling dice, which is out-world.  The
          skill scale is open-ended as the p5 roll is, but humans
          generally do not get scores beyond 50 (out-world).
        </p>
        <p>
          The following is a list of skills that are commonly used by
          characters on H&#226;rn.  It is neither complete no without
          overlap.
        </p>
        <h4>Skill Links</h4>
        <table class="links" style="width:90%">
          <tr>
            <td><a href="#sk-agr">Agriculture</a></td>
            <td><a href="#sk-alc">Alchemy</a></td>
            <td><a href="#sk-awa">Awareness</a></td>
            <td><a href="#sk-cli">Climbing</a></td>
            <td><a href="#sk-end">Endurance</a></td>
            <td><a href="#sk-fis">Fishing</a></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><a href="#sk-fle">Fletching</a></td>
            <td><a href="#sk-for">Foraging</a></td>
            <td><a href="#sk-hera">Heraldry</a></td>
            <td><a href="#sk-herb">Herblore</a></td>
            <td><a href="#sk-ini">Initiative</a></td>
            <td><a href="#sk-jum">Jumping</a></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><a href="#sk-men">Mental Conflict</a></td>
            <td><a href="#sk-mov">Move</a></td>
            <td><a href="#sk-phy">Physician</a></td>
            <td><a href="#sk-pie">Piety</a></td>
            <td><a href="#sk-psi">Psi Talents</a></td>
            <td><a href="#sk-rhe">Rhetoric</a></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><a href="#sk-swi">Swimming</a></td>
            <td><a href="#sk-thr">Throwing</a></td>
            <td><a href="#sk-weat">Weatherlore</a></td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h4>Attribute Links</h4>
        <table class="links" style="width:75%">
          <tr>
            <td><a href="#sk-agi">Agility</a></td>
            <td><a href="#sk-dex">Dexterity</a></td>
            <td><a href="#sk-eye">Eyesight</a></td>
            <td><a href="#sk-hea">Hearing</a></td>
            <td><a href="#sk-sta">Stamina</a></td>
            <td><a href="#sk-str">Strength</a></td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h4>Dimension Links</h4>
        <table class="links" style="width:75%">
          <tr>
            <td><a href="#di-acc">Accuracy</a></td>
            <td><a href="#di-co1">Combat/Melee</a></td>
            <td><a href="#di-co2">Combat/Missile</a></td>
            <td><a href="#di-co3">Combat/Grapple</a></td>
            <td><a href="#di-kno">Knowledge</a></td>
            <td><a href="#di-reg">Regional</a></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><a href="#di-rec">Recipes</a></td>
            <td><a href="#di-tra">Travel</a></td>
            <td><a href="#di-yie">Yield</a></td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h4>Skill Development</h4>
        <p>
          Skill Development is set up such that about 20% of MLU of n
          have MLU+10.  Since everyone has at least MLU 0, for normal
          cases, this means that about 3 in 10000 have MLU of 50.
          Individual may be awarded by the GM at any time, when
          something was &#8220;learned&#8221; (this is out-world).
          Remember that you learn most from failures.  Some skills may
          be developed by practice/study, some require training.  When
          you need time to learn, read this from the following table.
          I.e. the better you already are, the harder it is to
          improve.
        </p>
        <include id="$Teaching"/>
        <p>
          Some skill require that a teacher is present at the
          beginning of a skill career, e.g. because a Lnaguags cannot
          be learned without someone who actually speaks it reasonably
          well, or &#8220;glass blower trade secret&#8221; are
          imparted.  This is mentioned with the approproate skill.
        </p>
        <p>
          In all cases, GM discretion is highly advised.  When a
          mentor, coach, or teacher is available it can improve
          learning speed.  But materials may be of bad quality or
          study time is interrupted frequently.  The time to increase
          an MLU this way should usually be within 20% of the listed
          number. (A more thorough rule can be devised, but this does
          not seem to be of general interest.
        </p>
        <p>
          Sometimes forgetting or &#8220;unlearning&#8221; is called
          for.  If skill has not been used for as many days is stated
          in the table to <em>learn</em> something, deduct a point.
        </p>
        <p>
          Improving Specialties is a bit more elaborate.  Skills list
          specialties with a percentage value.  This percentage value
          gives the approximate part of the whole group that this
          specialization comprises.  When the skill is improved (the
          skill group of all specialties) all improvement may be
          dedicated to the specialty instead.  As an example, a
          Specialty/20 could see an improvement of 5 points instead of
          a 1 for the group and a 40% Specialty an improvement of 2.5
          points of the specialty instead of 1 for the group.  So,
          divide 100% by the given percentage to get a multiple
          <em>m</em>.  The time needed is the average of all the MLU
          points improved according to the basic law.
        </p>
        <p>
          Note: If at any time the skill group itself is developed,
          specialties are only improved, if they would fall below the
          MLU of the group otherwise.  It would be prudent to learn
          the &#8220;opposite&#8221; Specialty.
        </p>
        <h4>Dimensions</h4>
        <p>
          Dimensions are collected as common reference for the many
          skills that use them in more or less the same manner.  They
          determine a frame of reference for the difficulties of
          tasks.  They can also used in-world, but are more regularly
          used out-world, when a PC tries to achieve a concrete goal.
        </p>
        <h4>Attributes</h4>
        <p>
          Attributes come in textual form and a few in numeric form.
          The numeric attributes are listed above separately.  To have
          an appropriate scale, and keep the rule, just keep the
          attribute as-is.  Everything else, including the star-scale
          follows from there.
        </p>
        <p>
          When an attribute roll is called for, it comes in two forms.
          The first treats the attribute as a ficticious skill with an
          ML as a multiple of the attribute.  This form is treated as
          any MLU.  Say, Strength is 9 and a roll vs. 2 x Strength is
          called for.  The MLU is 7 and the task level is 20 (default).
        </p>
        <p>
          The second version is rolling n number of d6, summing them
          up and stay below an attribute value.  This does not fit
          well into the scheme, but the spirit is obviously that with
          each additional die the chances to succeed become sharply
          worse.  Treat 1d6 as task level 0, 2d6 as task level 5, 3d6
          as 10, and so on.
        </p>
        <h4>Specialties</h4>
        <p>
          Many skills can be divided into sub-skills or specialties;
          suggestions are given with some skills.  Characters may
          select specialties at any time.  The skill is then termed a
          group skill and includes all (potential) specialties, even
          if unknown.  The specific specialty skill is opened at the
          current group MLU (note that the ML can be calculated from
          that, if needed).  Each specialty is developed as a separate
          skill.
        </p>
        <p>
          Sometimes, only Specialties are given and the question
          arises, what MLU in the Specialty applies to the skill
          group.  Each specialty has a percentage value associated
          with it.  (For a new Specialty, this must be decided upon by
          the GM.)  Take that percentage of Specialty MLU to get the
          group&#8217;s MLU.  For example, a Mask/20% specialty in
          Woodcraft of 12 would imply a Woodcraft group score of 2.4,
          rounded down to 2.  This applies only to MLU.  OML (if
          specialization is attempted at the outset) is as for the
          group skill.
        </p>
        <h4>Sunsign</h4>
        <p>
          Sunsigns represent an astrological affinity to certain
          skills in-world, see original rules.  They give a direct bonus
          to the MLU.
        </p>
        <h4>Skill Testing</h4>
        <p>
          MLU is modified for a concrete test due to various
          circumstance resulting in an EMLU. Only minor additions or
          subtractions are considered.  In the odd case, where
          original rules call for taking half of the ML, subtract 10
          from the MLU.
        </p>
        <p>
          When a character attempts to use a skill, n5 is rolled,
          adding EMLU.  The GM will have decided upon a diffculty
          level of the task, often called the <em>negative</em> part.
          Some modfifiers are compounded here, although this makes no
          difference, whether it were included in the EMLU instead.
          This value is also subtracted from the roll and if the net
          result is non-negative, the skill has been successfully
          employed; if the roll is negative, the attempt has failed.
          For example, if a PC declares the intent to perform a
          gymnastic feat, the GM would instruct the player to
          &#8220;test Acrobatics against difficulty 15.&#8221; In
          cases where success or failure may not be obvious, the GM
          should make the roll secretly.
        </p>
        <p>
          It is often necessary to know the degree of success or
          failure.  The skill descriptions provide these so-called
          dimensions.  For skills, where no appropriate success levels
          are provided or for newly devised skills, estimate the
          effects by looking at the skills most closely related.
        </p>
        <p>
          When two characters use skills against each other, each
          character makes a p5 skill roll appropriate to the skill in
          question and the results are compared to give a net result.
          The descriptions of the two skills should match this net
          result (they should obviously be the negative of each
          other).  The character with the higher result wins the
          challenge.  If both characters achieve the same success
          level, the stalemate result of zero (0) applies.  If a tie
          is not appropriate to the situation, then decimal place may
          be rolled as explained in the initial section.
        </p>
        <h4>Penalties</h4>
        <p>
          Penalties are added to the task difficulty and rated at 40%
          of the original value.  For instance, a S10 wound turns into
          a -4 IPU.
        </p>
        <h4>Special Skill Considerations</h4>
        <p>
          Situations or skill applications can either fit to a certain
          skill fully or only partially.  Sometimes multiple skills
          may apply.  In any given situation, the GM will state the
          skills that apply and to what percentage.  Then use a
          weighted average as skill.  Example: The GM rules that
          performing a ballet, is 60% Acrobatics and 40% Dancing
          non-overlapping.  A character with MLU Acrobatics/16 and MLU
          Dancing/11 has MLU Ballet/14.
        </p>
        <p>
          Multiple attackers can combine their efforts through
          5-Addition into one.  This is generally a complex topic,
          because modifiers need to be accommodated as they enter the
          game, so this is best reserved for NPCs that perform as
          single units.  Multiple defendants are similarly added.  An
          exception to this is mounted combat, where PC rider and
          horse may be acting in unison.
        </p>
        <h3 id="d3im">Dimensions</h3>
        <p>
          The following shows example dimensions for the various
          skills, usually only the dominant ones.  Finding the
          appropriate dimension depends on the concrete circumstances.
          Consider what would be appropriate for an untrained
          individual (MLU 0) and what is expected (the average result)
          for a sufficiently educated persion (MLU 20).  Interprete
          the results inbetween and outside of the bounds accordingly.
        </p>
        <h5 id="di-acc">Accuracy</h5>
        <p>
          Judging the values of goods produced or performances
          delivered works the same for almost all skills.  This is
          different from the commercial value, which depends on a lot
          of other factors (market size, etc).  The rare occasion,
          where the MLU of the actor cannot be judged are at GM
          discretion.  I.e. someone who successfully evades perception
          cannot be judged on this &#8220;performance&#8221; by the
          potentially fooled or only in the most general sense.  The
          value in parenthesis is the range by which the estimation
          may be off.  It is calculated from the percentage value x by
          the range (100% - x) to 1/(100% - x).
        </p>
        <include id="$D-Accuracy"/>
        <h5 class="skill" id="sk-agi">Agility</h5>
        <p>
          The skill is used for multiple purposes; to avoid falling
          objects, weapon and missile attacks, and other situations
          requiring Agility.  See Combat for a relevant dimension.
        </p>
        <h5 class="skill" id="sk-agr">Agriculture</h5>
        <p>
          H&#226;rn Manor shows that the following dimension is
          useful: assume a standard task level of 20 and adjust the
          result for any applicable modifiers (such as Hardiness
          Rating), the resulting net value gives the percentage of the
          crop yield that is in excess or short of the 100%.  (See
          H&#226;rn Manor 29.) For example, if the MLU is 20, all
          modifiers are a total of -10 and the roll itself + +5, then
          the net value is -5, resulting in a crop yield of 95% in the
          given year.
        </p>
        <h5 class="skill" id="sk-alc">Alchemy</h5>
        <p>
          The <em>Recipe</em> dimension is commonly used.
        </p>
        <h5 class="skill" id="sk-awa">Awareness</h5>
        <p>
          Sleeping adds at least 10 to any task difficulty.  Loud
          noises give a bonus to the Skill roll.
        </p>
        <h5 class="skill" id="sk-cli">Climbing</h5>
        <p>
          Speed is measured as a factor to normal (walk) move.  A
          running total of vertical progress is kept to determine when
          the climb is complete, and the extent of any fall.  A single
          scale should only be rolled once, but any interruption, such
          as rest requires a new roll.  Any negative speed result (n5
          net result below 0) implies a fall.  Climbing speed can be
          increased at the price of increasing the risk.  A fall is
          evenly distributed across the attempted climbing height.
        </p>
        <include id="$D-Climbing"/>
        <h5 class="skill" id="di-co1">Combat/Melee</h5>
        <p>
          One dimension is the time (in seconds), which it takes to
          achieve the wound level zero on the defender.  The wound
          level is a separate dimension.  You should use trajectories.
          Once a (rolled) progression has reached its goal, a new
          skill roll is necessary.  It is therefore possible to play
          10 second round-based combat.
        </p>
        <p>
          The fractional parts for the higher values in the time
          dimension mean that multiple attacks &#8220;connect&#8221;
          at the same time.  This is to avoid combat in split seconds.
        </p>
        <p>
          Any effects from wounds or other external influences in
          combat are applied immediately to pending progressions, but
          the wound itself is modified by <em>B/E/P</em> of choice
          from the weapon and the appropriate armor.  The offset is
          along the trajectory chosen.  Note that the same is true
          for affects on the defender.  If this implies an action to
          occur in the past, it is resolved immediately.
        </p>
        <include id="$D-Combat"/>
        <h5 class="skill" id="di-co2">Combat/Missile</h5>
        <p>
          Use the same dimension as the Melee combat, but do not
          modify the time dimension below 5s.  Reloading a crossbow
          takes 10s.
        </p>
        <h5 class="skill" id="di-co3">Combat/Grapple</h5>
        <p>
          Wounds are treated as penalty to activity that involves the
          affected body part instead of damage to heal.  Such wounds
          are reduced to zero, once the grapple is no longer maintained.
        </p>
        <h5 class="skill" id="sk-dex">Dexterity</h5>
        <p>
          The time dimension is the time it takes to pick up a dropped
          item - this is a combat dimension.
        </p>
        <include id="$D-Dexterity"/>
        <h5 class="skill" id="sk-end">Endurance</h5>
        <p>
          Read Endurance as Healingrate for Fatigue, see Stamina.
          Remember that the fatigue accrued must be used as modifier
          for the next time interval. Standard healing rate is one
          point per minute.  Also consider the increased fatigue rate
          for carrying heavy loads, see Strength.
        </p>
        <include id="$D-Stamina"/>
        <h5 class="skill" id="sk-eye">Eyesight</h5>
        <p>
          The resolution is in mm/m or m/km.  Typical modifications
          are made for contrast (positive), movement (positive),
          distraction (negative), on the border of the visual field
          (negative).
        </p>
        <include id="$D-Eyesight"/>
        <h5 class="skill" id="sk-fis">Fishing</h5>
        <p>
          Fishing uses the <em>Fast Yield</em> dimension.  The base
          yield is one manday of food. Abundance of fish gives a
          modifier between -20 and +20.
        </p>
        <h5 class="skill" id="sk-fle">Fletching</h5>
        <p>
          The ability to make and repair bows and arrows.  Base yield
          is 1/4 bow or 3 arrows, which assumes tools and materials
          are available.  Use the <em>Slow Yield</em> dimensions.
        </p>
        <h5 class="skill" id="sk-for">Foraging</h5>
        <p>
          Fishing uses the <em>Fast Yield</em> dimension.  The base
          yield is one manday of food.  Different climate and terrain
          types may be specialties.  Areas near civilization are
          likely to have a penalty of at least 10.  Excellent
          conditions exist only in tropical rain-forests and special
          places like the Shava Forest with 10 bonus.  Season is
          highly relevant.  To seek specific plants, see Herblore.
          For hunting, see Tracking.  Use the <em>Fast Yield</em>
          dimensions.
        </p>
        <h5 class="skill" id="sk-hea">Hearing</h5>
        <div class="explain">
          <p>
            <em>-20:</em> Rural Silence
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>-10:</em> Whisper
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>0:</em> Low Speech
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>10:</em> Normal Speech
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>20:</em> Carts, Wagons, Combat
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>30:</em> Smith, Stone Quarry, Skirmish
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>40:</em> Thunder
          </p>
        </div>
        <include id="$D-Hearing"/>
        <h5 class="skill" id="sk-hera">Heraldry</h5>
        <p>
          Different regional/cultural types may be specialties.  The
          skill uses the <em>Recipe</em> and <em>Accuracy</em>
          dimensions.  One describes the achievements a character can
          actively reproduce/draw, the other the recognized
          achievements, if seen.
        </p>
        <h5 class="skill" id="sk-herb">Herblore</h5>
        <p>
          Different climate and terrain types may be specialties.  The
          ability to find and identify individual types of plant.  MLU
          is modified according to the plant&#8217;s rarity, seeking a
          plant in an inappropriate locale should also reduce ML.  Use
          the <em>Recipe</em>, <em>Accuracy</em> and <em>Fast
          Yield</em> dimensions.  The former dimension describes the
          recognized herbs, if seen.  Trajectories are commonplace.
        </p>
        <h5 class="skill" id="sk-ini">Initiative</h5>
        <p>
          Initiative reflects battle experience, discipline, and
          morale.  Initiative determines the speed in which characters
          can assess a stressful situation.  Instead of rolling a
          general awareness roll, the characters take the time listed
          before they can act.  An ambush and similar situations can
          give a bonus (for the ambushing party) as can the general
          awareness that combat is imminent.  Sleeping and other
          unawareness situations may incur hefty penalties.
        </p>
        <p>
          During the time a character is &#8220;frozen&#8221; this
          way, he is trying to understand the situation he is in and
          assesses the options he has.  He is <em>cautious</em> during
          that time.  General awareness issues such as during an
          ambush are not covered by Initiative.
        </p>
        <p>
          Battle-hardened characters may come into the fractional
          range often.  Optionally fractions can be used to determine
          who goes first.  The GM determines, whether going first
          impedes the action of another already in the second that
          action culminates.  This changes the drama of simultaneous
          activity, which may or may not be appropriate.
        </p>
        <include id="$D-Initiative"/>
        <h5 class="skill" id="sk-jum">Jumping</h5>
        <p>
          Jumping is tested when a character attempts to leap for
          height or distance.  Results assume a running start; for
          standing jumps, halve heights and distances.  Results below
          0 turn into a Fall.  For each 5 levels of dimension that are
          also accepted as fall, increase ML by 1 point.
        </p>
        <include id="$D-Jumping"/>
        <h5 class="skill" id="di-kno">Knowledge</h5>
        <p>
          This dimension can be exploited as knowledge and the
          knowledge about knowledge, i.e. how sure is the character
          that his reproduction of the knowledge is correct.  Some
          example task difficulties follow.
        </p>
        <div class="explain">
          <p>
            <em>0:</em> Character barely knows the domain for such
            knowledge exists.  With some luck, he can guess whether a
            general topic belongs to that domain or not.
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>10:</em> The basic concepts are known, the more
            esoteric concepts have been heard of but cannot be
            applied.
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>20:</em> Almost all concepts of the domain are known
            and can be applied with confidence.  Only a few topics
            escape the grasp.
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>30:</em> All of the domain is understood with ease.
            It is hard to find unknown territory, although it exists.
            Improvement of the art is possible.
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>40:</em> Mastery of the subject matter as far as
            humanly possible.  Genuine research or creation of new
            substance is possible.
          </p>
        </div>
        <h5 class="skill" id="sk-men">Mental Conflict</h5>
        <include id="$PsiConflict"/>
        <p>
          A fatigue rate of 1 fatigue level per minute is multiplied
          be the result in the table.  Mental Conflict is resolved
          similar to normal combat.
        </p>
        <include id="$D-PsiConflict"/>
        <h5 class="skill" id="sk-mov">Move</h5>
        <p>
          Humans can accelerate and decelerate as 3 m/s each second.
          Turning options are in parts of a full circle (centered
          around the direction of travel).  E.g. at 3 m/s this means
          60&#176; off the direction of travel on either side per
          second.  For the sake of playability variance in this should
          be suppressed, although a 20% spread (for a 10 level
          difference) with Agility modification could be appropriate.
        </p>
        <p>
          Since steeds and (animal-powered) vehicles are important on
          H&#226;rn, the table is extended beyond the human range.
          Humans max out at 9m/s at optimum.
        </p>
        <include id="$D-Move"/>
        <p>
          A steed&#8217;s movement rate must be declared before
          starting to move.  Effective movement is equal to its Move
          minus Steed Physical Penalty, then indexed in the Move table
          to find speed.  Horses have four rates of speed: Walk/40,
          Trot/60, Canter/80, and Gallop/100.  The number indicates
          the maximum speed that can be reached.  All speeds are
          available at all riding skills, although commanding the
          horse to use it may prove a challenge.  Horses/Steeds
          accelerate and decelerate at 6 m/s each second, but have the
          same turning options.
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>Rotation</em> (also while standing) takes 1 second for
          360 degree revolution (Acrobatic tricks apply) for bipeds,
          which is modified by physical penalty and rounded off.
          Horses take 1 second for 90 degrees, modified and rounded in
          the same way.
        </p>
        <h5 class="skill" id="sk-phy">Physician</h5>
        <p>
          Use Physician skill to determine an improvement for the
          healing rate (see Stamina).  Note that the presence of a
          physician improves the healing rate even further.  The
          injury points are subtracted as penalty to determine the
          healing bonus.
        </p>
        <include id="$D-Physician"/>
        <h5 class="skill" id="sk-pie">Piety</h5>
        <p>
          This skill is not learned as usual but improved through
          righteous actions; it can decline just as fast through
          improper ones.
        </p>
        <include id="$D-Piety"/>
        <h5 class="skill" id="sk-psi">Psi Talents</h5>
        <p>
          All Talents are treated as separate skills.
        </p>
        <h5 class="quality" id="di-qua">Quality</h5>
        <p>
          The Quality dimension can be used when a craftsman attempts
          to produce an item from raw materials.  The result is an
          added to the base value to find the new value.  An item with
          quality less than its base is usually broken.  The results
          obtained do not necessarily reflect market value.  Just
          because an item has +5 quality to its base does not mean
          anyone will pay the difference in pence.  Some finished
          goods may involve several stages of enhancement.  Uncut gems
          may be enhanced by cutting and then further enhanced by
          mounting in a gold-based necklace.  Sometimes an
          item&#8217;s resistance to damage is more important than how
          beautiful it looks.  Examples of this are weapon- and
          armour-crafting.
        </p>
        <p>
          Quality is the net roll divided by 10. I.e. -5 through +4
          results in 0, +5 through +14 results in 1, -15 through -6
          results in -1, and do on.
        </p>
        <h5 class="skill" id="di-rec">Recipes</h5>
        <p>
          For NPCs the associated table can be used to estimate the
          number of different recipes they know how to create.  PCs
          should rather keep a book and start with what their master
          has given them.  Self-made dabblers start with zero (0) and
          would need to do research.  Recipes have a wide range of
          meaning, from classic cooking to tricks the character can
          teach to animals.  It includes ritual or magic invocations.
        </p>
        <include id="$D-Recipes"/>
        <h5 class="skill" id="di-reg">Regional</h5>
        <include id="$D-Regional"/>
        <h5 class="skill" id="sk-rhe">Rhetoric</h5>
        <p>
          Multiple orators may compete for the &#8220;airwaves&#8221;
          and hinder each other more than they realize.  Therefore
          only two actors may combine their skills through 5-Addition
          if working in concert, thereafter it is only the maximum, if
          no competition takes place.  If a competition takes place,
          the difficulty is a 5-Addition instead.
        </p>
        <include id="$D-Rhetoric"/>
        <h5 class="skill" id="sk-sta">Stamina</h5>
        <p>
          Healing time is given for one injury point.  Subtract the
          number of injury points a wound has twice.  Add a potential
          physician&#8217;s bonus once when determining the healing rate for
          the wound. An effective healing rate can be improved with a
          physician present. Note that a reduction in the effective
          wound points does not cause re-evaulation of the effective
          healing rate.
        </p>
        <include id="$D-Stamina"/>
        <h5 class="skill" id="sk-str">Strength</h5>
        <p>
          The listed weight (excluding your own body) can be lifted as
          maximum when you apply the dimension of the table below to
          Strength.  For longer periods of lifting, apply the
          dimension to Endurance to get a maximum carry load
          (MCL). Fatigue rate is determined as the precentage of the
          real load carried divided by MCL multiplied by 10/minute.
        </p>
        <include id="$D-Strength"/>
        <h5 class="skill" id="sk-swi">Swimming</h5>
        <p>
          Difficulty of swimming conditions is rated on the Beaufort
          scale.  Test Swimming once for each continuous swim without
          rest.  Any interruption requires a new roll.  With a result
          below 0 the character starts to sink.  Consider currents for
          speed determination.  A swimmer accumulates one Fatigue
          Level for every minute of swimming at speed, but may rest by
          treading water.  A resting swimmer rolls to see if they
          sink, but does not move (except with the current).
          Underwater Swimming is at half speed.  When attempting to
          convey a conscious swimmer, apply a penalty of 5, for an
          unconscious person apply a penalty of 10.
        </p>
        <include id="$D-Swimming"/>
        <p>
          If a character is in water deeper than their height, a Sink
          result implies the character goes down with the speed of the
          negative result.  (I.e. -5 means going down at 0.5 m/s.)  A
          reroll may be attempted every second, but fatigue applies
          immediately.
        </p>
        <h5 class="skill" id="sk-thr">Throwing</h5>
        <p>
          The distance thrown in meters is the n5 roll doubled. E.g. a
          character with MLU of 15 and a roll of +4 throws a suitable
          object for a distance of 38 meters.
        </p>
        <h5 class="skill" id="sk-weat">Weatherlore</h5>
        <include id="$Weatherlore"/>
        <p>
          Different climate types may be specialties.  The ability to
          predict the weather.  Characters with this skill may attempt
          to predict the weather any time.  Also use the
          <em>Accuracy</em> dimension.
        </p>
        <include id="$D-Weatherlore"/>
        <h5 class="skill" id="di-yie">Yield</h5>
        <p>
          The Time dimension assumes a 12h workday, thus the apparent
          jump from 12h to 2 days.
        </p>
        <include id="$D-Yield"/>
        <h5/>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="combat">Combat</h1>
        <p>
          At the beginning of each combat the players and GM should
          jointly decide which action options they want to allow and
          which will simply be abstracted by a set penalty/bonus by
          the GM.  This can speed up combat tremendously.  If tactical
          options outside of combat are affected by the decision, the
          GM should inform the players of that.  For instance, if
          mounted combat is to tedious today, than the PCs might just
          as well dismount already to allow for smoother combat
          resolution.  The main option Melee and Missile should never
          be removed.
        </p>
        <p>
          In order to simulate larger combats with many participants,
          the usual 5-Addition can be used.  It does not provide as
          many tactical options as individual combat does, but greatly
          reduces time spent.  Both time and wound dimension should be
          scaled linearly with the number of particpipants.  E.g. a
          wound of 5 after 30 seconds would scale to a total of 50
          points after 5 minutes for 10 people or to 500 points after
          50 minutes for 100 people.  The points should be distributed
          in reasonable batches on the participants on each side, the
          smallest batch size being the wounds rolled.  People can be
          hit multiple times, but points beyond 40 generally
          don&#8217;t make sense unless explosives, catapults, or
          similar are involved.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-rest">Rest</h5>
        <p>
          Fatigue gained by any conflict recovers at one Fatigue Level
          every minute.  With dissolution, fatigue turns into injury.
          Note that spirits can take arbitrary injury before being
          destroyed and may heal forever.  Only in rare cases
          (e.g. divine intervention) can spirits be destroyed.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-move">Move</h5>
        <p>
          Use the Move skill to determine speed.  Subtract 2 from
          Missile ML for being mounted.  To avoid lengthy
          calculations, subtract 50% of the attacker speed in m/s.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-engage">Engage</h5>
        <p>
          Because the potential exists to attack/influence entities
          that come within range, each character has an <em>Engagement
          Zone</em> of 1m plus weapon length radius about his center
          (that does not extend into blocked areas).  The Engagement
          Zone of a conscious, prone character is only half that
          around his body.  This means a standing character is often
          not engaged by an adjacent prone enemy, although the prone
          character may be engaged by the standing character.
          Similarly, two adjacent prone characters often do not engage
          each other.  Unconscious characters have no Engagement Zones
          (not even the space their own body occupies) but may
          constitute obstacles.  A character may be (melee) attacked
          upon entering an enemy&#8217;s Engagement Zone until he
          leaves that zone.  This entering or leaving may be active or
          passive.  It is possible to be engaged with an arbitrary
          number of enemies at a time.  A character with a long reach
          weapon has an appropriately larger engagement zone and may
          therefore be eligible to attack before others.  This may be
          of importance for mounted Charges into a row of Pikemen.
          Also note the restriction on using long weapons at short
          range.  If combat extends into the third dimension, assume
          the volumetric &#8220;center&#8221; of a character to be a
          1m vertical line centered on their true center (when
          upright).  Horses have a two meter long horizontal line
          (when upright) centered on their true center.  More bizarre
          creatures may have more bizarre engagement zones, even when
          not fighting in three dimensions.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-charge">Charge</h5>
        <p>
          Requiring a steed to halt may imply multiple attacks due to
          deceleration restrictions.  Every engagement along the way
          may attack the steed/rider as usual.  If the intent is to
          cause little damage, use the unintentional hit rules for
          melee (see below).  Otherwise consider the group passed by
          to be the target and scale as per wild result in the missile
          attack section.  Instead of the 60 degrees +/-2 distance,
          collect all in the path of 5 feet width.  Any attacker
          plunging into defenders with an attack will decelerate at
          maximum rate, and that automatically determines the length
          of the path and the duration of the ride.  At the riders
          discretion this can be broken down into separate attacks.  A
          forced deceleration beyond what is normally allowed results
          in a fall impact for the rider and steed as from height
          equal to the forced decelaration minus the maximum allowed
          deceleration.  E.g. 10 m/s end speed with a possible allowed
          decelaration of 3 m/s equals a fall from 7 m.  Note that the
          fall impact also applies the targets fallen into.  This is
          the charge bonus, where the deceleration is not deducted.
          For opportunistic melee attacks, this is also a direct
          penalty to the Dodge skill.  A rider is not forced to halt
          his steed, but it usually requires a riding maneuver to not
          cause the steed to halt on its own, fire or similar
          incentives notwithstanding.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-push">Push</h5>
        <p>
          The push attempt must be in the direction the attacker is
          facing and the attacker must follow.  The defender has a
          choice to evade into a semi-circle of up to 120 degrees,
          assuming no obstacles.  Instead of Injury points, the number
          of meters pushed are used.  The defender is forced to deduct
          the move from his action allowance, regardless of whether he
          resists or not.  A resist deducts from the distance forced
          and can even be used as a counter-push.  The pushed
          character may opt to fall prone instead at any time, for
          instance to avoid falling of a cliff.  Any remaing distance
          is forfeit.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-rise">Rise</h5>
        <p>
          <b>Rise:</b> Use Acrobatics skill.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-grope">Grope</h5>
        <p>
          <b>Grope:</b> Use Dexterity skill.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-melee">Melee Attack</h5>
        <p>
          The rider and horse may act in unison and add their combat
          skill per 5-Addition.  Both accrue the same fatigue.
          Hitting the wrong target can happen in melee combat.
          Usually this is ignored, but if this ignorance is taken into
          account (out-world) when deciding on options, such accidents
          shall be played out.  Anybody within the range of the weapon
          is subject to a skill roll with MLU 0. This can be added to
          the benefit of other attackers as per multiple attacks above
          or resolved individually with the goal of 0 damage.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-missile">Missile Attack</h5>
        <p>
          For throwing arbitrary objects, use Throwing skill.  Since
          missile attacks are resolved with individual shots, a missed
          attack is applied only if the intended attack had no impact.
          Count all potential targets completely in an arc of 30
          degrees and +/-2 range levels of the intended target.  Use
          5-Addition of zeroes, but reduce by 5 for the missed,
          intended opponent.  If a hit is scored on the much larger
          &#8220;super-target&#8221;, roll which individual target is
          hit by distributing evenly among all the unintended targets.
          When determining hit chances and damage apply the size
          modifier from the Size table below.  At GM discretion,
          inanimate objects not participating in the skirmish may be
          counted as potential targets, particularly, if the actual
          targets are spread widely across the area.  This increases
          can be used purposefully and can be quite devastating when
          firing at advancing troops. The Missile Attack table below
          reduces calculation for playability.  Penetrating hits are
          ignored, i.e. no shots through multiple targets.  The
          assumed skills rolls all use 0 damage and MLU of 0.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-grapple">Grapple/Tangle Attack Defense</h5>
        <p>
          Use Unarmed Combat skill when no weapon is involved.  The
          basic radius of the two characters engaged is 5-added.
          Multiple Grapples are allowed , but keep track of the
          grappled weapons of all opponents, they can no longer be
          used to full potential.  Also observe any secondary
          considerations for odd Grapple attempts, e.g. grappling a
          horse&#8217;s hind leg.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-block">Block/Dodge</h5>
        <p>
          For dodging, use Dodge skill.  Dodge and Block/Parry are
          added through 5-Addition, if used together.  Dodge/parry is
          mostly used at the same time an attack is contemplated by
          the defender himself.  To ease calculation, only every
          defense beyond one attacker causes a -5 penalty in the next
          10 seconds. E.g., the first attacker is defended at full
          MLU, the second at MLU-5 and the third is at MLU-10 and sone
          on.  Note that that this is in addition to potential
          5-addition of potential attackers&#8217; MLU.  If attackers
          coordinate in this manner, the defense MLU is not 5-added,
          but the penalty is averaged.  Also note that Dodge is at -5
          for high velocity missile attacks.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-steed">Steed Trample</h5>
        <p>
          <b>Steed Trample:</b> Use steed ML (and penalties) only.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-polearm">Polearm Defense</h5>
        <p>
          Remember the Reach of Long weapons.  Usually Steed Stumble
          Roll, followed by an Unhorsing Roll is necessary to continue
          a Charge into polearms (assuming the Steed Command Check was
          successful).
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-esoteric">Esoteric Attack/Defense, Dropping Items, Ignore, Mount/Dismount, Mounted Move</h5>
        <p>
          No further out-world explanation is necessary.  If useful,
          subactions here and elsewhere can be extracted that should
          become possible during a specific out-world handling of
          combat.  Rewrite the rules here to accomodate this.  The
          missing tactical option is compensated by an appropriate
          penalty/bonus if the action is still taken in-world.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-aim">Aiming</h5>
        <p>
          The Attacker may declare one Main area as not being hit for
          a penalty of 1 to MLU.  This choice can be taken multiple
          times, but the remaining Main locations must remain (bodily)
          connected.  If all but one Main location has been
          eliminated, individual percentage points may be reduced for
          a Detail area.  This penalty can again be taken multiple
          times but the remaining Detail hit locations must be
          (bodily) connected.  The GM may restrict or penalize the
          choice of Aiming Zone if the attacker could only reach
          certain target zones with the declared attack weapon.  A
          prone attacker would find it difficult to aim high on a
          standing opponent with a melee weapon.  The Size table can
          be used, if the target is smaller than man-sized.  This
          effect does not cummulate with aiming for parts of a target
          (the main part of this paragraph).  There is no modification
          for man-sized creatures, unless the target offers a smaller
          effective target, but it may be combined with unintentional
          hitting (see above).  A prone man, for example, presents a
          target about 2 feet tall, and a crouching man about 4 feet
          tall.  Similar height adjustments may apply to other targets
          at GM discretion.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-prone">Prone</h5>
        <p>
          A character who is attacking (or being attacked by) a prone
          enemy increases Attack/Defense MLU with that character by 4.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-stop">Stop</h5>
        <p>
          A stop from a sprint/charge faster than the maximum natural
          deceleration rate may be necessary.  (Running into a wall or
          head on into another opponent that doesn&#8217;t dodge.)  In
          that case consider the distance that is not available to
          stopping as fall.  Surface is considered at 30&#176;.  This
          damage is taken by the steed (or the runner).  An
          appropriate strike location should be chosen.  If the
          obstacle is reasonably capable of taking damage apply it
          there too.  (If desired, use physics of an inelastic
          collision, i.e. when running into a wagon that starts to
          roll when run into.  Damage always applies to both parties
          of a collision.) Also see Charge.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-close">Close Mode</h5>
        <p>
          Subtract 1 for each significant impediment reaching into an
          engagement zone in the direction of the two enemies.  For
          Multiple impediments only choose the greater intrusion.  A
          blanket counts as significant, as does a wooden beam.  A
          feather bush does not.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-fumble">Fumble</h5>
        <p>
          Any new wound of at least 1 point to arms results in a
          Fumble chance.  Use accumulated damage to that extremity and
          fatigue as difficulty for a Dexterity skill roll against 0.
          Failure results in dropping anything held on that arm.  If
          something is held in both hands, 5-add the difficulties and
          the two Dexterity EMLUs.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-stumble">Stumble</h5>
        <p>
          Any new wound of at least 1 point to legs results in a
          stumble chance.  Use accumulated damage to that extremity
          and fatigue as difficulty for an Agility skill roll against
          0.  Failure results in dropping prone. Each additional leg
          after the first can be 5-added.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-shock">Shock</h5>
        <p>
          Any new wound of at least 1 point results in a Shock chance.
          Use accumulated injury and fatigue as difficulty for a
          Stamina skill roll against 0.  Failure results in
          unconsciousness for a time indiciated in the Shock table.
          Unconscious people cannot eat and drink.  Someone in Shock
          for more than 10 days will likely never wake up again.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-rest">Inanimate Damage</h5>
        <p>
          Instead of (autonomous) Healing, Repair must be applied
          externally.  Use the appropriate Craft skill instead of
          Physician.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-rest">Weapon/Armor Damage</h5>
        <p>
          Weapon and Armor make a Shock roll for the damage that they
          absorb, respectively deal.  Weapon Quality (WQ) is used
          instead of Stamina skill and damage is not accumulated.
          Armor works the same way, but the instead if Stamina, sum up
          BEPF.  Failure means a weapon or armor breaks, which may
          potentially be repaired as above. (Regular maintenance is
          assumed, otherwise accumlate 1 point per "unrepaired wound"
          for weapons and armor for the purpose of Shock rolls.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-blooodloss">Bloodloss</h5>
        <p>
          Damage taken increases with every complete multiple of 5
          injury level above 6 every 10s.  For example, a 16-20 point
          injury causes 2 points per 10 seconds, or 1 point of
          bloodloss every 5 seconds.  At GM discretion some wounds
          will not cause bloodloss (e.g. Frost) including to inanimate
          objects or reduced damage, e.g. blunt trauma.
        </p>
        <h5/>
        <p style="text-align:center">
          Missile Attack Table
        </p>
        <include id="$Combat-MA"/>
        <p style="text-align:center">
          Size Table
        </p>
        <include id="$Combat-Size"/>
        <p style="text-align:center">
          Fall Table
        </p>
        <include id="$Combat-Fall"/>
        <p style="text-align:center">
          Shock Table
        </p>
        <include id="$Combat-Shock"/>
        <p>
          Any ML additions that are multiples of 10 need to be
          downgraded to 40% as MLU modifier and multiples of 5 are
          downgraded to 60%.  Otherwise the combat charts are used as
          written.
        </p>
        <p>
          Strike location is important for two main reasons.  First,
          only the armour worn at the location struck is relevant.
          Second, injury effects vary by location; a blow to the skull
          is more serious than a blow to the foot.  The percentages
          allocated to body parts do not reflect the relative size of
          that part, since the head, arms, or groin are favored
          targets.  Combatants can influence Strike Location by
          targeting their aim.  Although combatants instinctively turn
          to face the most imminent threat, some armour only covers
          part of a strike location - a breastplate, for example, only
          covers the front of the thorax and abdomen.  In random
          situation, where it is hard to determine whether the front
          or back of a strike location is struck, experience shows
          there is a 75% chance of being struck on the front side.  An
          asterisk (*) indicates that Stumble or Fumbles may apply.
        </p>
        <include id="$Location"/>
        <h3 id="wounds">Wounds</h3>
        <p>
          Combatants who sustain Serious or Grievous wounds may die
          during the healing routine.  On the other hand, various
          types of magic, miracles, Psionics, and potions can improve
          healing.  The following wound types exist and individual
          wounds are tracked with their location.  Effects on the use
          of the corresponding part are described below.
        </p>
        <p>
          When the following text says, adjacent body parts are affected,
          effects include penalties (which are not cumulative but take
          the maximum) infection chance and bloodloss (also not cumulative
          but take the maximum).  They are not recursive, i.e. do not
          imply secondary effects.  To determine which penalty applies to
          which activity use common sense and GM discretion.
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>1-5:</em> Minor.  Wounds only have wound penalty.
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>5-10:</em> Serious. Wounds of this type also have minor
          effects on neighbouring detailed body parts at 5 points
          less.  Any activity involving these body parts are at the
          appropriate penalty.  These effect wounds do not heal
          separately.
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>11-15:</em> Grievous.  The detailed body part cannot be
          used, serious use effects on neighbouring detailed body
          parts, and minor on neighboring main parts. (This might
          only be the including main part.)  These effect wounds do not
          heal separately.  Minor effects are at 10 less than the
          Grievous, while serious are 5 less.
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>16-20:</em> Incapacitating, the main body part cannot be
          used, serious use effects on neighbouring main body parts.
          (For head this means unconsciousness and for thorax imminent
          death.)  Serious effects are at 10 less than the
          incapacitating wound itself.
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>21+:</em> Destroyed, the main body part lost its
          integrity, Grievous use effects on neighbouring main body
          parts.  (For limbs this means at least severed.  Thorax is
          split open or spinal cord severed.  For all but the
          extremities this means instant death.  For all other body
          parts, death is probably imminent due to the side effects.)
          Grievous use effects are at 10 less than the Destroyed wound
          itself.
        </p>
        <h3 id="heal-wounds">Healing</h3>
        <p>
          Any wound needs to heal its injury points.  This depends on
          Stamina; medicine may improve the healing rate.  A physician
          may attempt to find or create the correct medicine. See the
          appropriate sections.
        </p>
        <p>
          An untreated wound is considered as being treated by a
          Physician with the negative wound-level.  E.g. a wound with
          6 injury points is treated as if diagnosed by Physician with
          MLU -6.  The standard treatments mostly known by all still
          need to be applied and detailed, so a physician&#8217;s
          diagnosis is always necessary.  &#8220;Destroyed&#8221;
          wounds may be treated as incapacitating, with a Bonus on
          Diagnosis of 5.  Note that the usage effects on bordering
          regions needs to be treated as well. Overtreatment is
          possible but has no specific negative impact.
        </p>
        <include id="$Wounds"/>
        <p>
          A serious or worse wound may become infected until it turns
          into a minor wound.  An infection is a daily attack on the
          wounded area with a level of the (remaining) injury points,
          defended against with Stamina.
        </p>
        <p>
          Bloodloss is treated as a separate injury.  Note that the
          circulatory system is incapacitated with points in excess of
          15 points as other body parts are.  The circulatory system
          itself will not turn infectious.  Treatment by physicians
          depend on the location.  Some locations are incurable by
          H&#226;rnic physicians.  For multiple bleeders only take the
          maximum in the same extremity, but add those for different
          extremities.  Incapacitating and destroying wounds have no
          additional effects over the bleeder and infection dangers.
        </p>
        <p>
          Infections, diseases, toxins, and other come in various
          forms.  Bloodloss is already explained elsewhere, but
          repeated here for reference.
        </p>
        <div class="explain">
          <p>
            <em>Bloodloss</em> Once a wound in excess of 10 points is
            received, bloodloss is calculated.  (Some form of damage
            do not create bloodloss, e.g. diseases.)  This number is
            lost every 10 seconds until the treatment
            <em>Compress</em> is applied.  Thereafter these points
            heal at 1 per day.
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>Infection</em> An open wound with more than 5 injury
            points is attacked daily with MLU 0 until it has less than
            5 points or is otherwise closed. The injury points start
            with 1 and are received 1 per watch until the infection
            has run its course. The healing rate is modified by all
            running infections&#8217; points and the injury points of
            the wound in question.
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>Sleep deprivation</em> Every watch after a Stamina
            roll against -20 in hours, with a penalty of 1 per hour of
            not having slept.  For playability start rolling after 24h
            and the injury points are always 5.  The points are
            regained at the rate of 1 per hour of sleep.
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>Thirst</em> Every watch after a Stamina roll against
            -20, with a penalty of 1 for each liter of water that has
            not been drunk per day on average.  For playability start
            rolling after 3 days without water have passed.  Points
            are regained at the rate of 1 per hour.
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>Hunger</em> Every day after a Stamina roll against
            -20, with a penalty of 1 for each two pounds of food that
            have not been eaten per day on average.  For playability
            start rolling after 10 days without food have passed.
            Points are regained at the rate of 1 per hour.
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>Suffocation</em> Every minute without air a Stamina
            roll against 0 is required, with a penalty of 5 for each
            consecutive minute without air.  Points are regained at
            the rate of 1 per second once air is available again..
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="sprules">Specific Rules</h1>
        <p>
          In the course of Harn campaigns specific rules become necessary
          such that our simplifications do not defeat their purpose.
          We collect them as they come up.
        </p>
        <h3 id="Maritime Travel">Maritime Travel</h3>
        <p>
          Steady Wind (2) is optimal, for (1) and (3) half the speed
          and for (0) and (4) halve it again.  Effects on hazards are
          not covered yet.  The table below gives leagues per watch or
          km/h.
        </p>
        <include id="$Maritime-Travel"/>
        <p style="text-align:center">
          Maritime Travel Table
        </p>
        <p>
          Oar movement is full at calm (0) wind, reduced by 25% for light (1)
          and 50% for steady (2) wind.  No rowing is possible in stronger
          wind conditions.  Rowing and Sailing may not be combined during a
          watch.
        </p>
        <include id="$Maritime-Travel-Oar"/>
        <p style="text-align:center">
          Maritime Oar Travel Table
        </p>
        <h3 id="Treasure20">Treasure 20</h3>
        <h4 id="Horn of Kergis">Horn of Kergis</h4>
        <p>
          Roll WILU + n5 against 10. Every time the horn is blown,
          roll p5. If 0, there is no charge left.
        </p>
        <h3 id="Naveh6">Naveh 6</h3>
        <h4 id="Gekrish's Song">Gekrish's Song</h4>
        <p>
          After a short chant of 10 seconds, caster makes an active p5
          roll adding RSUI, which anyone hearing must roll WILU + p5
          or flee until he is no longer aware of the caster's location
          and he has broken morale.
        </p>
        <h3 id="Psionics8">Psionics 8</h3>
        <h4 id="Telepathy">Telepathy</h4>
        <p>
          The talent has three dimensions: Range, Duration, and Language.
          The range is determined to reach the target and the other dimensions
          (trajectory) may be chosen by the user.  The range is MLU in kilometers,
          and the duration is 30 seconds, halved or doubled for every 20 levels
          difference.  Language is the effectiveness a concept can be shared.  It
          is capped by a combined skill roll in a common language, if the recipient
          is willing. Otherwise it is capped by individual skill rolls.
        </p>
      </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</html>
