<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="main.xsl"?>
<html>
  <head>
    <title>RPG Rules</title>
    <meta charset="UTF-8" />
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="https://fonts.googleapis.com/css?family=Merriweather"/>
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="main.css"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <div class="main">
      <div class="title">RPG Rules</div>
      
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="motiv">Motivation</h1>
        <p>
          At first I was tempted to start a philosophical debate about
          RPG rules in general and a justification of my attempt
          specifically.  But this would soon turn out to take up more
          space than the entire rules to be presented.  So this
          discussion must be provided elsewhere.  Suffice it to say
          that my disinfatuation with current rules available stems
          from the fact that they are overly complicated for the
          little "fitness" they show for representing the genre or
          game world they supposedly apply to.
        </p>
        <p>
          Two major issues that annoy in particular I want to address
          shortly in the next two section.
        </p>
        <h3 id="scale">Scalability</h3>
        <p>
          One of the technical flaws of almost every single set of
          rules I have come across is the applicability of skills and
          difficulties as they progress.  With this rule set, higher
          skill levels compare to higher difficulty level exactly as
          lower skills and lower difficulty level.  At every
          <em>level</em> the rules yield the same probability.
        </p>
        <p>
          One consequence of this, as it turns out, is that using
          rules for multiple actors or multiple targets happens
          (<em>scales</em>) smoothly.  There are no odd jumps in
          probabilities when rules are applied to groups nor is there
          a need for a new type of rule.  Thus separate rules that
          apply to massive or complex (<em>large scale</em>)
          situations are not necessary.
        </p>
        <h3 id="dim">Dimensions</h3>
        <p>
          Many rule sets complicate situations, especially combat,
          because they address the complexity of tactical decisions by
          creating artificial dimensions.  Strength, Combat skills and
          Hit points are the dominating techical terms.  This
          unnecessary creation of dimensions should be avoided.
          Tactical decisions should only be applied to comprehensive
          dimensions, which directly relate to the <em>reality</em>
          modelled.  This is done here in the hope that both
          simplicity and <em>realism</em> can be fostered at the same
          time.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="basic">Basic Rule</h1>
        <p>
          You roll a <d5/> until you roll a <n1/> and the count the
          number of dice that did not show up a <n1/>.  That is the
          same as the number of dice you actually rolled minus one.
          The higher you get, the better, therefore we call it the
          <em>positive</em> roll.  This roll is dominated by the
          active character, or more generally, the actor.  Of course,
          there is a <em>negative</em> roll that is associated with
          the passive resistance or impediment, which is handled in
          the same way.  These two numbers are subtracted.  The result
          will be a whole number (i.e. a positive or negative number
          without fractional part).  An understanding of this rule is
          crucial, so we elaborate a bit by listing the probabilities
          involved as well as some examples.
        </p>
        <h3 id="prob">Probabilities</h3>
        <p>
          The first row shows the result achieved when you roll.  The
          second row shows the chance that you have of moving up one
          point (i.e. left) at any given point.  Note that this chance
          is always the same.  Then third row gives the percentage
          chance that you have of achieving the result in the
          corresponding first row.  These you could achieve by rolling
          a <d100/> in order to cut down on the number of dice to
          roll.  All but the first column of this row are
          approximations.
        </p>
        <p>
          The last column is somewhat special.  It combines all higher
          results.  You could expand the table to infinity, if you
          wanted.  While the extensions of the first and second row
          are quite obvious, the third is not.  It should be
          interpreted thus: if you roll 91-100, you need to roll again
          on this table, get the result as before and then add 10 to
          the result.  (For the mathematically inclined, this is a
          <em>recursive</em> definition, since it is possible that you
          roll 91-100 again, which forces you to roll on this table
          again and add 20 to the net result from the repeated
          application.  We will see this in the examples.)
        </p>
        <table>
          <caption>Table 1</caption>
          <tr>
            <th>0</th><th>1</th><th>2</th><th>3</th>
            <th>4</th><th>5</th><th>6</th><th>7</th>
            <th>8</th><th>9</th><th>...</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>...</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>01-20</td><td>21-36</td><td>37-49</td><td>50-60</td>
            <td>61-68</td><td>69-74</td><td>75-80</td><td>81-84</td><td>85-87</td>
            <td>88-90</td><td>91-100</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          The previous table only considered one roll, the positive or
          the negative roll.  (You can also call them the active and
          the passive roll; in most instances the obstacle is passive,
          such as door being lock-picked or a weight being lifted.)
          The following table shows the chances for overall results.
          Generally, this table is interpreted as the one above, with
          a few key differences.
        </p>
        <p>
          With a roll of 01-06 and 95-100 the extended roll is
          continued on the previous table with the obvious
          consequences.  Positive continuation is correct, while
          negative continuation results in negative results to be
          added.  The second row cell below the 0 result means 4/9
          chance to increase the result by 1, the same chance to
          descrease the result by one and a 1/9 to stay at 0.  The
          astute reader will see the chance for 0 in the third row is
          only 8%, while 1/9 ~ 11%.  Again this is due to rounding;
          the price for rolling less dice.
        </p>
        <table>
          <caption>Table 2</caption>
          <tr>
            <th>...</th><th>-9</th><th>-8</th>
            <th>-7</th><th>-6</th><th>-5</th>
            <th>-4</th><th>-3</th><th>-2</th>
            <th>-1</th><th>0</th><th>1</th>
            <th>2</th><th>3</th><th>4</th>
            <th>5</th><th>6</th><th>7</th>
            <th>8</th><th>9</th><th>...</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>...</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>44%/44%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>...</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>01-06</td><td>07-08</td><td>09-10</td><td>11-12</td>
            <td>13-15</td><td>16-19</td><td>20-24</td><td>25-30</td>
            <td>31-37</td><td>38-46</td><td>47-54</td><td>55-63</td>
            <td>64-70</td><td>71-76</td><td>77-81</td><td>82-85</td>
            <td>86-88</td><td>89-90</td><td>91-92</td><td>93-94</td>
            <td>95-100</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          In order to keep the probabilities correct, all rolls should
          be made in secret and the result only be exposed when
          necessary.  In many situtations this is highly impractical,
          you therefore need to decide, when to sacrifice correctness
          for playability.  We will see in later sections examples of
          this.  But it should be obvious that a player will rather
          break of a long lasting activity when he knows it will not
          end well.  Think of a race, where everyone knows the
          probable outcome after a few meters have been run.
        </p>
        <p>
          In case a more precise outcome needs to be rolled, roll a
          <d10/> for as many digits after the decimal point as needed.
        </p>
        <h3 id="prob_ex">Examples</h3>
        <p>
          The most generic way to roll the dice would be to roll <d5/>
          until a <n1/> is rolled.  To improve speed, several <d10/>
          may be rolled in ordered fashion.  Order them according to
          size or alphabetical color (e.g. black, blue, green, yellow)
          or in any other way you can remember.  With a <d10/> stop at
          <n1/> or <n2/>.  If you lack <d5/>s, you can also roll
          <d6/>s with only a marginal 3% error on each roll.  But all
          players (and GM) should roll the same type dice.  Computer
          applications that make rolling as easy as pressing a button
          are also easy to program.
        </p>
        <p>
          <ul>
            <li>
              Assume you decided to use <d100/> and rolled a
              <em>24</em> on the first roll.  This means a result of
              <n1/>.  The second roll (the negative or passive roll)
              shows a <em>50</em>, which results in <n3/> for a net
              result of <em>-2</em>.
            </li>
            <li>
              Another decision is to use the combined table, and a
              <em>28</em> is rolled, which results in -<n3/>.
            </li>
            <li>
              A more exotic roll would be the sequence <em>96, 99, 93,
              61</em> on the <d100/>.  The result would be
              <em>34</em>.
            </li>
            <li>
              Using the standard method, the positive sequence on a
              <d10/> shows <em>3, 8, 10, 7, 9, 4, 6, 3, 10, 10, 8, 4,
              2</em> and the negative sequence shows <em>3, 6, 9, 4,
              4, 1</em>.  The result is positive <em>12</em> and
              negative <em>5</em> with a net result of <em>+7</em>.
            </li>
            <li>
              If you decide that <em>+7</em> is not precise enough, a
              roll of <n3/> and <n5/> on a <d10/> (each) gives are
              finer result of <em>+7.35</em>.
            </li>
          </ul>
        </p>
        <h3 id="adv">Advantages</h3>
        <p>
          This basic rule has several advantages over other rules that
          are proposed in other systems.  In no particular order:
          <ul>
            <li>
              Active and passive are symmetrical.  If you imagine one
              character stealthily evading another, the first may
              interprete the rolls as his actively evading against a
              passive observation of the surroundings, while the
              second may interprete the rolls as his actively
              scrutinzing the vicinity against a passively hiding
              opponent.  Either way, one roll (or set of rolls) will
              determine the outcome.
            </li>
            <li>
              Scaling with respect to difficulty.  Imagine that one
              character is particularly strong with a certain skill,
              but he also attempts more difficult tasks.  Imagine the
              child character climbing the neighborhood tree and as a
              grown, experienced man climbing an overhanging cliff.
              The child's climbing bonus of <em>12</em> against a
              difficulty addition of <em>14</em> for the tree gives
              the same <em>distribution</em> as the adult's bonus of
              <em>57</em> against the cliff's <em>59</em>.  (We have
              not made any rules on skills and difficulties yet, but
              the will turn out to be additions and subtractions from
              the levels.)
            </li>
          </ul>
        </p>
        <h3 id="design">Design Guideline</h3>
        <p>
          When designing the concrete implementations of skills,
          difficulties, situations, etc. keep in mind one of the key
          probability of the basic rule.  And that is <em>a result of
          10 or higher has appoximately a 5% chance</em>.  For a
          positive/active roll alone this is at about 10%.  So when
          designing additions/subtractions consider that when
          comparing numbers directly, say skills in a duel, a <n0/>
          will only break even (or win) against a <n10/> in 5% of all
          cases.
        </p>
        <p>
          In the upcoming paragraphs, we will use this to create a
          <em>level</em> system.  Assuming a <em>level</em> for every
          10 point difference gives a good scale.  Passing a level of
          <n10/> higher is not impossible but improbable.
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>Skills</em> (or <em>Attributes</em>, etc.) should be
          designed as to properly apply to genre-typical situations
          and <em>tests</em>.  Whether generic skills and attributes
          or stylized, specific skills are used, depends on the genre.
          Such specialized application is not of importance at this
          stage.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="extended">Extended Rules</h1>
        <p>
          The following sections deal with application of the
          previously explained <em>basic rule</em>.  Many situations
          can be ruled according to the same principles, regardless of
          the specific genre-rule.
        </p>
        <h3 id="dimscale">Scales &#038; Dimensions</h3>
        <p>
          Skill tests may succeed completely, partially, or not at
          all.  It may take more or less time to complete a task.
          Actions or tasks are therefore split into several
          appropriate dimensions, such that an action can succeed or
          fail in each dimension separately.  The sense of introducing
          dimensions into the rules is to give tactical control to the
          actor/character.  Sometimes a wall needs to be torn down, no
          matter how long it takes.  Sometimes only a certain amount
          of digging can be done before it is interrupted.  A very
          important choice is that of the right dimensions.  A
          predominate dimension applicable to many tasks is
          <em>time</em>.
        </p>
        <p>
          You should always try to create <em>scalable</em> dimensions
          and this is generally not hard.  Time, distance, and weight
          are classic examples of such dimensions, But also skills
          such as knowledge can be made scalable.
        </p>
        <p>
          Once you have decided on some effects for a scalable
          dimension, you will have a list like <em>skill 0: 1 minute,
          skill 10: 2 minutes, ...</em>.  The skill level will be in
          steps of 10 (remember the design guidelines), while the
          values depend on the dimension and the concrete skill.  The
          above may be a skill of <em>Holding Breath</em>, but for a
          skill called <em>Ten-Second-Dash</em> the list may look like
          <em>skill 0: 30 meters, skill 40: 100 meters</em>.  To have
          the appropriate intermediate steps, both in skill level and
          dimension, use the following table.  On the far left and
          right side you will find the typical values for skill level
          <em>n</em> and <em>n+10</em> in inceasing fashion.  By
          reading from righht to left you can easily accommodate for
          descreasing values.  Use the next to lowest row for that.
        </p>
        <p>
          Finally, this is a <em>utility</em> table.  Often, the
          instinctive <em>linear interpolation</em> - dividing the
          difference into equal steps and taking the appropriate step
          - is not to far from the <em>smoother</em> version the table
          gives you.
        </p>
        <table>
          <caption>Table 3</caption>
          <tr>
            <th>0</th><th>1</th><th>2</th><th>3</th>
            <th>4</th><th>5</th><th>6</th><th>7</th>
            <th>8</th><th>9</th><th>10</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>10</th><td>11</td><td>11</td><td>12</td>
            <td>13</td><td>14</td><td>15</td><td>16</td>
            <td>17</td><td>19</td><th>20</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>10</th><td>11</td><td>12</td><td>14</td>
            <td>16</td><td>17</td><td>19</td><td>22</td>
            <td>24</td><td>27</td><th>30</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>10</th><td>12</td><td>14</td><td>17</td>
            <td>20</td><td>24</td><td>29</td><td>35</td>
            <td>42</td><td>50</td><th>60</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>10</th><td>13</td><td>16</td><td>20</td>
            <td>25</td><td>32</td><td>40</td><td>50</td>
            <td>63</td><td>79</td><th>100</th>
          </tr>
          <tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="11"></th></tr><tr></tr>
          <tr>
            <th>20</th><td>21</td><td>22</td><td>23</td>
            <td>24</td><td>24</td><td>26</td><td>27</td>
            <td>28</td><td>29</td><th>30</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>20</th><td>22</td><td>25</td><td>28</td>
            <td>31</td><td>35</td><td>39</td><td>43</td>
            <td>48</td><td>54</td><th>60</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>20</th><td>23</td><td>28</td><td>32</td>
            <td>38</td><td>45</td><td>53</td><td>62</td>
            <td>72</td><td>85</td><th>100</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>20</th><td>25</td><td>32</td><td>40</td>
            <td>50</td><td>63</td><td>80</td><td>100</td>
            <td>130</td><td>160</td><th>200</th>
          </tr>
          <tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="11"></th></tr><tr></tr>
          <tr>
            <th>30</th><td>32</td><td>34</td><td>37</td>
            <td>40</td><td>42</td><td>45</td><td>49</td>
            <td>52</td><td>56</td><th>60</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>30</th><td>34</td><td>38</td><td>43</td>
            <td>49</td><td>55</td><td>62</td><td>70</td>
            <td>79</td><td>89</td><th>100</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>30</th><td>36</td><td>44</td><td>53</td>
            <td>64</td><td>77</td><td>94</td><td>110</td>
            <td>140</td><td>170</td><th>200</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>30</th><td>38</td><td>48</td><td>60</td>
            <td>75</td><td>95</td><td>120</td><td>150</td>
            <td>190</td><td>240</td><th>300</th>
          </tr>
          <tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="11"></th></tr><tr></tr>
          <tr>
            <th>60</th><td>63</td><td>66</td><td>70</td>
            <td>74</td><td>77</td><td>82</td><td>86</td>
            <td>90</td><td>95</td><th>100</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>60</th><td>68</td><td>76</td><td>86</td>
            <td>97</td><td>110</td><td>120</td><td>140</td>
            <td>160</td><td>180</td><th>200</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>60</th><td>70</td><td>83</td><td>97</td>
            <td>110</td><td>130</td><td>160</td><td>190</td>
            <td>220</td><td>260</td><th>300</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>60</th><td>76</td><td>95</td><td>120</td>
            <td>150</td><td>190</td><td>240</td><td>300</td>
            <td>380</td><td>480</td><th>600</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>10</th><th>9</th><th>8</th><th>7</th>
            <th>6</th><th>5</th><th>4</th><th>3</th>
            <th>2</th><th>1</th><th>0</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>&#945;</th>
            <td><font size="-1">&#945;(<math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mtext>&#946;</mtext><mtext>&#945;</mtext></mfrac></math>)<sup>0.1</sup></font></td>
            <td><font size="-1">&#945;(<math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mtext>&#946;</mtext><mtext>&#945;</mtext></mfrac></math>)<sup>0.2</sup></font></td>
            <td><font size="-1">&#945;(<math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mtext>&#946;</mtext><mtext>&#945;</mtext></mfrac></math>)<sup>0.3</sup></font></td>
            <td><font size="-1">&#945;(<math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mtext>&#946;</mtext><mtext>&#945;</mtext></mfrac></math>)<sup>0.4</sup></font></td>
            <td><font size="-1">&#945;(<math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mtext>&#946;</mtext><mtext>&#945;</mtext></mfrac></math>)<sup>0.5</sup></font></td>
            <td><font size="-1">&#945;(<math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mtext>&#946;</mtext><mtext>&#945;</mtext></mfrac></math>)<sup>0.6</sup></font></td>
            <td><font size="-1">&#945;(<math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mtext>&#946;</mtext><mtext>&#945;</mtext></mfrac></math>)<sup>0.7</sup></font></td>
            <td><font size="-1">&#945;(<math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mtext>&#946;</mtext><mtext>&#945;</mtext></mfrac></math>)<sup>0.8</sup></font></td>
            <td><font size="-1">&#945;(<math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mfrac><mtext>&#946;</mtext><mtext>&#945;</mtext></mfrac></math>)<sup>0.9</sup></font></td>
            <th>&#946;</th>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          The numbers in the table have been rounded.  If you want to
          expand the table for other differences or mitigate rounding
          errors and you are willing to go through the mathematics of
          it, the formula in the last row can be used.  (The variable
          &#945; being the left and &#946; the right end.)
        </p>
        <h3 id="combo">Combinations</h3>
        <p>
          The following rule only applies when you deem it prudent.
          It combines several actors into one and that only makes
          sense, if resolving the situation takes less time than
          rolling them individually.
        </p>
        <p>
          Sometimes several people (or more generally <em>actors</em>)
          will want to join forces to expedite an action.  Jointly
          lifting a weight or looking for a clue are typical examples.
          This should be simulated by combining the joining people
          into one actor with an increased bonus to the activities.
          The same is true for attempting several tasks in one
          activity, where rolling many dice would become combersome.
          Attempting to clear away rubble instead of individual stones
          and broken items could be such a situation.
        </p>
        <p>
          First decide what the bonus would be, if two characters with
          the same skill level combine their effort into one.  Then
          the following table provides a way to combine two general
          actors into one.  Take the difference in bonus (<em>skill
          level</em>) as column index and the bonus an equal skill
          should give as row index.  Cross-indexing gives the bonus,
          the actor with the higher skill level should receive.
        </p>
        <table>
          <caption>Table 4</caption>
          <tr>
            <th>0</th><th>1</th><th>2</th><th>3</th>
            <th>4</th><th>5</th><th>6</th><th>7</th>
            <th>8</th><th>9</th><th>10</th><th>&#946;</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>1</th><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td>
            <td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td>
            <td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>...</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>2</th><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>0</td>
            <td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td>
            <td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>...</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>3</th><td>2</td><td>2</td><td>1</td>
            <td>1</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>0</td>
            <td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>...</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>4</th><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>2</td>
            <td>2</td><td>2</td><td>1</td><td>1</td>
            <td>1</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>...</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>5</th><td>4</td><td>4</td><td>3</td>
            <td>3</td><td>2</td><td>2</td><td>2</td>
            <td>2</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>...</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>6</th><td>5</td><td>5</td><td>4</td>
            <td>4</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>3</td>
            <td>2</td><td>2</td><td>2</td><td>...</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>7</th><td>6</td><td>6</td><td>5</td>
            <td>5</td><td>4</td><td>4</td><td>4</td>
            <td>3</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>...</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>8</th><td>7</td><td>7</td><td>6</td>
            <td>6</td><td>5</td><td>5</td><td>5</td>
            <td>4</td><td>4</td><td>4</td><td>...</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>9</th><td>8</td><td>8</td><td>7</td>
            <td>7</td><td>6</td><td>6</td><td>5</td>
            <td>5</td><td>5</td><td>4</td><td>...</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>10</th><td>9</td><td>9</td><td>8</td>
            <td>8</td><td>7</td><td>7</td><td>6</td>
            <td>6</td><td>6</td><td>5</td><td>...</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>&#945;</th><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td>
            <td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td>
            <td>...</td>
            <td colspan="3"><em>&#945;ln(1+e<sup>-&#946;ln(2)/&#945;</sup>)/ln(2)</em></td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          For example, assume the bonus would be a full <n10/> for
          equal characters, but the better character is <n5/> points
          ahead on the skill.  Then this table gives the skill of the
          better character plus <n7/> to the combined actor.
        </p>
        <p>
          The standard example of taking the best skill roll of two
          (this is the same as requiring at least one of the two to
          succeed.)  would best equate to using row <n5/> in the
          table.  If you have two actors that both must succeed a
          test, then you should use -<n5/>, which is equivalent to
          using the fifth row for the <em>reverse</em> roll.  Keep in
          mind that the reversal of <em>positive</em> and
          <em>negative</em> roll, also changes who of the two has the
          higher skill level.
        </p>
        <p>
          The rule can be applied multiple times and its application
          does not depend on the order or sub-grouping of several
          actors, thereby adhering to the outline given in the
          motivational section.  In order to keep this rule simple,
          the results were rounded.  Using the rule multiple times,
          always group two actors of similar skill value together.
	</p>
	<p>
          As a more elaborate example, say you have four characters in
          a room searching for something and you have determined that
          this technically means that either of those characters could
          find it, i.e. all would have to roll against a set
          diffculty.  But you want just one roll.  These characters
          have a skill level of <n5/>, <n7/>, <em>13</em>, and
          <em>17</em>.  Taking the first two, because they are closest
          to each other, we combine them into an actor with <n11/>.
          (The difference between the two is <n2/> and from the above
          we know that we should use row five.  We add the <n4/> we
          find to the higher <n7/>.) Now we combine <n11/> and
          <em>13</em> in the same manner to <em>17</em>.  In the last
          step, we combine the two <em>17</em>s into a <em>22</em> by
          way of the zero'th column.
	</p>
	<p>
          If you want to expand the table for higher differences or
          mitigate rounding errors for repeated applications and you
          are willing to go through the mathematics of it, the formula
          in the last row can be used.  (The variable &#945; being the
          row index and &#946; the column index.)
        </p>
        <h3 id="abort">Abort and Control</h3>
        <p>
          The variance in outcome of an activity can be controlled by
          manipulating the scale of a dimension.  By reducing an
          active roll by <em>n</em>, the active roll can be repeated
          <em>n</em> times and the average of all (<em>n+1</em) rolls
          is taken.  This will result in a higher probability of the
          (new) average.
	</p>
	<p>
          When actions are not completed, but aborted prematurly,
          partial outcomes are possible.  This is usually a an
          interruption during the time dimension, e.g. due to
          inflicted wounds on an active person at some point.
          Consider this the equivalent of a control.  That is, if the
          abort happens, when time to completion is <em>n</em>, then
          proceed as if the active roll had been reduced by
          <em>n</em>.
        </p>
        <h3 id="combo">Pragmatics</h3>
        <p>
          The calculations result in a level difference between the
          <em>active</em> and the <em>passive</em> part, which is the
          only number relevant for rolling.  If only the failure or
          success is of interest and not the circumstances in the
          domains, you can apply the following shortcut.  Since the
          difference must be met by the lower contestant, you may roll
          all the difference dice in one combined
          &#x201c;throw&#x201d; and check, whether any stop digit
          appears.  If it does the lower contestant cannot win, since
          it is irrelevant, where the stop digit appears.  If the stop
          digit does not appear, chances have reduced to 50/50, and
          you can flip a coin in any of a number of ways.
	</p>
	<p>
          For example, suppose the active climber with a skill level
          of <em>57</em> wants to scale a cliff of difficulty
          <em>49</em>.  The difference is <n8/>.  The GM rolls <n8/>
          dice, which show up <n3/>, <n5/>, <n6/>, <n1/>, <n3/>,
          <n9/>, <n9/>, and <n8/>.  Since <n1/> is a stop digit, the
          cliff is scaled.  If the <n1/> had been a <n7/>, for
          instance, the cliff would have had a &#x201c;fighting
          chance&#x201d; to drop the character.  The GM decides that
          even is good for the character and odd is bad and rolls a
          <d10/>.  It comes up a <n6/> and the character has barely
          made it.  Any story-telling description of this close
          encounter is at your option.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="concret">Concrete Rules</h1>
        <h3 id="gf">Fantasy</h3>
        <p>
          <a class="list" href="gf.xml">&#x27a4;</a>An example of a
          simple Warhammer Fantasy conversion.  (Click on the arrow.)
        </p>
        <p>
          <a class="list" href="oper.xml">&#x27a4;</a>An example of a
          concrete Harnmaster conversion.  (Click on the arrow.)
        </p>
      </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</html>
