<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="main.xsl"?>
<html>
  <head>
    <title>RPG Rules</title>
    <meta charset="UTF-8" />
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="https://fonts.googleapis.com/css?family=Merriweather"/>
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="main.css"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <div class="main">
      <div class="title">Abstract RPG Rules</div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="Introduction">Introduction</h1>
        <p>
          In RPGs, most gameplay does not need rules.  During play,
          players will only recurr to rules in two instances:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            The gameworld is alien enough that common sense cannot be
            used to resolve a situation.  This is the case for magic
            spell casting, for instance.
          </li>
          <li>
            Players and GMs do not want to determine the outcome
            according to their common understanding but want some
            undeterministic influence, i.e. chance, to do it for them.
            This may be used to enhance tension or drama but also to
            reolve different understanding of the situation by
            different players, but they can still agree on a chance
            value.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          Additionally, common rule systems create probabilities that
          are hard to gauge.  In fact, only for playing a game for an
          extended period of time, will patterns emerge.  I find this
          fatiguing, in particular, if the probabilities do not turn
          out to match expectations and thereby impact enjoyment.
	</p>
	<p>
	  The following rules are written with these points in mind.
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            Keep out rules that explain a setting.  Let's call these
            <em>in-world</em> rules.  Rules are called
            <em>out-world</em> rules, when they apply only to players
            and/or the GM.  Sometimes the distinction is not easy, a
            matter of taste, or how willing you are to distinguish.
          </li>
          <li>
            Keep it comprehensible.  This does not mean generic
            simple, but rather that probabilities do not provide
            surprises when subject matter changes.
          </li>
        </ul>
	<p>
	  The following section contains a few reasonable assumptions
	  on rules and tries to explain, why certain rules are chosen.
	  If you are only interested in the mechanics, you can skip
	  it.
	</p>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="AddSkills">Adding Skills</h1>
        <p>
          Most rules intend to resolve skill application.  Whether it
          be fighting, hiding, finding, lifting, or something else.  A
          character can have different skill levels but tasks at hand
          can also also have different difficulty levels.  We make the
          following assumptions: A skill proficiency and a task
          difficulty can be expressed as numbers.  <strong>A skill
          level of <em>k</em> has the same chance of success for one
          task of difficulty <em>n</em> and one of difficulty
          <em>m</em>, as a skill of <em>k</em> against a single task
          of difficulty of <em>n+m</em>.</strong> The numbers <em>m,
          n, k</em> are your regular (integer) numbers.  <strong>A
          skill level of <em>k</em> has the same chance of success for
          one task of difficulty <em>n</em> as a skill of level
          <em>n</em> has of failure against a task of difficulty
          <em>k</em></strong>.  Assuming we have a failure probability of
          <em>p/2</em> for a skill of <em>1</em> for a task of
          <em>0</em>, we will restrict ourselves to <em>p=0.8</em>.
        </p>
        <p>
          The only real assumptions are set in <strong>bold</strong>.
          This is in fact all we need, because the following are
          conclusions.  This paragraph was written to show that we
          make very few, natural assumptions that already imply the
          most important rule.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="Basic">One Rule to Rule Them</h1>
        <p>
          <em>
	    You roll a d5 until you roll a 1 and then count the number
	    of dice that did not show up a 1.  That is the same as the
	    number of dice you actually rolled minus one.  The higher
	    you get, the better.  This first number is used for the
	    active character, or more generally, the actor.  It should
	    be clear in almost all situations, who is active - the one
	    with the applicable skill.  We call it the <b>positive
	    (stop) roll</b> roll, even though it is a number of rolls.
	    Of course, there is a <b>negative (stop) roll</b> that is
	    associated with the passive resistance or impediment,
	    which is handled in the same way.  That would be the task
	    in most cases.  The result of the negative stop roll
	    (which is still a positive number!) is subtracted from the
	    result of the positive.  Understanding this rule is
	    crucial, so we elaborate by listing the probabilities
	    involved as well as some examples.
	  </em>
        </p>
        <p>
          The mechanism is different from most other rules (I haven't
          found any that use it), where you will often roll either a
          pool of dice and count those that match a certain threshold
          or single die roll.
        </p>
        <p>
	  All these methods, ours included, are usually compared
	  against a threshold.  The further away from the threshold
	  you are the more extreme the results will become.  Depending
	  of the sign of the difference, the results is good or bad
	  for the actor.
        </p>
        <p>
	  The follwoing two tables are explanatory and not needed,
	  just as the Translation section.  The mechanics have been
	  described completely in the highlighted section.  Everything
	  else can be used to reduce the number of dice thrown or to
	  better understand the implication of the (stop) roll
	  mechanic.
        </p>
        <p>
          In Table 1 the first row shows the results you can achieve
          when making a positive roll.  Since you continue rolling
          until you get a 1 on your <em>d5</em>, you can interpret the
          complete positive stop roll as a series of <em>d5</em> rolls
          as you move right on the first row, starting with 0.  The
          second row shows the chance that you have of moving up one
          point (i.e. right) at any given point.  Note that this
          chance is always the same.  The third row gives the
          percentage chance that you have of achieving the result in
          the corresponding first row.  These you could achieve by
          rolling a <em>d100</em> in order to cut down on the number
          of dice to roll.  All but the first column of this row are
          approximations.
        </p>
        <p>
          The last column is somewhat special.  It combines all higher
          results.  You could expand the table to infinity, if you
          wanted.  While the extensions of the first and second row
          are quite obvious, the third is not.  It should be
          interpreted thus: if you roll 91-100, i.e. the highest 10%,
          you need to roll again on this table, get the result as
          before and then add 10 to the result.  (For the
          mathematically inclined, this is a <em>recursive</em>
          definition, since it is possible that you roll 91-100 again,
          which forces you to roll on this table again and add 20 to
          the net result from the repeated application.  We will see
          this in the examples.)  Some system have a similar mechanic
          and call it an "exploding" roll or "open-ended".
        </p>
        <table style="width:70%">
          <tr>
            <th>0</th><th>1</th><th>2</th><th>3</th>
            <th>4</th><th>5</th><th>6</th><th>7</th>
            <th>8</th><th>9</th><th>...</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>...</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>01-20</td><td>21-36</td><td>37-49</td><td>50-60</td>
            <td>61-68</td><td>69-74</td><td>75-80</td><td>81-84</td>
            <td>85-87</td><td>88-90</td><td>91-100</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          The previous table only considered one stop roll, either the
          positive or the negative.  (You can also call them the
          active and the passive (stop) roll; in most instances the
          obstacle is passive, such as door being lock-picked or a
          weight being lifted.)  The following table shows the chances
          for overall results.  Generally, the next table is
          interpreted as the one above, with only a few key
          differences.
        </p>
        <p>
          With a roll of 01-06 and 95-100 the extended roll is
          continued on the previous table with certain consequences.
          Positive continuation - the one on the right end of the
          table with 95-100 - is exactly as before, while negative
          continuation results in negative results to be added.  For
          instance, rolling 02 and then a 25 gives a result of -11.
          The second row cell below the 0 result means 4/9 chance to
          increase the result by 1, the same chance to descrease the
          result by one and a 1/9 to stay at 0.  The astute reader
          will see the chance for 0 in the third row is only 8%, while
          1/9 is approximatly 11%.  Again this is due to rounding; the
          price for rolling less dice.
        </p>
        <table style="font-size:75%;width:90%">
          <tr>
            <th>...</th><th>-9</th><th>-8</th>
            <th>-7</th><th>-6</th><th>-5</th>
            <th>-4</th><th>-3</th><th>-2</th>
            <th>-1</th><th>0</th><th>+1</th>
            <th>+2</th><th>+3</th><th>+4</th>
            <th>+5</th><th>+6</th><th>+7</th>
            <th>+8</th><th>+9</th><th>...</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>...</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>44%/44%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>...</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>01-06</td><td>07-08</td><td>09-10</td><td>11-12</td>
            <td>13-15</td><td>16-19</td><td>20-24</td><td>25-30</td>
            <td>31-37</td><td>38-46</td><td>47-54</td><td>55-63</td>
            <td>64-70</td><td>71-76</td><td>77-81</td><td>82-85</td>
            <td>86-88</td><td>89-90</td><td>91-92</td><td>93-94</td>
            <td>95-100</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          In case a more precise outcome needs to be rolled, roll a
          <em>d10</em> for as many digits after the decimal point as
          needed.
        </p>
        <h3 id="Examples">Examples</h3>
        <p>
          The most generic way to roll the dice would be to roll
          <em>d5</em> until a 1 is rolled.  To improve speed, several
          <em>d10</em>s may be rolled in ordered fashion.  Order them
          according to size or alphabetical color (e.g. black, blue,
          green, yellow) or in any other way you can remember.  With a
          <em>d10</em> stop at 1 or 2.  If you lack <em>d5</em>s, you
          can also roll <em>d6</em>s with only a marginal 3% error on
          each roll.  But all players (and GM) should roll the same
          type dice.  Computer applications that make rolling as easy
          as pressing a button are also easy to program.
        </p>
        <div class="explain">
          <p>
            Assume you decided to use <em>d100</em> and rolled a 24 on
            the first roll.  This means a result of 1 on the first table. 
            The second roll (the negative or passive roll) shows a 50, which
            results in 3 for a net result of -2.
          </p>
          <p>
            Using Table 2, a 28 is rolled, which results in -3.
          </p>
          <p>
            A more exotic roll would be the sequence 96, 99, 93, 61 on
            the <em>d100</em>.  The result would be 34 for a positive
            stop roll. For a combined stop roll, the result would be
            29 (and the roll of 61 ignored, because it is not needed,
            because the 93 already "stops" on Table 2).
          </p>
          <p>
            Using the standard method, the positive sequence on a
            <em>d10</em> shows 3, 8, 10, 7, 9, 4, 6, 3, 10, 10, 8, 4,
            2 and the negative sequence shows 3, 6, 9, 4, 4, 1.  The
            result is positive 12 and negative 5 with a net result of
            +7.
          </p>
          <p>
            If you decide that +7 is not precise enough, a roll of 3
            and 5 on a <em>d10</em> (each) gives are finer result of
            +7.35.  I.e. you simple roll the decimal places.
          </p>
        </div>
        <p>
          Remember that the second row is technically correct and the
          third row only provides less rolls.  We will look at some
          further hints for rolling.
        </p>
        <p>
          Active and passive are symmetrical.  If you imagine one
          character stealthily evading another, the first may
          interprete the rolls as his actively evading against a
          passive observation of the surroundings, while the second
          may interprete the rolls as his actively scrutinzing the
          vicinity against a passively hiding opponent.  Either way,
          one roll (or set of rolls) will determine the outcome.
        </p>
        <h3 id="Hints">Hints</h3>
        <p>
	  When describing a certain situation, the actor and the
	  obstacle both possess a ceratin <em>level</em>. The first is
	  usually a skill in the particular act and second a measure
	  of the difficulty of the task.  In the previous example, the
	  observer might have a (skill) level of 5 and finding the
	  clandestine character a (task) level of 3.  These levels
	  will be added to the positive and negative stop rolls,
	  respectively.
        </p>
        <p>
          We are adding and subtracting 4 numbers; stop rolls and
          levels.  The calculations result in a level difference
          between the active and the passive part (or the skill level
          and task level) which is relevant for rolling.  If only the
          failure or success is of interest and not the degree of
          success or failure, you can apply the following shortcut.
          Since the difference must be met by the lower level
          contestant, you may roll all the difference dice in one
          combined “throw” and check, whether any stop digit appears.
          If it does the lower contestant cannot win, since it is
          irrelevant, where the stop digit appears.  If the stop digit
          does not appear, chances have reduced to 50/50, and you can
          flip a coin in any of a number of ways.
        </p>
        <p>
          For example, suppose the active climber with a skill level
          of 57 wants to scale a cliff of difficulty level 49.  The
          difference is 8.  The GM rolls 8 dice, which show up 3, 5,
          6, 1, 3, 9, 9, and 8.  Since 1 is a stop digit, the cliff is
          scaled.  If the 1 had been a 7 instead, for instance, the
          cliff would have had a "fighting chance" to drop the
          character.  The GM decides that even is good for the
          character and odd is bad and rolls a d10.  It comes up a 6
          and the character has barely made it.  Any story-telling
          description of this close encounter is at your option.
        </p>
        <p>
          Another pragmatic rule applies to differences of at least
          10. Rolling 10 non-stop rolls in a row to match a level
          difference of 10 can be shortened to rolling a 1 on a d10.
          The chance 1/10 is an approximation of 0.1073741824, which
          is the exact chance.  In fact, the choice of d5 in the
          initial paragraph was made for the reason that this
          heuristic holds.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="Application">Applications to Existing Rules</h1>
        <p>
          Many rulesets rank a skill on a percentile scale 0% through
          100%.  This is the case for Rolemaster, Runequest, or
          Harnmaster.  Rolling below your skill value makes you
          succeed.  This approximates our levels 0, 10, 20 and 30 at
          about the classical 5%, 35%, 65%, and 95%.  That means these
          rules have about fourty skill levels, in which all values
          fall according to our rules.  The same is true for Dungeons
          and Dragons, Pathfinder, or generally the d20 group of
          rules, which use twenty 5% steps, instead of the finer
          grained 1% step.  Note that these steps are approximations,
          since none of these rolls are translation-invariant.
        </p>
        <p>
          Note that you could just multiply the d20 skill levels by
          two or take half for the precentile system, why the strange,
          non-linear mapping?  Since we do not intend to simulate
          other rules in this manner, you most certainly can do that
          conversion.  We provide the above to show that the
        </p>
        <p>
          The two-page character sheet is applicable to all rules,
          because it captures the <em>out-world</em> probabilities.
          You need to fill in the relevant skills and tasks for the
          PC.  Since the possible combinations are virtually
          limitless, list only the most common ones or add another
          sheet, if you do not find a suitable decomposition of skills
          and tasks.
        </p>
        <p>
          Most rules apply linear modifications (i.e. additions and
          subtractions) to the skill and task levels and this is what
          we do for specific rule conversions in the dedicated
          sections.
        </p>
        <p>
          All following headings are links to the corresponding
          sub-pages.
        </p>
        <h3 id="harn">
          <a href="harn.xml">Rules for Hârnworld</a>
        </h3>
        <h3 id="expanse">
          <a href="expanse.xml">Rules for Expanse</a>
        </h3>
        <h3 id="char">
          <a href="char.svg">Generic Char Sheet</a>
        </h3>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="Roaming">Roaming the Skill Space</h1>
        <p>
          The following rules address common situations. How do you
          combine a group of actors that support each other?  How do
          you apply two skills to a task that fits both?  You should
          never indiscriminately add values.  Remember that a
          difference of 10 means a 90% winning difference by design.
        </p>
        <h3 id="Combinations">Combinations</h3>
        <p>
          Taking the best skill roll of two (this is the same as
          requiring at least one of the two to succeed) can be done by
          using the table below.
        </p>
        <p>
          Say you want to add the skills <em>n</em> and <em>m</em> of
          two actors, where the respective task difficulties have
          already been subtracted. In the first row, you index the
          positive difference between <em>n</em> and <em>m</em>. The
          second row will then give you the "bonus" to add to the
          higher of the two skills - which is then the only one you
          need to roll.  Say the skills are 5 and 9.  Then the net
          skill level of the two actors together is 12.
        </p>
        <table style="width:75%">
          <tr>
            <th>Difference</th><td>0-1</td><td>2-3</td><td>4-6</td><td>7-10</td><td>11-19</td><td>20+</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Result</td><td>+5</td><td>+4</td><td>+3</td><td>+2</td><td>+1</td><td>0</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          The rule can be applied multiple times and its application
          does not depend on the order or sub-grouping of several
          actors.  In order to keep this rule simple, round results in
          your tables.  If you use the rule multiple times, always
          group two actors of similar skill levels together to reduce
          rounding errors.  (This is "normalized" skill level,
          i.e. the task level has already been subtracted.)
        </p>
        <p>
          As a more elaborate example, say you have four characters in
          a room searching for something and you have determined that
          this technically means that either of those characters could
          find it, i.e. all would have to roll against a set
          diffculty.  But you want just one roll.  These characters
          have a skill level of 5, 7, 13, and 17. Taking the first
          two, because they are closest to each other, we combine them
          into an actor with 11.  Now we combine 11 and 13 in the same
          manner to 17.  In the last step, we combine 17 and 17 into
          22.
        </p>
        <p>
	  If you have two actors that both must succeed a test, that
	  is equivalent to using the <em>reverse</em> stop roll, which
	  means exchanging the role of positive and negative for the
	  purposes of combining.  Logically this means that either
	  obstacle may foil the actor.  Keep in mind that the reversal
	  of <em>positive</em> and <em>negative</em> roll also changes
	  who of the two has the higher skill level.
        </p>
        <p>
          Imagine in the previous example that the same characters are
          trying to hide from a guard.  If one is detected, the guard
          will raise the alarm and the maneuver fails.  As luck will
          have it, their Hide skill level is exactly as their Search
          skill level.  But now it is passive: 5 and 7 will turn into
          1. 13 and 17 (closest together) will turn into 10. The
          difficulty of the skill "pairs" 1 and 10 turns into -1.
          Since the guard isn't really paying attention, the GM gives
          the guard a skill level of 0.  That leaves the group with a
          60% failure chance.
        </p>
        <p>
          If you are worried about rounding errors, use the following
          formula, where &#946; is the difference in level you plug in
          and and the addition to the higher value is calculated.
          Round when done with "addition".
        </p>
        <p style="font-weight:bold;text-align:center;">
          5 ln(1+e<sup>-&#946;ln(2)/5</sup>)/ln(2)
        </p>
        <p>
          Do not be overwhelmed by this suggestion, you will most
          likely never ever use it, since role playing is more about
          an individual's actions than a group's. And lengthy
          calculations just to be correct will reduce enjoyment. Use
          it only when players try to "break the rules" by
          misconstrued rounding and then have <em>them</em> do the
          math! Come to think of it, players never do that, so forget
          the whole suggestion.
        </p>
        <h3 id="decomp">Decomposition</h3>
        <p>
          A skill may be decomposed into other skills, if so desired.
          The decomposition must be such that the combination of
          (weighted) averages of the new skill levels results in the
          original skill level.  Additional measures should be in
          place to indicate that the skills actually belong to a
          group.  A typical restriction is that the individual skills
          of a goup may not differ by more than 10 points.
        </p>
        <p>
          If a decomposition results in multiple rolls, make sure that
          the rules of <em>Combinations</em> remain valid.  A typical
          example would be to turn a roll that would usually apply every 10 days
          into a roll that applies every day.  This implies that all
          of the daily rolls have a difficulty increased by 10.
        </p>
        <p>
          Decomposition and then combining skills is a great tool to
          extend the skill space beyond what rules generally cover.
          Imagine that a PC wants to tie a knot, but his skill sheet
          says he has level 5 as Sailor and level 3 as Mountaineer.
          For tasks like knots where the difficulty is the same for a
          Sailor and a Mountaineer, the GM can allow the PC to use a
          9. The reasoning is that the knot skill application works as
          if two separate actors were trying to tie the knot together.
          Be careful, however, with allowing such additions, because
          if you treat 0 as the value an untrained individual has,
          then in the above case a sailor that has never seen a
          mountain would still have a 0 in mountaeineering and adding
          a 0 would yield an effective knot skill of 8.
        </p>
      </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</html>
