<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="main.xsl"?>
<html>
  <head>
    <title>RPG Rules</title>
    <meta charset="UTF-8" />
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="https://fonts.googleapis.com/css?family=Merriweather"/>
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="main.css"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <div class="main">
      <div class="title">RPG Rules</div>
      
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="motiv">Motivation</h1>
        <p>
          RPG rules at large have several issues, which I want to address
          with these rules.  I do not want to go into theory - that would
          burdon the rules - suffice it to say that the rules weal with the
          <em>simulation</em> aspect of the RPG genre.
        </p>
        <h3 id="scale">Scalability</h3>
        <p>
          A technical flaw of all rules I know is that intended skill
          progression does not change in accordance with the technical
          realisation.  In other words, a skill "value" and "difficulty"
          has a different meaning than what the rule mechanics suggest.
          With this rule set, higher skill levels compare to higher
          difficulty level exactly as lower skills and lower difficulty
          level.  At every <em>level</em> the rules yield the same
          probability.
        </p>
        <p>
          One consequence of this, as it turns out, is that using
          rules for multiple actors or multiple targets happens
          (<em>scales</em>) smoothly.  There are no odd jumps in
          probabilities when rules are applied to groups nor is there
          a need for a new type of rule.  Thus separate rules that
          apply to massive or complex (<em>large scale</em>)
          situations are not necessary.
        </p>
        <h3 id="dim">Dimensions</h3>
        <p>
          Rules complicate situations, especially combat, because they
          address the complexity of tactical decisions by creating
          artificial dimensions.  Strength, Combat skills and Hit
          points are the dominating techical terms.  We avoid this
          here in the hope that both simplicity and <em>realism</em>
          can be fostered at the same time.  Dimensions will be created
          according to the skill as plausible and not as separate
          "entities".
        </p>
        <h3 id="inout">Inner and Outer Rules</h3>
        <p>
          One of the most difficult problems is differentiating between 
          rules that are observable by the members of the game world,
          such as NPCs and those only available to the players outside.
          Since these are generic rules, world-specific rules are not
          provided, but mechanisms to simulate much of a game-world are.
        </p>
        <p>
          We do not provide rules for influencing Luck or Karma, even
          though they can be made generic.  It is only the simulation part
          that concerns us here.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="basic">Basic Rule</h1>
        <p>
          You roll a <em>d5</em> until you roll a 1 and the count the
          number of dice that did not show up a 1.  That is the same
          as the number of dice you actually rolled minus one.  The
          higher you get, the better, therefore we call it the
          <em>positive</em> roll.  This roll is dominated by the
          active character, or more generally, the actor.  Of course,
          there is a <em>negative</em> roll that is associated with
          the passive resistance or impediment, which is handled in
          the same way.  These two numbers are subtracted.  The result
          will be a whole number (i.e. a positive or negative number
          without fractional part).  An understanding of this rule is
          crucial, so we elaborate by listing the probabilities
          involved as well as some examples.  If the method is intuitively
          clear, you can skip the (theretical) next section.
        </p>
        <p>
          The mechanism is different from other rules, where you will
          often roll eithe a pool of dice and count those that match a
          certain threshol or single die roll gives you better results
          the higher (lower) your roll turns out.
        </p>
        <h3 id="prob">Probabilities</h3>
        <p>
          In Table 1 the first row shows the result achieved when you roll.
          The second row shows the chance that you have of moving up one
          point (i.e. left) at any given point.  Note that this chance
          is always the same.  Then third row gives the percentage
          chance that you have of achieving the result in the
          corresponding first row.  These you could achieve by rolling
          a <em>d100</em> in order to cut down on the number of dice
          to roll.  All but the first column of this row are
          approximations.
        </p>
        <p>
          The last column is somewhat special.  It combines all higher
          results.  You could expand the table to infinity, if you
          wanted.  While the extensions of the first and second row
          are quite obvious, the third is not.  It should be
          interpreted thus: if you roll 91-100, you need to roll again
          on this table, get the result as before and then add 10 to
          the result.  (For the mathematically inclined, this is a
          <em>recursive</em> definition, since it is possible that you
          roll 91-100 again, which forces you to roll on this table
          again and add 20 to the net result from the repeated
          application.  We will see this in the examples.)
        </p>
        <table style="width:70%">
          <tr>
            <th>0</th><th>1</th><th>2</th><th>3</th>
            <th>4</th><th>5</th><th>6</th><th>7</th>
            <th>8</th><th>9</th><th>...</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>...</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>01-20</td><td>21-36</td><td>37-49</td><td>50-60</td>
            <td>61-68</td><td>69-74</td><td>75-80</td><td>81-84</td>
            <td>85-87</td><td>88-90</td><td>91-100</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          The previous table only considered one roll, the positive or
          the negative roll.  (You can also call them the active and
          the passive roll; in most instances the obstacle is passive,
          such as door being lock-picked or a weight being lifted.)
          The following table shows the chances for overall results.
          Generally, this table is interpreted as the one above, with
          a few key differences.
        </p>
        <p>
          With a roll of 01-06 and 95-100 the extended roll is
          continued on the previous table with the obvious
          consequences.  Positive continuation is correct, while
          negative continuation results in negative results to be
          added.  The second row cell below the 0 result means 4/9
          chance to increase the result by 1, the same chance to
          descrease the result by one and a 1/9 to stay at 0.  The
          astute reader will see the chance for 0 in the third row is
          only 8%, while 1/9 is approximatly 11%.  Again this is due
          to rounding; the price for rolling less dice.
        </p>
        <table style="font-size:75%;width:90%">
          <tr>
            <th>...</th><th>-9</th><th>-8</th>
            <th>-7</th><th>-6</th><th>-5</th>
            <th>-4</th><th>-3</th><th>-2</th>
            <th>-1</th><th>0</th><th>1</th>
            <th>2</th><th>3</th><th>4</th>
            <th>5</th><th>6</th><th>7</th>
            <th>8</th><th>9</th><th>...</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>...</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>44%/44%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>...</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>01-06</td><td>07-08</td><td>09-10</td><td>11-12</td>
            <td>13-15</td><td>16-19</td><td>20-24</td><td>25-30</td>
            <td>31-37</td><td>38-46</td><td>47-54</td><td>55-63</td>
            <td>64-70</td><td>71-76</td><td>77-81</td><td>82-85</td>
            <td>86-88</td><td>89-90</td><td>91-92</td><td>93-94</td>
            <td>95-100</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          In order to keep the probabilities correct, all rolls should
          be made in secret and the result only be exposed when
          necessary.  In many situtations this is highly impractical,
          you therefore need to decide, when to sacrifice correctness
          for playability.  We will see in later sections examples of
          this.  But it should be obvious that a player will rather
          break off a long lasting activity when he knows it will not
          end well.  Think of a race, where everyone knows the
          probable outcome after a few meters have been run.
        </p>
        <p>
          In case a more precise outcome needs to be rolled, roll a
          <em>d10</em> for as many digits after the decimal point as
          needed.
        </p>
        <h3 id="prob_ex">Examples</h3>
        <p>
          The most generic way to roll the dice would be to roll
          <em>d5</em> until a 1 is rolled.  To improve speed, several
          <em>d10</em> may be rolled in ordered fashion.  Order them
          according to size or alphabetical color (e.g. black, blue,
          green, yellow) or in any other way you can remember.  With a
          <em>d10</em> stop at 1 or 2.  If you lack <em>d5</em>s, you
          can also roll <em>d6</em>s with only a marginal 3% error on
          each roll.  But all players (and GM) should roll the same
          type dice.  Computer applications that make rolling as easy
          as pressing a button are also easy to program.
        </p>
        <div class="explain">
          <p>
            Assume you decided to use <em>d100</em> and rolled a 24 on
            the first roll.  This means a result of 1 o the first table. 
            The secon roll (the negative or passive roll) shows a 50, which
            results in 3 for a net result of -2.
          </p>
          <p>
            Another decision is to use the combined table, and a 28 is
            rolled, which results in -3.
          </p>
          <p>
            A more exotic roll would be the sequence 96, 99, 93, 61 on
            the <em>d100</em>.  The result would be 34.
          </p>
          <p>
            Using the standard method, the positive sequence on a
            <em>d10</em> shows 3, 8, 10, 7, 9, 4, 6, 3, 10, 10, 8, 4,
            2 and the negative sequence shows 3, 6, 9, 4, 4, 1.  The
            result is positive 12 and negative 5 with a net result of
            +7.
          </p>
          <p>
            If you decide that +7 is not precise enough, a roll of 3
            and 5 on a <em>d10</em> (each) gives are finer result of
            +7.35.
          </p>
        </div>
        <h3 id="adv">Advantages</h3>
        <p>
          This basic rule has several advantages over other rules that
          are proposed in other systems.  In no particular order:
        </p>
        <div class="explain">
          <p>
            Active and passive are symmetrical.  If you imagine one
            character stealthily evading another, the first may
            interprete the rolls as his actively evading against a
            passive observation of the surroundings, while the second
            may interprete the rolls as his actively scrutinzing the
            vicinity against a passively hiding opponent.  Either way,
            one roll (or set of rolls) will determine the outcome.
          </p>
          <p>
            Scaling with respect to difficulty.  Imagine that one
            character is particularly strong with a certain skill, but
            he also attempts more difficult tasks.  Imagine the child
            character climbing the neighborhood tree and as a grown,
            experienced man climbing an overhanging cliff.  The
            child's climbing bonus of 12 against a difficulty addition
            of 14 for the tree gives the same <em>probability distribution</em> as
            the adult's bonus of 57 against the cliff's 59.  (We have
            not made any rules on skills and difficulties yet, but they
            will turn out to be additions and subtractions from the
            levels.)
          </p>
        </div>
        <h3 id="design">Design Guideline</h3>
        <p>
          When designing the concrete implementations of skills,
          difficulties, situations, etc. keep in mind one of the key
          probability of the basic rule.  And that is <em>a result of
          10 or higher has appoximately a 5% chance</em>.  For a
          positive/active roll alone this is at about 10%.  So when
          designing additions/subtractions consider that when
          comparing numbers directly, say skills in a duel, a 0 will
          only break even (or win) against a 10 in 5% of all cases.
        </p>
        <p>
          In the upcoming paragraphs, we will use this to create a
          <em>level</em> system.  Assuming a <em>level</em> for every
          10 point difference gives a good scale.  Passing a level of
          10 higher is not impossible but improbable.
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>Skills</em> (or <em>Attributes</em>, etc.) should be
          designed as to properly apply to genre-typical situations
          and <em>tests</em>.  Whether generic skills and attributes
          or stylized, specific skills are used, depends on the genre.
          Such specialized application is not of importance at this
          stage.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="extended">Extended Rules</h1>
        <p>
          The following sections deal with application of the
          previously explained <em>basic rule</em>.  Many situations
          can be ruled according to the same principles, regardless of
          the specific genre-rule.
        </p>
        <h3 id="dimscale">Scales &#038; Dimensions</h3>
        <p>
          Skill tests may succeed completely, partially, or not at
          all.  It may take more or less time to complete a task.
          Actions or tasks are therefore split into several
          appropriate dimensions, such that an action can succeed or
          fail in each dimension separately.  The sense of introducing
          dimensions into the rules is to give tactical control to the
          actor/character.  Sometimes a wall needs to be torn down, no
          matter how long it takes.  Sometimes only a certain amount
          of digging can be done before it is interrupted.  A very
          important choice is that of the right dimensions.  A
          predominate dimension applicable to many tasks is
          <em>time</em>.
        </p>
        <p>
          You should always try to create <em>scalable</em> dimensions
          and this is often not hard.  Time, distance, and weight are
          classic examples of such dimensions, But also skills such as
          knowledge can be made scalable.
        </p>
        <p>
          Once you have decided on some effects for a scalable
          dimension, you will have a list like <em>skill 0: 1 minute,
          skill 10: 2 minutes, ...</em>.  The skill level will be in
          steps of 10 (remember the design guidelines), while the
          values depend on the dimension and the concrete skill.  The
          above may be a skill of <em>Holding Breath</em>, but for a
          skill called <em>Ten-Second-Dash</em> the list may look like
          <em>skill 0: 30 meters, skill 40: 100 meters</em>.  To have
          the appropriate intermediate steps, both in skill level and
          dimension, use simple (linear) interpolation.  More complex,
          but potentially accurate intermediate steps are likely to
          sacrifice too much playability.
        </p>
        <h3 id="combo">Combinations</h3>
        <p>
          The following rule only applies when you deem it prudent.
          It combines several actors into one and that only makes
          sense, if resolving the situation takes less time than
          rolling them individually.
        </p>
        <p>
          Sometimes several people (or more generally <em>actors</em>)
          will want to join forces to expedite an action.  Jointly
          lifting a weight or looking for a clue are typical examples.
          This should be simulated by combining the joining people
          into one actor with an increased <em>active</em> value for
          the activity.  The same is true for attempting several tasks
          in one activity, where rolling many dice would become
          combersome.  Attempting to clear away rubble instead of
          individual stones and broken items could be such a
          situation.
        </p>
        <p>
          First decide what the bonus would be, if two characters with
          the same skill level combine their effort into one.  Then
          the following formula provides a way to combine two general
          actors into one.  Take the difference in bonus (<em>skill
          level</em>) as &#946; and the bonus an equal skill level
          should give as &#945;.  If you have set of values, you
          should provide players with a table to reduce calculations
          at the table.  Here, it would distract from the intention.
        </p>
        <p style="font-weight:bold;text-align:center;">
          &#945;ln(1+e<sup>-&#946;ln(2)/&#945;</sup>)/ln(2)
        </p>
        <p>
          For example, assume the bonus would be a full 10 for equal
          characters, but the better character is 5 points ahead on
          the skill.  Then this formula gives the skill of the better
          character plus 8 to the combined actor.
        </p>
        <p>
          You should never indiscriminately add values.  Remember that
          a difference of 10 means a 90% winning difference by design.
          Thus, adding a value that depends on the individual's skill
          makes this quite awkward.  The question you should rather
          ask is, how many people does it take to even out a
          difference of 10.
        </p>
        <p>
          The standard example of taking the best skill roll of two
          (this is the same as requiring at least one of the two to
          succeed.)  would best equate to using &#945;=5.  If you have
          two actors that both must succeed a test, then you should
          use -5, which is equivalent to using the &#945;=5 for the
          <em>reverse</em> roll.  Keep in mind that the reversal of
          <em>positive</em> and <em>negative</em> roll also changes
          who of the two has the higher skill level.
        </p>
        <p>
          The rule can be applied multiple times and its application
          does not depend on the order or sub-grouping of several
          actors, thereby adhering to the outline given in the
          motivational section.  In order to keep this rule simple,
          round results in your tables.  Using the rule multiple
          times, always group two actors of similar skill value
          together.
        </p>
        <p>
          As a more elaborate example, say you have four characters in
          a room searching for something and you have determined that
          this technically means that either of those characters could
          find it, i.e. all would have to roll against a set
          diffculty.  But you want just one roll.  These characters
          have a skill level of 5, 7, 13, and 17.  We keep three
          siginificant digits, so you can verify the formula
          application.  This is <em>not</em> recommended during
          gameplay.  Taking the first two, because they are closest to
          each other, we combine them into an actor with 10.694.  (The
          difference between the two actor levels is 2 and from the
          explanations of the previous paragraphs we know that we
          should use &#945;=5.  We add 3.694 to the higher 7.)  Now we
          combine 10.694 and 13 in the same manner to 16.585.  In the
          last step, we combine 17 and 16.585 into 21.298.
        </p>
        <h3 id="mult">Simultaneous Actions</h3>
        <p>
          Attempting to do simultaneous actions is simple and works
          like reducing both activities by 1 and then doing them both.
          Note that the time required for the activity is not
          simultaneous but consecutive, but in any order desired.
          This can mean that an activity can be postponed and
          "triggered" separately.  As an example, you can observe
          while running; or pick a lock and listen for foot steps.
        </p>
        <p>
          When attacking twice, this may be used as what is called an
          "attack of opportunity" in other rule systems.
        </p>
        <p>
          Some activities may result in higher reductions or no
          reduction for the individual feats attempted.  Penalties for
          attempting more than two actions at the same time must be
          judged separately.
        </p>
        <h3 id="decomp">Decomposition</h3>
        <p>
          A skill may be decomposed into other skills, if so desired.
          The decomposition must be such that the combination of
          (weighted) averages of the new skill levels results in the
          original skill level.  Additional measures should be in
          place to indicate that the skills actually belong to a
          group.  A typical restriction is that the individual skills
          of a goup may not differ by more than 10 points.
        </p>
        <p>
          If a decomposition results in multiple rolls, make sure that
          the rules of <em>Combinations</em> remain valid.  A typical
          example would be to turn a roll that applies every 10 days
          into a roll that applies every day.  This implies that all
          of the daily rolls have a difficulty increased by 10.
        </p>
        <h3 id="abort">Abort and Control</h3>
        <p>
          The variance in outcome of an activity can be controlled by
          manipulating the scale of a dimension.  By reducing an
          active roll by n, the active roll can be repeated n times
          and the average of all (n+1) rolls is taken.  This will
          result in a higher probability of the (new) average,
          effectively "controlling" the results.
        </p>
        <p>
          The reverse is not possible, i.e. increasing the active roll
          and randomizing the rolls even more.
        </p>
        <p>
          When actions are not completed, but aborted prematurly,
          partial outcomes are possible.  This is usually an
          interruption during the time dimension, e.g. due to
          inflicted wounds on an active person at some point.
          Consider this the equivalent of a control.  That is, if the
          abort happens, when time to completion is equivalent to an
          active value difference of n, then proceed as if the active
          roll had been reduced by n in another dimension.  If another
          dimension is not feasible, the activity simply fails.
        </p>
        <h3 id="pragm">Pragmatics</h3>
        <p>
          The calculations result in a level difference between the
          <em>active</em> and the <em>passive</em> part, which is the
          only number relevant for rolling.  If only the failure or
          success is of interest and not the circumstances in the
          domains, you can apply the following shortcut.  Since the
          difference must be met by the lower contestant, you may roll
          all the difference dice in one combined
          &#x201c;throw&#x201d; and check, whether any stop digit
          appears.  If it does the lower contestant cannot win, since
          it is irrelevant, where the stop digit appears.  If the stop
          digit does not appear, chances have reduced to 50/50, and
          you can flip a coin in any of a number of ways.
        </p>
        <p>
          For example, suppose the active climber with a skill level
          of 57 wants to scale a cliff of difficulty 49.  The
          difference is 8.  The GM rolls 8 dice, which show up 3, 5,
          6, 1, 3, 9, 9, and 8.  Since 1 is a stop digit, the cliff is
          scaled.  If the 1 had been a 7, for instance, the cliff
          would have had a &#x201c;fighting chance&#x201d; to drop the
          character.  The GM decides that even is good for the
          character and odd is bad and rolls a <em>d10</em>.  It comes
          up a 6 and the character has barely made it.  Any
          story-telling description of this close encounter is at your
          option.
        </p>
        <p>
          Another pragmatic rule that has already been mentioned is
          rolling 10 non-stop rolls in a row can be shortened to
          rolling a 1 on a <em>d10</em>.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="concret">Examples</h1>
        <p>
          All headings are links to the corresponding sub-pages.
        </p>
        <h3 id="harn">
          <a href="harn.xml">Rules for Hârnworld</a>
        </h3>
        <p>
          The first concrete implementation of the rules.  Contains a
          lot of readily applicable rules to many settings.
        </p>
        <h3 id="harn-char">
          <a href="char.svg">Sheets for Hârnworld</a>
        </h3>
        <p>
          A character sheet.  Click on the icon field to toggle
          between the two pages.
        </p>
        <h3 id="expanse">
          <a href="expanse.xml">Rules for Expanse</a>
        </h3>
        <p>
          The main rules are references to the Hârnworld rules.  Links
          are available.
        </p>
      </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</html>
