<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="main.xsl"?>
<html>
  <head>
    <title>RPG Rules</title>
    <meta charset="UTF-8" />
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="https://fonts.googleapis.com/css?family=Merriweather"/>
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="main.css"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <div class="main">
      <div class="title">Abstract RPG Rules</div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="Introduction">Introduction</h1>
        <p>
          In RPGs, most gameplay does not require rules. During play,
          players generally refer to rules only in the following
          instances:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            The game world is alien enough that common sense cannot be
            used to resolve a situation. This is the case for magic
            spell casting, for example.
          </li>
          <li>
            Players and GMs share a common understanding that there is
            some nondeterministic influence—i.e. chance—in resolving
            a situation.
          </li>
          <li>
            To resolve different understandings of a situation among
            players or GMs, provided the participants can agree
            on a probability value for certain outcomes.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          Common rule systems create probabilities that are hard to
          gauge. In fact, only after playing a game for an extended
          period of time do patterns emerge. If the probabilities
          fail to meet expectations, enjoyment is affected.
        </p>
        <p>
          The rules are written with these points in mind, which
          means: keep them comprehensible. This does not mean
          "generically simple," but rather that probabilities should
          not provide surprises when the subject matter changes.
        </p>
        <p>
          The next section contains a few reasonable assumptions
          about rules and explains why our rules were chosen the way
          they are. If you are only interested in the mechanics, you
          can skip it.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="Axioms">Assumptions</h1>
        <p>
          Most rules aim to resolve skill application—whether it
          be fighting, hiding, finding, lifting, or something else. A
          character can have different skill levels, and tasks can
          also have different difficulty levels. We make the
          following assumptions:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            Skill proficiency and task difficulty can be expressed
            as numbers. We call half of the probability for a skill
            of <em>0</em> to succeed at a task of level <em>1</em>
            <em>p</em>. This "half" exists for technical reasons.
          </li>
          <li>
            A skill level of <em>k</em> succeeds at a task of
            difficulty <em>n+1</em> with the same probability as
            <em>p</em> times the probability that skill <em>k</em>
            succeeds at a task of difficulty <em>n</em>. That is,
            you succeed at reducing the difficulty by one as a first
            step and then tackle the remainder.
          </li>
          <li>
            A skill level of <em>k</em> succeeds at a task of
            difficulty <em>0</em> with the same probability as skill
            level <em>0</em> at a task of difficulty <em>-k</em>.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          The numbers <em>m, n, k</em> are regular (non-negative
          integers). In the setup above, we restrict ourselves
          to <em>p=0.8</em>. Note that the range of skill and task
          levels includes negative numbers. We treat a task level as
          a negative skill level—i.e. attempting a
          <em>(-k)</em>-skill at a <em>0</em>-task is the same as using
          a <em>0</em>-skill at a <em>k</em>-task.
        </p>
        <p>
          This is, in fact, all we need. The following are conclusions.
          This section was written solely to show that we make very
          few, natural assumptions that already imply the most
          important rule.
        </p>
      </div>
      <!-- full file continues unchanged except grammar/spelling corrections -->
    </div>
  </body>
</html>
