<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="main.xsl"?>
<html>
  <head>
    <title>RPG Rules</title>
    <meta charset="UTF-8" />
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="https://fonts.googleapis.com/css?family=Merriweather"/>
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="main.css"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <div class="main">
      <div class="title">Abstract RPG Rules</div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="Introduction">Introduction</h1>
        <p>
          In RPGs, most gameplay does not require rules.  During play,
          players will generally refer to rules only in the following
          instances:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            The game world is alien enough that common sense cannot be
            used to resolve a situation.  This is the case for magic
            spellcasting, for example.
          </li>
          <li>
            Players and GMs have a common understanding that there is
            some nondeterministic influence - i.e., chance—in resolving
            a situation.
          </li>
          <li>
            To resolve different understandings of a situation among
            different players or GMs, but participants can still agree
            on a probability value for certain outcomes.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          Common rule systems create probabilities that are hard to
          gauge.  In fact, only after playing a game for an extended
          period of time do patterns emerge. If the probabilities
          do not match expectations, they impact enjoyment.
        </p>
        <p>
          The rules are written with these points in mind, which
          means: keep them comprehensible.  This does not mean "generically
          simple," but rather that probabilities should not provide
          surprises when the subject matter changes.
        </p>
        <p>
          The next section contains a few reasonable assumptions about
          rules and explains why our rules are chosen the way they
          are.  If you are only interested in the mechanics, you can
          skip it.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="Axioms">Assumptions</h1>
        <p>
          Most rules are intended to resolve skill application, whether it
          be fighting, hiding, finding, lifting, or something else.  A
          character can have different skill levels, but tasks at hand
          can also have different difficulty levels.  We make the
          following assumptions.
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            A skill proficiency and a task difficulty can be expressed
            as numbers.  We define <em>p</em> as half of the probability for a skill
            of <em>0</em> to succeed at a task of level <em>1</em>.
            This “half” is for technical reasons.
          </li>
          <li>
            A skill level of <em>k</em> succeeds at a task of
            difficulty <em>n+1</em> with the same probability as
            <em>p</em> times the probability that a skill of <em>k</em> succeeds at a task
            of difficulty <em>n</em>; i.e., you succeed at reducing
            the difficulty by one as a first step and then tackle the
            remaining portion.
          </li>
          <li>
            A skill level of <em>k</em> succeeds at a task of
            difficulty <em>0</em> with the same probability as a
            skill level of <em>0</em> succeeds at a task of difficulty <em>-k</em>.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          The numbers <em>m</em>, <em>n</em>, and <em>k</em> are your regular (non-negative
          integer) numbers.  In the above setup, we will restrict
          ourselves to <em>p=0.8</em>.  Note that the range of skill
          and task levels includes negative numbers.  We treat a
          task level as a negative skill level; i.e., a <em>(-k)</em>-skill
          at a <em>0</em>-task is the same as using a <em>0</em>-skill
          at a <em>k</em>-task.
        </p>
        <p>
          This is, in fact, all we need.  The following are conclusions.
          This section was written solely to show that we make very
          few natural assumptions, which already imply the most
          important rule.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="Basic">One Rule to Rule Them</h1>
        <p>
          <em>
            You roll a d5 until you roll a 1 and then count the number
            of dice that did not show a 1. That is the same as the
            number of dice you actually rolled minus one.  This first
            number is used for the skill roll (of a character).  We
            also call this the <b>positive (stop) roll</b>.  The
            <b>negative (stop) roll</b> is associated with the task
            roll (the resistance of the environment or impediment),
            which is rolled/handled in the same way.  The result of
            the negative stop roll (which is still a positive number)
            is subtracted from the result of the positive.
          </em>
        </p>
        <p>
          We elaborate by listing the probabilities involved as well
          as some examples.  The mechanism is different from other RPG
          rules (I haven&#8217;t found any that use it), where you
          will often roll either a pool of dice and count those that
          meet a certain threshold or use a single die roll.
        </p>
        <p>
          The following two tables are explanatory and not necessary.
          The mechanics have been described completely in the
          highlighted section.  Everything else can be used to reduce
          the number of dice rolled or to better understand the
          implications of the (stop) roll mechanic.
        </p>
        <p>
          In Table 1 the first row shows the results you can achieve
          when making a positive roll.  Since you continue rolling
          until you get a 1 on your d5, you can interpret the complete
          positive stop roll as a series of d5 rolls as you move right
          on the first row, starting with 0.  The second row shows the
          chance of moving up one point (i.e., right) at
          any given step as a percentage value.  Note that this chance
          is always the same.  The third row gives the chance of obtaining
          the result in the corresponding first row
          in each column.  These are expressed as rolls on a d100.
          (This row can be used to reduce the number of rolls but
          still retain the benefits of the rule.)  All but the first
          column of this row are approximations.
        </p>
        <p>
          The last column is somewhat special.  It combines all
          results beyond 9.  Imagine you expand the table to infinity.
          While the extensions of the first and second rows are quite
          obvious, the third is not.  It should be interpreted thus:
          if you roll 91-100, i.e., the highest 10%, you need to roll
          again on this table, get the result as before, and then add
          10 to the result.  (For the mathematically inclined, this is
          a <em>recursive</em> definition, since it is possible that
          you roll 91-100 again, which forces you to roll on this
          table again and add 20 to the net result from the repeated
          application. We will see this in the examples.)  Some
          systems have a similar mechanic and call it an
          &#8220;exploding&#8221; roll or &#8220;open-ended&#8221;.
        </p>
        <table style="width:70%">
          <tr>
            <th>0</th><th>1</th><th>2</th><th>3</th>
            <th>4</th><th>5</th><th>6</th><th>7</th>
            <th>8</th><th>9</th><th>...</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>...</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>01-20</td><td>21-36</td><td>37-49</td><td>50-60</td>
            <td>61-68</td><td>69-74</td><td>75-80</td><td>81-84</td>
            <td>85-87</td><td>88-90</td><td>91-100</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          This table only considers one stop roll, either the positive
          or the negative.  (You can also call them the skill and the
          task (stop) roll.)  The next table shows the chances for
          overall results.  The interpretation of the table is similar
          to the first.
        </p>
        <p>
          Only the third row needs explanation.  With a roll of 01-06
          and 95-100 the extended roll continues on the previous
          table with corresponding consequences. Positive
          continuation - the one on the right end of the table with
          95-100 - is exactly as before, while negative continuation
          results in negative values being added.  For instance,
          rolling 02 and then a 25 gives a result of -11.  The second
          row cell below the 0 result means a 4/9 (44%) chance to
          increase the result by 1, the same chance to decrease the
          result by 1, and a 1/9 (11%) chance to stay at 0.  The astute
          reader will see the chance for 0 in the third row is only
          8%, while 1/9 is approximately 11%.  This &#8220;error&#8221;
          is due to rounding - the price for rolling fewer dice.
        </p>
        <table style="font-size:75%;width:90%">
          <tr>
            <th>...</th><th>-9</th><th>-8</th>
            <th>-7</th><th>-6</th><th>-5</th>
            <th>-4</th><th>-3</th><th>-2</th>
            <th>-1</th><th>0</th><th>+1</th>
            <th>+2</th><th>+3</th><th>+4</th>
            <th>+5</th><th>+6</th><th>+7</th>
            <th>+8</th><th>+9</th><th>...</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>...</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>44%/44%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>80%</td>
            <td>80%</td><td>80%</td><td>...</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>01-06</td><td>07-08</td><td>09-10</td><td>11-12</td>
            <td>13-15</td><td>16-19</td><td>20-24</td><td>25-30</td>
            <td>31-37</td><td>38-46</td><td>47-54</td><td>55-63</td>
            <td>64-70</td><td>71-76</td><td>77-81</td><td>82-85</td>
            <td>86-88</td><td>89-90</td><td>91-92</td><td>93-94</td>
            <td>95-100</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h3 id="Examples">Examples</h3>
        <p>
          A stop roll is rolling a d5 until a 1 is rolled.  Physical
          dice cannot have five equal faces, so you can use a d10
          that stops on 1 and 2 instead.  To improve speed, several
          d10s may be rolled in an ordered fashion.  Order them according
          to size or alphabetical color (e.g., black, blue, green,
          yellow) or in any other way you can remember.  If you lack
          d10s, you can also roll d6s with only a marginal 3% error on
          each roll, or you can reroll all 6s.  But all players (and
          the GM) should roll the same way.  Computer applications that
          make rolling as easy as pressing a button are also easy to
          program.
        </p>
        <div class="explain">
          <p>
            Assume you decided to use the third row in Table 1 with a
            d100 and rolled a 24 on the first roll.  This means a
            result of 1 on the first table.  The second roll (the
            negative or passive roll) shows a 50, which results in 3
            for a net result of -2.
          </p>
          <p>
            Using Table 2, a 28 is rolled, which results in -3.
          </p>
          <p>
            A more exotic roll would be the sequence 96, 99, 93, 61 on
            the d100. The result would be 34 for a positive stop
            roll.  For a combined stop roll, the result would be 29
            (and the roll of 61 ignored, because it is not needed,
            since the 93 already &#8220;stops&#8221; on Table 2).
          </p>
          <p>
            Using the d10-for-d5 replacement method, the positive
            sequence on a d10 shows 3, 8, 10, 7, 9, 4, 6, 3, 10, 10,
            8, 4, 2 and the negative sequence shows 3, 6, 9, 4, 4, 1.
            The result is positive 12 and negative 5 with a net result
            of +7.
          </p>
        </div>
        <p>
          Skill and task rolls are symmetrical.  If you imagine one
          character stealthily evading another, the first may
          interpret the rolls as his skill at evading observation,
          while the second may interpret the rolls as his skill in
          successfully observing the vicinity. Either way, one roll
          (or set of rolls) will determine the outcome.
        </p>
        <h3 id="Hints">Hints</h3>
        <p>
          When describing a situation, the actor and the obstacle both
          possess a certain <em>level</em>.  The first is usually a
          skill in the particular act and the second a measure of the
          difficulty of the task.  In the previous example, the
          observer might have a (skill) level of 5 and finding the
          clandestine character a (task) level of 3.  These levels
          will be added to the positive and negative stop rolls,
          respectively.
        </p>
        <p>
          We are adding and subtracting four numbers: stop rolls and
          levels.  The calculations result in a level difference
          between the positive and negative part (or the skill level
          and task level), which is relevant for rolling.  If only the
          failure or success is of interest and not the degree of
          success or failure, you can apply the following shortcut.
          Since the level difference must be met by the lower-level
          contestant, you may roll all the difference dice in one
          combined attempt and check whether any stop digit appears.
          If it does, the lower contestant cannot win, since it is
          irrelevant where the stop digit appears.  If the stop digit
          does not appear, chances are reduced to 50/50, and you can
          flip a coin in any of a number of ways.
        </p>
        <p>
          For example, suppose a climber with a skill level of 57
          wants to scale a cliff of difficulty level 49.  The
          difference is 8.  The GM rolls 8 dice, which show 3, 5,
          6, 1, 3, 9, 9, and 8.  Since 1 is a stop digit, the cliff is
          scaled.  (The cliff has the lower level!)  Suppose the 1 had
          been a 7 instead - the cliff would have had a good chance to
          drop the character.  The GM decides that even is good for
          the character and odd is bad, and rolls a d10.  It comes up a
          6, and thus the character has barely made it.
        </p>
        <p>
          Another pragmatic rule applies to differences of at least
          10.  Rolling 10 non-stop rolls in a row to match a level
          difference of 10 can be shortened to rolling a 1 on a d10.
          (The chance, 1/10, is an approximation of the exact chance.)
          In fact, the choice of 80% (d5) in the initial paragraph was
          made for the reason that this heuristic holds.
        </p>
        <h3 id="Hints">Diet Rules</h3>
        <p>
          Also known as <em>light rules</em>, the above easily scales
          into a lighter version.  Divide the skill values above by 10
          and record them as such. This will give a 90% advantage to
          someone with one more point.
        </p>
        <p>
          As an example, we record a skill called <em>Fisticuff</em>
          with a 1-5 star rating. When you have two opponents, either
          simply declare the one with more stars the winner, or roll a
          d10, and he wins with 1 through 9.  With equal rating, or
          with a 10 on the d10, you have a draw - if that is an
          acceptable outcome.  If not, flip a coin to see
          who the winner is.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="Roaming">Roaming the Skill Space</h1>
        <p>
          The following rules address common situations.  How do you
          combine a group of actors that support each other?  How do
          you apply two different skills to a task that involves both?
          You should never indiscriminately add skill values.  Remember that a
          difference of 10 means a 90% winning difference by design.
        </p>
        <h3 id="Combinations">Combinations</h3>
        <p>
          Taking the best skill roll of two (this is the same as
          requiring at least one of the two to succeed) can be done by
          using the table below.
        </p>
        <p>
          Suppose you want to combine the skills <em>n</em> and <em>m</em> of
          two actors, where the respective task difficulties have
          already been subtracted.  In the first row, you index the
          positive difference between <em>n</em> and <em>m</em>.  The
          second row will then give you the bonus to add to the higher
          of the two skills - which is then the only one you need to
          roll.  For example, if the skills are 5 and 9.  Then the net skill level
          of the two actors together is 12.
        </p>
        <table style="width:75%">
          <tr>
            <th>Difference</th><td>0-1</td><td>2-3</td><td>4-6</td><td>7-10</td><td>11-19</td><td>20+</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Result</td><td>+5</td><td>+4</td><td>+3</td><td>+2</td><td>+1</td><td>0</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          If you use the rule multiple times, always group two actors
          of similar skill levels together to reduce rounding errors.
          (This is normalized skill level, i.e., the task level has
          already been subtracted.)  The application of this rule
          should not depend on the order or sub-grouping of several
          actors, but rounding errors are present in the table.  See
          below to avoid them.
        </p>
        <p>
          As a more elaborate example, say you have four characters in
          a room searching for something and you have determined that
          this technically means that any of those characters could
          find it, i.e., all would have to roll against a set
          difficulty.  But you want just one roll; imagine you had a
          group search skill.  These characters have skill levels of
          5, 7, 13, and 17.  Taking the first two, because they are
          closest to each other, we combine them into an actor with
          11.  Now we combine 11 and 13 in the same manner to 17.  In
          the last step, we combine 17 and 17 into 22.
        </p>
        <p>
          If you have two actors that both must succeed at a test, that
          is equivalent to using the <em>inverse</em> stop roll, which
          means exchanging the role of positive and negative for the
          purposes of combining.  Logically, this means that either of
          the two obstacles (formerly known as actors) may foil the
          actor (originally the obstacle).  Keep in mind that the
          reversal of <em>positive</em> and <em>negative</em> roll
          also changes who of the two has the higher skill level.
          This may require a bit of getting used to.
        </p>
        <p>
          Imagine in the previous example that the same characters are
          trying to hide from a guard. If either one is detected, the
          guard will raise the alarm and the maneuver fails.  As luck
          would have it, their Hide skill level is exactly their Search
          skill level. But in the inverse, the guard is active and he
          has to succeed at detecting any of the four. Task (inverse
          skill) levels 5 and 7 will turn into 1.  Then 13 and 17 (closest
          together) will turn into 10.  The combined level of the task
          (inverse skill) groups 1 and 10 turns into -1.  Since the
          guard isn&#8217;t really paying attention, the GM gives the
          guard a skill level of 0. That still leaves the group with
          a 60% failure chance.
        </p>
        <p>
          If you are worried about rounding errors, particularly when
          adding large numbers of skills or tasks, use the following
          formula, where &#946; is the difference in level you plug in
          and the addition to the higher value is calculated.
          Round only when done with the 5-addition - as late as
          possible.  (I advise you to use this formula only if you are a rule
          designer who needs to deal with scaling issues.)  Reserve this
          for situations where players attempt to &#8220;break the rules&#8221; by
          exploiting the rounding errors.
        </p>
        <p style="font-weight:bold;text-align:center;">
          5 ln(1+e<sup>-&#946;ln(2)/5</sup>)/ln(2)
        </p>
        <h3 id="decomp">Decomposition</h3>
        <p>
          A skill may be broken down into related skills, if so desired.
          The decomposition must be such that the combination of the
          (weighted) averages of the new skill levels results in the
          original skill level.  Additional measures should be in
          place to indicate that the skills actually belong to a
          group.  (A typical restriction is that the individual skills
          of a group may not differ by more than 10 points.)
        </p>
        <p>
          If a decomposition results in multiple rolls, make sure that
          the rules of <em>Combinations</em> remain valid.  A typical
          example would be to turn a roll that would usually apply
          every 10 days into a roll that applies every day.  This
          implies that each of the daily rolls has its difficulty
          increased by 10.
        </p>
        <p>
          Breaking down and then recombining skills is a useful tool to
          extend the skill space beyond what rules generally cover.
          Imagine that a PC wants to tie a knot, but his skill sheet
          says he has skill level 5 as a Sailor and level 3 as a
          Mountaineer.  For tasks like knots where the difficulty is
          the same for a Sailor and a Mountaineer, the GM can allow
          the PC to use a 9. The reasoning is that the knot skill
          application works as if two separate skills (actors) were
          trying to tie the knot in combination.  Be careful, however,
          with allowing such additions, because if you treat 0 as the
          value an untrained individual has, then in the above case a
          sailor who has never seen a mountain would still have a 0
          in mountaineering, and adding a 0 would yield an effective
          knot skill of 8.
        </p>
        <h3 id="Normalization">Normalization</h3>
        <p>
          We suggest normalizing skills and tasks to zero (0).  What
          does that mean?  This value should represent the skill level
          of an untrained, uneducated, but otherwise healthy 20-year-old
          human.  This is a fictional person.  For instance, in order
          to compare different language skills, we assume this normal
          person has none.  When it comes to gender or racial
          differences, we also suggest creating a fictitious average.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="Dimensions">Dimensions</h1>
        <p>
      		A skill may be applied in multiple <em>dimensions</em>.  It
      		may be used to evaluate something, to produce something, to
      		use something, and more within the appropriate domain.  It can
      		happen under time pressure or at one’s leisure.  These
      		different variable results are called dimensions.  A typical
      		dimension is the time it takes to apply a skill.  Another
      		typical dimension is the quality of the result.  It is useful
      		to prepare common dimensions for skill application, both to
      		be prepared and to remain consistent over time.
   	    </p>
   	    <p>
      		If an actor decides to use multiple dimensions at the same
      		time, this is called a <em>trajectory</em>.  For example,
      		assume that we have two common applications of a skill
      		called <em>Fletching</em>: creating an arrow of standard
      		quality, where time varies, and creating an arrow while
      		whittling for an hour, where quality varies.  In preparing
      		for an upcoming attack on his village, the character wants
      		to create good arrows quickly.  The GM rules that this
      		results in 50% speed and 50% quality.  This is a typical
      		trajectory.
        </p>
        <h3 id="Accuracy">Accuracy</h3>
        <p>
      		Judging the value of goods produced or performances
      		delivered works the same for almost all skills, which is why
      		this dimension fits into the general framework.  Since the
      		spread of these values in the concrete environment remains
      		unknown, let us look at how these values are derived
      		and how they are interpreted.
    	  </p>
        <p>
          Consider that you want to express a <em>certainty</em>
          between 100% and 0%.  In an example scenario, you might
          rule that someone with a skill level of 20 is 80% certain,
          and that someone with a 0 has 0% certainty.  The rest is
          interpolated and extrapolated accordingly, e.g., at 10 the
          certainty is 40%.  If you do not want to have the spread as an
          independent dimension, you can calculate this as between
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>V x C</em> and <em>V / C</em>
        </p>
        <p>
          where <em>C</em> represents the certainty value between 0
          and 1 (the percentage divided by 100) and <em>V</em> the
          actual value known only to the GM.
        </p>
        <p>
          Write down the results of these calculations according to
          the skills you are interested in.  (You can see an example
          of this in Harnmaster.)  Now assume that you have determined
          both <em>C</em> and <em>V</em> for a specific instance.  Since
          these numbers are usually not easy to work with, choose
          any number by any arbitrary means between (roughly) the
          values given in the above formula.  This is the estimate
          that the PC is given.  If he is interested in how accurate
          he is - for instance, to check whether a merchant is trying
          to outsmart him in a trade - he can do the reverse operation
          and be sure that the true value is within that range.
        </p>
        <p>
          As a concrete example, suppose you determine <em>C</em> =
          0.60 (60%) and <em>V</em> is $160.  We are picking these
          numbers to show that the calculations are not difficult even
          if the numbers appear to be so.  Now eyeball <em>C</em>
          roughly as two thirds.  Multiplying $160 by 2/3 gives
          roughly $100, and dividing by it (multiplying by 3/2) gives
          roughly $250, thus an interval between $100 and $250.  If
          these calculations still seem excessive, consider any other
          method of approximation.  Now pick a random value in that
          range, e.g., roll a d100 and say low is at the lower end.
          That number comes up 87 in our example, so we tell the PC
          his estimate is $200.  The PC wants to buy that item, so he
          wants to gauge the value more accurately in order not to be
          ripped off but also not to miss out on a good deal.  Being a
          number cruncher, he will do the reverse operation with
          rigor.  Because he knows his certainty to be 60%, he
          calculates the interval:
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>$220 x (1 - 0.6) = $132</em> and <em>$220 / 0.6 =
          $366.67</em>
        </p>
        <p>
          This interval contains the real value $160 and leaves the PC
          a little wiser, but he is not in a very good bargaining
          position.  Note that for large values of <em>C</em> (close to
          1) you can use <em>V/C = V x (2 - C)</em> if you’d rather use
          multiplication instead of division.
        </p>
        <p>
          In summary: use certainty in any way you agree with your
          playing group.  The above provides a way to express
          uncertainty less ambiguously.
        </p>
        <h3 id="Proportional">Proportional</h3>
        <p>
          This is a very simple dimension often used intuitively.  When
          a result roll is positive (e.g., +3) then the normal
          success is exceeded by the same amount as a <em>constant
          percentage</em> (e.g., 10%, which would mean 30%
          overachievement).  To obtain a sensible constant, it is
          useful to think of the result roll that would yield 0%.
        </p>
        <p>
          Say that -20 would mean disaster and nothing is achieved at
          all.  This implies that from 0% to 100% we have 20 points to
          bridge, which puts each point at 5%, which is the <em>constant
          percentage</em>. We get (as an example):
        </p>
        <table style="width:75%">
          <tr>
            <th>Result Roll</th><td>-20</td><td>-15</td><td>-10</td><td>-5</td><td>0</td><td>5</td><td>10</td><td>15</td><td>20</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Result</td><td>0%</td><td>25%</td><td>50%</td><td>75%</td><td>100%</td><td>125%</td><td>150%</td><td>175%</td><td>200%</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h3 id="Exponential">Exponential</h3>
        <p>
          An exponential scale is not as easy to compute.
          Unfortunately, it is more natural to our ruleset.  It can be
          simplified by using tables where necessary.  The reason
          this is more natural is the way differences in the
          value behave: 10 more points mean 10 times as likely to
          succeed; this is the defining property of an exponential
          curve.
        </p>
        <p>
          A very simple dimension is this: when you say that 4 people
          are as likely to succeed as a single person who has 10 more
          points.  In that case, you can also use 5-addition.
        </p>
        <p>
          As a concrete simple example, assume that a person who is
          10 times as skilled as another produces four times the result
          of the lesser.  That would be equivalent to simply adding the
          results of the aforementioned 4 lesser people.  Maybe think
          of adding the weights each individual can lift so that in total
          they simply add up.  That is row <em>Result 4</em> in
          the next table.
        </p>
        <p>
          Another result would be that 4 people cannot simultaneously
          address the problem with the same efficiency.  They would
          stand in each other&#8217;s way, reserve tools exclusively,
          etc.  In row <em>Result 2</em> we assume that these 4 people
          are only twice as effective as one person.  Since there is
          some rounding taking place, the number in parentheses gives
          a factor that is often easier to work with than the more
          exact percentage.
        </p>
        <table style="width:75%">
          <tr>
            <th>Result Roll</th><td>-20</td><td>-15</td><td>-10</td><td>-5</td><td>0</td><td>5</td><td>10</td><td>15</td><td>20</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Result 4</td><td>6.75%</td><td>12.5%</td><td>25%</td><td>50%</td><td>100%</td><td>200%</td><td>400%</td><td>800%</td><td>1600%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Result 2</td><td>25%</td><td>35% (3/8)</td><td>50%</td><td>70% (3/4)</td><td>100%</td><td>141% (3/2)</td><td>200%</td><td>283% (3)</td><td>400%</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="Application">Appendix</h1>
        <p>
          Note that you could simply multiply the d20 skill levels by
          two or take half for the percentile system - why use a
          strange mapping?  Since we do not intend to simulate other
          rules in this manner, you can certainly do that
          conversion.  We provide the details to show that these rules
          do not have the natural chance progression we desire.  But a
          simple mapping is also included.
        </p>
        <p>
          Many rulesets rank a skill on a percentile scale, 0% through
          100%.  This is the case for Rolemaster, RuneQuest, or
          Harnmaster.  Rolling below your skill value means you
          succeed (or formulated equivalently).  The skill levels (in
          our rules) are 0, 10, 20, and 30, and they can be mapped to
          the classical skill values of 5%, 35%, 65%, and 95%.  That means
          these rules have about forty skill levels, into which all
          values fall according to our system.  To keep things simple,
          use:
        </p>
        <p style="font-weight:bold;text-align:center;">
          skill level = 4/10 x classic value
        </p>
        <p>
          Something similar is true for Dungeons &#38; Dragons,
          Pathfinder, or generally the d20 family of rules, which use
          twenty 5% steps instead of the finer-grained 1% steps.  Our
          levels 0, 10, ..., 40 correspond to the classic skill bonuses of
          +0, +9, +18, +27, and +36.  These steps are approximations,
          since none of these rolls are translation-invariant.  To
          keep things simple, use:
        </p>
        <p style="font-weight:bold;text-align:center;">
          skill level = classic bonus
        </p>
        <p>
          The one-page character sheet is applicable to all rules.
          You need to fill in the relevant skills and tasks for a
          character.  Since the possible combinations are virtually
          limitless, list only the most common ones or add another
          sheet if you do not find a suitable decomposition of skills
          and tasks.
        </p>
        <p>
          All following headings are links to the corresponding
          subpages.
        </p>
        <h3 id="scifi">
          <a href="scifi.xml">Rules for SciFi</a>
        </h3>
        <h3 id="char">
          <a href="char.svg">Generic Char Sheet</a>
        </h3>
      </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</html>
