<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="main.xsl"?>
<html xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">
  <head>
    <title>Harn RPG Rules</title>
    <meta charset="UTF-8" />
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="https://fonts.googleapis.com/css?family=Merriweather"/>
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="main.css"/>
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="gf.css"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <div class="main">
      <div class="title">Harn RPG Rules</div>

      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="char">Character</h1>
        <h3 id="char-1">Page 1-6, 13-14, 17-18, 28-30</h3>
        <p>
          The attributes and descriptons remain in place as Harnworld
          requires them (at least for some characters).  In other
          words, without them, a character designed toward a specific
          career would be incomplete in the setting.  They are also
          not transformed in any way.  Generation of values can be
          used as suggested.  <em>Relationship and Loyalty</em> for
          contacts are descriptive only.
        </p>
        <p>
          Sunsigns are attributes with value 5.  Modifiers in later
          sections are treated as combination of the corrsponding
          percentage, e.g. +3 = 60%.  See the <em>Skills</em> section
          how this effects the overall skill level.
        </p>
        <h3 id="char-2">Page 7-8, 10</h3>
        <p>
          The attributes described are translated (linearly) into the
          range -15 to 15.  <em>Moraliy</em> is dropped.  Generation
          of values can be used as suggested.
        </p>
        <h3 id="char-3">Page 9, 11-12</h3>
        <p>
          Table results from these page are used purely in their
          descriptive sense.  Whether they retroractively have any
          effect on other attributes is a choice that can be made
          during character creation and according to the severity or
          interpretation of the result that you want to portait.
          <em>Piety</em> is turned into a skill (q.v.) for each deity.
          For a single deity the value can be chosen or generated as
          suggested.  All others are 0 initially.
        </p>
        <h4 id="piety">Piety</h4>
        <ul class="explain">
          <li>
            <b>Level 0:</b> NN knows that the reigion exist but cannot
            separate it from other convocations.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 5:</b> Lip service payed to the religion and
            ability to separate it from other major faiths.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 10:</b> The main tenants of the religion are
            known and followed on individual level.  Sects or heresies
            are not considered.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 15:</b> The religion is quoted often and other
            faiths routinely treated underhanded.  Proselytizing is
            rarely attempted.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 20:</b> At this level the adherent is actively
            seeking to further the tenants of the religion outside of
            his immediate domain.  Distinction between inner-religion
            minutiae are important.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 25:</b> Heresy is abhorred more than other
            religions.  Support for the religion takes precendents
            over other interests almost always.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 30:</b> The adherent is a prophet for the
            religion and accepts otherwise serious consequences for
            following details of his faith.  May invent rituals and
            the like.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <h3 id="char-4">Page 15</h3>
        <p>
          The occupations of the table on this page serve as skills
          and the listed "old" skills serve only as descriptive
          values.
        </p>
        <h3 id="char-5">Page 16, 19</h3>
        <p>
          <em>Automatic</em> skills are determined accoridng to the
          appropriate skill section (q.v.) and <em>Occupation</em>
          skills work as transformed for the previous page.  They open
          as 20 for the chosen occupation.  <em>Family</em> skills for
          parents in the same occupation add 2 points, while for a
          different occupation they add 5.  (This is effectively
          <em>Row-5-addition</em> of a 0 skill level.)
          <em>Optional</em> skills are as they exist, but new skills
          may be "invented"; the scope is at GM discretion.  Any
          reasoonable skill can be improved by 5 for each option point
          (OP) through <em>Row-5-addition</em>; this includes OPs
          gained for Veterans.  Militia skills are explained elsewhere
          as are psionics.
        </p>
        <h3 id="char-6">Page 20-22</h3>
        <p>
          Rules on these page are completely dropped currently.
          Generation of values can be used as suggested.
        </p>
        <h3 id="char-6">Page 23-27</h3>
        <p>
          Each clerical occupation is treated as a separate
          occupation, with the "old" skills being used in a
          descriptive sense.  The same is true for the Shek-Pvar.
          <em>Chantry Applications</em> are dropped.  Treat Sunsigns
          as attributes of the same level from the <em>Convocational
          Sunsign Modifiers</em> for magic invocations.  Magic does
          not work along spell lines (q.v.).  Each military occupation
          is treated as a separate occupation as well.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="skills">Skills</h1>
        <p>
          Available skills are according to the occupations listed
          above, determined by Harnworld professions.  More skills may
          be created according to players' or GM's wishes.  A
          selection of often used skills that do not easily relate to
          occupations is given below
        </p>
        <p>
          Situations which require rolls are announced by the GM with
          a general description of what needs to be resolved.  Players
          will then argue, which skills could be applicable and the GM
          will give a corresponding percentage of how much they apply.
        </p>
        <p>
          For example, an assessemnt of the correct political relation
          between to rival noble families may be Herald/75% and
          Knight/50%, and Mercantyler/25%.
        </p>
        <p>
          Now roll for all applicable skills you have a value in.
          (Remember that a base 0 always applies.)  In the example
          above, the mercantyler has a 1 in 4 chance of using his
          mercantyler skill, say 12, and a 3 in 4 chance of using his
          knight skill 0.  All skills which were succeessfully rolled
          for are added up through row 3 from the main rules additions
          table (repeated here).  The end result is the skill to roll
          against.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Skill Difference</th><td>0-1</td><td>2-3</td><td>4-9</td><td>10+</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Addition</th><td>3</td><td>2</td><td>1</td><td>0</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h3 id="skill-1">Page 1-2, 5</h3>
        <p>
          These pages are ignored.
        </p>
        <h3 id="skill-2">Page 3-4</h3>
        <p>
          The following skills can be used in addition to the
          occupation skills.  They are considered standard.  Sunsigns
          affect certain applications of skills.  Since the "old"
          skills still remain in their descriptive sense, a player
          should announce, when he feels like his sunsign would apply
          to a situation.  Sunsigns are attributes
        </p>
        <ul class="explain">
          <li>
            <b>Climbing</b>
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Stealth</b>
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Intuition:</b> This skill combines the "old" Awareness
            and Intrigue skills and means the ability to infer more
            than the senses obviously provide.  This includes
            interpreting the twitching when someone lies as well as a
            piece of wood out of place.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          Certain applications of skills are provided with result
          tables to allow comparisons.
        </p>
      </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</html>
