<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="main.xsl"?>
<html xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">
  <head>
    <title>Rules for Hârnworld</title>
    <meta charset="UTF-8" />
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="https://fonts.googleapis.com/css?family=Merriweather"/>
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="main.css"/>
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="gf.css"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <div class="main">
      <div class="title">Rules for Hârnworld</div>

      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="rules">Rules</h1>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="attrib">People</h1>
        <h3 id="attrib">Attributes</h3>
        <p>
          All people are individuals that act in Hârnworld.  They,
          particularly PCs, are at the core of what these rules are
          all about.  Apart of the numerical attributes, a few of the
          only descriptive aspects should be mentioned.
        </p>
        <p>
          Attributes are values that other people "attribute" to
          individuals they encounter, particularly those that they
          interact with for some time.  The following lists those
          properties and the common values used for them.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <td><a href="#birthdate">Birthdate</a></td>
            <td><a href="#birthplace">Birthplace</a></td>
            <td><a href="#clanhead">Clanhead</a></td>
            <td><a href="#comeliness">Comeliness</a></td>
            <td><a href="#complexion">Complexion</a></td>
            <td><a href="#culture">Culture</a></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><a href="#deity">Deity</a></td>
            <td><a href="#estrangement">Estrangement</a></td>
            <td><a href="#eyehaircolor">Eye/Hair Color</a></td>
            <td><a href="#frame">Frame</a></td>
            <td><a href="#gender">Gender</a></td>
            <td><a href="#height">Height</a></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><a href="#medical">Medical</a></td>
            <td><a href="#mental">Mental</a></td>
            <td><a href="#morality">Morality</a></td>
            <td><a href="#parent">Parent</a></td>
            <td><a href="#physical">Physical</a></td>
            <td><a href="#psyche">Psyche</a></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><a href="#senses">Senses</a></td>
            <td><a href="#sexuality">Sexuality</a></td>
            <td><a href="#siblingrank">Sibling Rank</a></td>
            <td><a href="#socialclass">Social Class</a></td>
            <td><a href="#species">Species</a></td>
            <td><a href="#sunsign">Sunsign</a></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><a href="#voice">Voice</a></td>
            <td><a href="#weight">Weight</a></td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h4 id="morality">Morality</h4>
        <p>
          Individuals should have a moral compass.  Morality is a
          measure of unselfishness.  The following serves as a
          guideline of the diversity found in Hârnworld, but is by no
          means exhaustive.  Sindarin tend towards the “higher” moral
          standards.
        </p>
        <p>
          Customary description of Morality include: <em>Diabolical,
          Unscrupulous, Corruptible, Law-Abiding, Principled,
          Exemplary.</em> They are not always applied correctly when
          dealing with enemies or friends.  Moral description from
          others tend to be worse when describing an enemy.
        </p>
        <h4 id="sexuality">Sexuality</h4>
        <p>
          People have a descriptive sexuality.  The distribution of
          sexuality in Hârn is roughly 90% heterosexual, 5% bi-sexual
          and 5% homosexual.  Other forms of sexuality may exist but
          are hidden.
        </p>
        <h4 id="species">Species</h4>
        <p>
          Although Hârn has many exotic creatures, Humans, Sindarin
          and Khuzdul are by far the most commonly encountered.  The
          population distribution on Hârn is approximately Human
          (97%), Sindarin (1%), and Khuzdul (1%).
        </p>
        <h4 id="gender">Gender</h4>
        <p>
          Among encountered humans 48% are male, among Sindarin 45%,
          and among Khuzdul 75%.  (Other individuals encountered are
          female.)
        </p>
        <h4 id="birthdate">Birthdate</h4>
        <p>
          Every day of the year (360) has an equal probability of
          being the birthday of a random person.  In other words: they
          are evenly distributed.  Names of calendar months are
          readily available in other sections of Hârnworld.
        </p>
        <h4 id="sunsign">Sunsign</h4>
        <p>
          Sunsign is a major factor for skill-affinity, but all
          sunsigns have advantages and disadvantages.  Sunsign is
          determined by birthdate.  The first two and last two days of
          each sign are termed the cusp: a person born on the 1st
          of Ilvin is termed a Tai-Skorus Cusp (the actual sunsign is
          named first).  Those born on the cusp enjoy the benefits of
          either sign.  Hârnic astrology reveals the Pvaric nature of
          Kelestia.  Personality descriptions for each of the twelve
          signs of the zodiac are given in HârnPlayer.  The
          personality of a person born on the cusp would be a blend
          of the two signs.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>From</th><th>To</th><th>Sunsign</th><th>Symbol</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>4th Nuzyael</td><td>3rd Peonu</td><td>Ulanus</td><td>Tree</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>4th Peonu</td><td>2nd Kelen</td><td>Aralius</td><td>Wands</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>3rd Kelen</td><td>3rd Nolus</td><td>Feniri</td><td>Smith</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>4th Nolus</td><td>4th Larane</td><td>Ahnu</td><td>Fire Dragon</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>5th Larane</td><td>6th Agrazhar</td><td>Angberelius</td><td>Flaming Sword</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>7th Agrazhar</td><td>5th Azura</td><td>Nadai</td><td>Salamander</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>6th Azura</td><td>4th Halane</td><td>Hirin</td><td>Eagle</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>5th Halane</td><td>3rd Savor</td><td>Tarael</td><td>Pentacle</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>4th Savor</td><td>2nd Ilvin</td><td>Tai</td><td>Lantern Bearer</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>3rd Ilvin</td><td>2nd Navek</td><td>Skorus</td><td>Mixer</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>3rd Navek</td><td>1st Morgat</td><td>Masara</td><td>Chalice</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>2nd Morgat</td><td>3rd Nuzyael</td><td>Lado</td><td>Galley</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h4 id="birthplace">Birthplace</h4>
        <p>
          HârnWorld regional modules provide Birthplace generation
          tables.  The GM may assign you a birthplace, or tell you
          what dice to roll to generate one on these tables.
        </p>
        <h4 id="culture">Culture</h4>
        <p>
          A person’s Culture is determined by Birthplace.  Most people
          born on Hârn are Feudal.  Common exceptions are: Imperial
          (Tharda), Viking (Orbaalese), Tribal, Sindarin, and Khuzan.
        </p>
        <h4 id="socialclass">Social Class</h4>
        <p>
          The Social Class is usually not something considered random.
          The table shows the distribution of all classes, should a
          hypothetical census be taken.  It may be useful to determine
          the Social Class of a randomly encountered individual.  For
          some cultures a random result does not make sense
          (e.g. Slaves in Kaldor).  Refer to the relevant HârnWorld
          publication.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th></th><th>Tribal</th><th>Viking</th><th>Feudal</th><th>Imperial</th><th>Khuzan</th><th>Sindarin</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Slave</td><td>10%</td><td>15%</td><td>15%</td><td>25%</td><td>-</td><td>-</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Serf</td><td>-</td><td>65%</td><td>55%</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Unguilded</td><td>89%</td><td>13%</td><td>23%</td><td>65%</td><td>15%</td><td>70%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Guilded</td><td>-</td><td>5%</td><td>5%</td><td>8%</td><td>83%</td><td>29%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Noble</td><td>1%</td><td>2%</td><td>2%</td><td>2%</td><td>2%</td><td>1%</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h4 id="siblingrank">Sibling Rank</h4>
        <p>
          About a third of all individuals encountered are first-born.
          Of the remainder, a third is a second-born and so on.  For
          Sindarin and Khuzdul 50% are first-born and of the
          remainder, 50% are second-born instead.  The sex and age of
          each sibling may be determined accordingly, with a 60% of
          each still being alive.  To determine the number of
          siblings, determine the rank of the last sibling as before,
          but which obviously must come after the indiviual's rank
          already determined.
        </p>
        <h4 id="parent">Parent</h4>
        <p>
          The individual’s Father and Mother represent an important
          aspect of an individual in a mostly feudal society.
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            50% of all people are regular offspring, the person is
            raised by his natural parents.  Of these cases, when a
            minor comes of age, 60% see both parents alive and living
            together, 20% see either the father or the mother absent
            (desertion, divorce, etc.).  In the remaining 20% either
            the father or mother is dead, in half of the cases the
            surviving spouse has remarried.
          </li>
          <li>
            20% of all people were fostered; they lived with another
            family for social, economic, or political reasons.
            Guilded apprentices are usually fostered with their
            masters, as are squires training for knighthood.  Poor
            families, especially those with only one parent, commonly
            foster one or more children with a relative or neighbor.
            Fostered children are usually aware of their parents’
            identity.
          </li>
          <li>
            5% of individuals were adopted by another family for
            social, economic, or political reasons.  Adoption is
            generally only done if both parents are dead, but there
            are exceptions if parental consent is given.  Adopted
            children are often unaware of the fact.
          </li>
          <li>
            15% are Bastards. Parents never married, most likely
            because the father was of a higher social class, or one
            (or both) parents were already married or
            betrothed. Acknowledgement happens only in a third of all
            cases. A bastard usually lives with his mother, but may
            reside with father if acknowledged.
          </li>
          <li>        
            10% of people are orphans, both father and mother are
            deceased.  Only 5% of orphans live alone, the others are
            either Fostered with another family/clan (80%) or adopted
            by another family/clan (15%).  Brothers and sisters (if
            any) may have been fostered/adopted by another family.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          It is the habit of the upper classes to spread their oats
          throughout the lower classes; if unacknowledged, the real
          father may never be known, but then again, he may be someone
          of wealth and power who could be helpful.  Acknowledging a
          bastard is a significant act; the admission can have
          important emotional ramifications for both parents,
          especially to their respective spouses.  In families where
          there is property and/or titles to inherit, acknowledged
          bastards usually follow the youngest legitimate heir, but
          dynamic characters may do better, especially if they happen
          to be a father’s eldest son and the legitimate heirs are
          weak.  Many a dynastic bonfire has been ignited with such a
          spark.
        </p>
        <h4 id="estrangement">Estrangement</h4>
        <p>
          Estrangement measures a person’s popularity in the clan,
          tribe, and/or family.  It has a significant effect on
          opportunities, including any inheritance.  Being the eldest
          child of a knight is less advantageous if he hates
          you. Siblings with different estrangements are often jealous
          of each other; this can produce interesting family politics.
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            10% are outcasts.  They are ignored or may even be
            attacked by other family members.  Of eldest children,
            only 5% are outcasts, and in small clans any child has
            only a 1% chance of being outcast.
          </li>
          <li>
            30% are unpopular.  With the likely exception of the
            mother, the family dislikes the person.  Any birthright
            is/was given grudgingly, if at all.  In small clans this
            happens only a 20% of the time.
          </li>
          <li>
            35% are popular with their clan.
          </li>
          <li>
            5% are treated as favorites.  The individual has
            privileges, possibly at the expense of other siblings.  Of
            eldest children, 10% are favorite.  In small clans, 24% of
            offspring is treated favoringly.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <h4 id="clanhead">Clanhead</h4>
        <p>
          A person’s relationship to the Clanhead is often more
          important than to parents.  Hârnic clans tend to be large.
          Some live in close proximity.  Some number in the thousands
          and are widely dispersed.  Wealthy and noble clans are often
          extended.  Poor clans are likely to be smaller, especially
          if they live in major settlements.  Poor families in the
          same town or district may have the same clan name, but have
          been out of touch for generations.  Except for outcast
          characters, the clanhead can always provide shelter and a
          hot meal.  In some cultures, maternal relationships are more
          important.
        </p>
        <p>
          The hypothetical census would have for a person: 15% father
          or mother as the clan head, 10% a cousin, 25% an aunt or
          uncle. All others (50%) identify the clanhead as distant.
        </p>
        <h4 id="height">Height</h4>
        <p>
          The average height of a Hârnic male human is 68 inches with
          a variance of 5.83. The average is modified: Sindarin: -3",
          Khuzdul: -14".  Human females: -2", Sindarin females: 1".
          Ivinian +1”, nobility +2”, urban poor -2”.  Such
          measurements are often made by Physicians, while averages
          and variance thereof are only calculated by excentric
          scholars.
        </p>
        <h4 id="weight">Weight</h4>
        <p>
          On Hârn, the "optimal" weight of a person depends on his
          height and is determined by the Physician's Guild and
          usually published in a yearly almanach.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Height</th><th>Weight</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>40" - 51"</td><td>75 lbs - 97 lbs</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>52" - 63"</td><td>100 lbs - 133 lbs</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>64" - 71"</td><td>137 lbs - 165 lbs</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>72" - 89"</td><td>170 lbs - 255 lbs</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          The Clothiers' Guild and others have agreed on a size
          measure that relates to weight and is only a scale from
          1-10.  The apparent distribution of sizes is recorded here.
          Items that are too small or too big cause discomfort.  A one
          size difference may be acceptable.  The distribution was
          calculated on the human population alone.  Non-humans were
          too rare, when the data was sampled, but their sizes have
          been standardized by the guild none-the-less.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Weight (lbs)</th><td>61-65</td><td>66-75</td><td>76-90</td>
            <td>91-110</td><td>111-135</td><td>136-165</td><td>166-200</td>
            <td>201-240</td><td>241-285</td><td>286-335</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th><b>Size</b></th><td>1</td><td>2</td><td>3</td>
            <td>4</td><td>5</td><td>6</td><td>7</td>
            <td>8</td><td>9</td><td>10</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Distribution</th><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td>
            <td>3%</td><td>27%</td><td>54%</td><td>15%</td>
            <td>1%</td><td>-</td><td>-</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h4 id="frame">Frame</h4>
        <p>
          Frame is another proportional attribute mainly used by
          Clothiers.  It is measured in five main categories. It is
          determined by the actual instead of the optimal weight to
          height ratio.  The optimal <em>Weight : Height</em> ratio is
          considered 100%.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Frame</th><th>W : H</th><th>Human Males</th><th>Human Females</th><th>Sindarin</th><th>Khuzdul</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Scant</td><td>80%</td><td>5%</td><td>26%</td><td>16%</td><td>-</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Light</td><td>90%</td><td>21%</td><td>36%</td><td>34%</td><td>21%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Medium</td><td>100%</td><td>48%</td><td>33%</td><td>41%</td><td>37%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Heavy</td><td>110%</td><td>21%</td><td>5%</td><td>9%</td><td>33%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Massive</td><td>120%</td><td>5%</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>9%</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h4 id="complexion">Complexion</h4>
        <p>
          Complexion is the color of a person’s skin.  Human is for
          all people of Hârnic ancestry.  Nordic humans are similar to
          Khuzdul.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Complexion</th><th>Human</th><th>Sindarin</th><th>Khuzdul</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Fair</td><td>25%</td><td>97%</td><td>90%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Medium</td><td>50%</td><td>2%</td><td>9%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Dark</td><td>25%</td><td>1%</td><td>1%</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h4 id="eyehaircolor">Eye/Hair Color</h4>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th rowspan="2">Color</th><th colspan="3">Human</th>
            <th rowspan="2">Sindarin</th><th rowspan="2">Khuzdul</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Fair</th><th>Medium</th><th>Dark</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td style="border: 2px solid var(--h1);">Eye Color</td>
            <td style="border: 2px solid var(--h1);" colspan="6"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Hazel</td><td>15%</td><td>40%</td><td>65%</td><td>15%</td><td>50%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Gray</td><td>15%</td><td>15%</td><td>15%</td><td>50%</td><td>15%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Violet</td><td>5%</td><td>5%</td><td>5%</td><td>10%</td><td>5%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Green</td><td>10%</td><td>10%</td><td>10%</td><td>5%</td><td>15%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Blue</td><td>55%</td><td>30%</td><td>5%</td><td>20%</td><td>15%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td style="border: 2px solid var(--h1);">Hair Color</td>
            <td style="border: 2px solid var(--h1);" colspan="6"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Brown</td><td>15%</td><td>40%</td><td>65%</td><td>25%</td><td>40%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Black</td><td>15%</td><td>15%</td><td>15%</td><td>20%</td><td>5%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Red</td><td>10%</td><td>10%</td><td>10%</td><td>5%</td><td>25%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Silver</td><td>5%</td><td>5%</td><td>5%</td><td>10%</td><td>20%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Blond</td><td>55%</td><td>30%</td><td>5%</td><td>40%</td><td>10%</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h4 id="comeliness">Comeliness</h4>
        <p>
          A person’s attractiveness to the same species.  Comeliness
          can be modified by cosmetics, but these enhancements usually
          wear off after some time. The courtesan's guild maintains
          these statistics.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Comeliness</th><th>Ugly</th><th>Plain</th>
            <th>Average</th><th>Attractive</th><th>Handsome</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Human, Khuzdul</td><td>5%</td><td>21%</td>
            <td>48%</td><td>21</td><td>5%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Sindarin</td><td>-</td><td>9%</td>
            <td>41%</td><td>34%</td><td>16%</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h4 id="physical">Physical</h4>
        <p>
          Physical ability is assessed by the military (including
          their physicians) and a five-star rating is used.
          Non-humans often have their own physiology - that is
          recognized in the statistics.  (The scale is extended to six
          stars for exceptional non-humans.)
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>Agility</em> moves the body. Agility is useful for
          warriors, seamen, and dancers.
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>Dexterity</em> is the ability to manipulate objects with
          the hands. Dexterity is important for warriors and
          cut-purses.
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>Stamina</em> is the general physiological
          condition. Stamina determines for how long wound healing
          takes and also affects disease and poison resistance.
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>Strength</em> is sheer physical power, a crucial
          attribute for combat and other physical activities, which is
          why military types usually assess it.  It is common
          knowledge that additional weight leads to increased
          strength.  However, this has not been measured accurately
          and not any weight leads to an increase in strength.  It is
          also unknown whether the same relationship to weight exists
          for Sindarin and Khuzdul.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Value</th><th>*</th><th>**</th>
            <th>***</th><th>****</th><th>*****</th><th>******</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td style="border: 2px solid var(--h1);">Agility</td>
            <td style="border: 2px solid var(--h1);" colspan="6"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Massive Frame</th><td>10%</td><td>50%</td>
            <td>33%</td><td>7%</td><td>-</td><td>-</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Heavy Frame</th><td>6%</td><td>26%</td><td>55%</td>
            <td>11%</td><td>1%</td><td>-</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Normal Frame</th><td>4%</td><td>16%</td><td>60%</td>
            <td>16%</td><td>4%</td><td>-</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Light Frame</th><td>1%</td><td>11%</td>
            <td>55%</td><td>26%</td><td>6%</td><td>1%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Scant Frame</th><td>-</td><td>7%</td><td>33%</td>
            <td>50%</td><td>8%</td><td>2%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td style="border: 2px solid var(--h1);">Dexterity</td>
            <td style="border: 2px solid var(--h1);" colspan="6"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Human</th><td>4%</td><td>16%</td><td>60%</td>
            <td>16%</td><td>4%</td><td>-</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Khuzdul</th><td>1%</td><td>11%</td>
            <td>55%</td><td>26%</td><td>6%</td><td>1%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Sindarin</th><td>-</td><td>7%</td><td>33%</td>
            <td>50%</td><td>8%</td><td>2%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td style="border: 2px solid var(--h1);">Stamina</td>
            <td style="border: 2px solid var(--h1);" colspan="6"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Human</th><td>4%</td><td>16%</td><td>60%</td>
            <td>16%</td><td>4%</td><td>-</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Khuzdul</th><td>-</td><td>7%</td><td>33%</td>
            <td>50%</td><td>8%</td><td>2%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Sindarin</th><td>1%</td><td>11%</td>
            <td>55%</td><td>26%</td><td>6%</td><td>1%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td style="border: 2px solid var(--h1);">Strength</td>
            <td style="border: 2px solid var(--h1);" colspan="6"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Human, Sindarin</th><td>4%</td><td>16%</td><td>60%</td>
            <td>16%</td><td>4%</td><td>-</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Khuzdul</th><td>-</td><td>2%</td><td>13%</td>
            <td>60%</td><td>20%</td><td>5%</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h4 id="senses">Senses</h4>
        <p>
          Physicians collect the data for the senses, often diseases
          or poisons affect the senses and their origin can be
          determined by gauging their effects.  A five-star rating is
          used.  (The scale is extended to six stars for exceptional
          non-humans.)
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>Eyesight</em> is the ability to see in daylight.  Except
          for nocturnal creatures (like Gargun) eyesight is reduced in
          the dark and that affects all activity requiring vision.
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>Hearing</em> is used to sense sound.  This is essential
          for musicians.
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>Smell</em> estimates sensitivity to odor and taste.
          This can be useful for hunting and/or tracking, and may warn
          of danger.  Of course, in a medieval town, a keen sense of
          smell may well be a curse.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Value</th><th>*</th><th>**</th>
            <th>***</th><th>****</th><th>*****</th><th>******</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td style="border: 2px solid var(--h1);">Eyesight</td>
            <td style="border: 2px solid var(--h1);" colspan="6"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Human</th><td>4%</td><td>16%</td><td>60%</td>
            <td>16%</td><td>4%</td><td>-</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Khuzdul, Barbarians</th><td>1%</td><td>11%</td>
            <td>55%</td><td>26%</td><td>6%</td><td>1%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Sindarin</th><td>-</td><td>7%</td><td>33%</td>
            <td>50%</td><td>8%</td><td>2%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td style="border: 2px solid var(--h1);">Hearing</td>
            <td style="border: 2px solid var(--h1);" colspan="6"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Human</th><td>4%</td><td>16%</td><td>60%</td>
            <td>16%</td><td>4%</td><td>-</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Barbarians</th><td>-</td><td>7%</td><td>33%</td>
            <td>50%</td><td>8%</td><td>2%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Khuzdul, Sindarin</th><td>-</td><td>7%</td><td>33%</td>
            <td>50%</td><td>8%</td><td>2%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td style="border: 2px solid var(--h1);">Smell</td>
            <td style="border: 2px solid var(--h1);" colspan="6"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Human</th><td>4%</td><td>16%</td><td>60%</td>
            <td>16%</td><td>4%</td><td>-</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Barbarians, Khuzdul</th><td>-</td><td>7%</td><td>33%</td>
            <td>50%</td><td>8%</td><td>2%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Sindarin</th><td>-</td><td>4%</td><td>21%</td>
            <td>58%</td><td>14%</td><td>3%</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h4 id="voice">Voice</h4>
        <p>
          The pleasantness and/or volume of a person’s voice.
          Excellent and unearthly voices are in high demand.  The
          scale is provided by the Sindarin.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Voice</th><th>Unbearable</th><th>Unpleasant</th><th>Average</th>
            <th>Pleasant</th><th>Excellent</th><th>Unearthly</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Human, Khuzdul</td><td>1%</td><td>14%</td><td>65%</td>
            <td>15%</td><td>5%</td><td>-</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Sindarin</td><td>-</td><td>5%</td><td>33%</td>
            <td>47%</td><td>8%</td><td>4%</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h4 id="medical">Medical</h4>
        <p>
          Some people have one or more Medical Traits, or diseases,
          scars, and other identifying marks acquired during life.
          The Sindarin are immune to human diseases, but more are
          considered “Sterile” than other species.  The list is not
          complete and no prevalence statistics in the populace are
          given.
        </p>
        <ul class="explain">
          <li>
            <em>Addiction:</em> Individuals consume some substance
            like alcohol or a drug.  The urge is hard to overcome in
            certain situations.  When under the influence, people may
            become unconscious, injure themselves, etc.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Albinism:</em> Pallid complexion, white hair, red
            eyes.  Viewing bright light causes intense eye pain.
            Albinos sunburn very easily.  Some people consider them
            very attractive.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Allergy:</em> Common allergies are to pollen, hair,
            fur, feathers, wool, bee stings, or to foods such as eggs,
            milk, cereals, or shellfish.  When the substance is
            nearby, a person suffers from sneezing, wheezing, and
            coughing.  This results in reduced abilities until the
            allergy source is avoided or removed.  Eating allergic
            foods can cause serious illness or death - consider this
            as poison.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Ambidextrous:</em> can use both hands equally well.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Arm missing or deformed:</em> Activities which require
            two hands (such as shooting a bow, or using a shield and
            weapon) are impossible.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Birthmark(s):</em> may impact Comeliness, or indicate
            a special ancestry.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Dwarfism:</em> Height is Species minimum minus 2-12
            inches, with Heavy Frame.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Epilepsy:</em> Individual may have a seizure if
            traumatized.  Swimming and Riding should be avoided.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Ear:</em> One ear is missing or deaf.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Eye:</em> One eye is missing or blind.  Lack of depth
            perception and reduced field of vision makes some
            activities difficult.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Gigantism:</em> Individual height is Species maximum
            plus 2-12 inches, with Massive Frame.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Hemophilia:</em> Blood clots much more slowly than
            normal.  Females do not suffer the effect, but pass it on
            to their sons.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Hirsutism:</em> Excessive body hair.  Such a person
            may be mistaken for Gargun or were-creature.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Leg:</em> One leg is missing or deformed.  Such an
            individual can only move at 1/3 sprint speed with the use
            of a peg-leg.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Left-Handed:</em> People with this "affliction" are
            likely to suffer some discrimination.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Leprosy:</em> Body covered with sores/scabs.  Pain
            sensitivity is reduced.  Comliness is reduced.  Leprosy is
            contagious.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Lycanthropy:</em> The individual is a were-creature.
            Some Physicians consider this an imaginary disease, used
            by miscreants to scare gullible people.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Monochromasia:</em> Severe color blindness.  All
            colors are perceived as shades of gray.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Obesity:</em> A person’s weight is 50% to 100% more
            than optimal.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Parasites:</em> Worms, fleas, lice, etc.  These are
            fairly common among the lower classes.  Such individuals
            have special difficulties with social activity.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Poxmarks (healed):</em> A person may bear scars from a
            disease such as smallpox.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Scars:</em> Invariably reduces Comeliness.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Sterile:</em> The person cannot have children.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <h4 id="mental">Mental</h4>
        <p>
          Shek-P'var and Priests collect the statistics for these
          attributes.  They are not willingly shared, only few
          scholars have access to the combined treasure of these
          numbers.  A five-star rating is used.  (The scale is
          extended to six stars for exceptional non-humans.)
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>Intelligence</em> is the ability to reason and
          articulate.  Often the following descriptions are used for
          the star scale:
        </p>
        <ul class="explain">
          <li>* = Absent-minded, moronic, stupid</li>
          <li>** = Forgetful, slow-witted</li>
          <li>*** = Average</li>
          <li>**** = Good memory, clever</li>
          <li>***** = Excellent memory, genius</li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          <em>Aura</em> is Psionic concept.  Hârnic philosophers
          believe that all living things have Aura and that the
          physical body is simply a place where the immortal spirit
          currently resides.  High Aura indicates high psychic
          ability, and is the most important attribute for Psionics
          and magic (although Will and Intelligence are also vital).
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>Will</em> encapsulates mental strength, tenacity, and
          patience.  A person with low Will lacks confidence, panics
          easily, and has difficulty with tedious tasks.  Those with
          high Will are resolute, confident, and stubborn.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Value</th><th>*</th><th>**</th>
            <th>***</th><th>****</th><th>*****</th><th>******</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td style="border: 2px solid var(--h1);">Intelligence</td>
            <td style="border: 2px solid var(--h1);" colspan="6"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>All</th><td>4%</td><td>16%</td><td>64%</td>
            <td>12%</td><td>4%</td><td>-</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td style="border: 2px solid var(--h1);">Aura</td>
            <td style="border: 2px solid var(--h1);" colspan="6"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Human Males</th><td>4%</td><td>16%</td><td>60%</td>
            <td>16%</td><td>4%</td><td>-</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Human Females</th><td>-</td><td>7%</td><td>33%</td>
            <td>50%</td><td>8%</td><td>2%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Khuzdul</th><td>9%</td><td>50%</td><td>32%</td>
            <td>7%</td><td>3%</td><td>-</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Sindarin</th><td>-</td><td>2%</td><td>13%</td>
            <td>60%</td><td>20%</td><td>5%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td style="border: 2px solid var(--h1);">Will</td>
            <td style="border: 2px solid var(--h1);" colspan="6"></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Human, Sindarin</th><td>4%</td><td>16%</td><td>60%</td>
            <td>16%</td><td>4%</td><td>-</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Khuzdul</th><td>-</td><td>4%</td><td>20%</td>
            <td>58%</td><td>14%</td><td>4%</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h4 id="psyche">Psyche</h4>
        <p>
          Phobias, manias, and other mental disorders can be
          disruptive.  The list of mental disorders is not
          comprehensive.  Mental disorders of the same type may have
          different severities.  A phobia is an irrational
          fear/aversion.  When likely to be stimulated by an
          appropriate situation, a person's Will is tested to
          determine if the phobia can be resisted or not.  If relief
          is impossible, the person may faint, become hysterical, go
          berserk, etc.  A mania is an irrational fascination,
          obsession, or compulsion, usually to excess.  An individual
          with Pyromania takes every opportunity to start a fire; with
          Hydrophobia he is unlikely to enjoy swimming, boating, etc.
          Severity of the disorder is, of course, relevant in the
          actions that are taken.  Some disorders are only latent and
          the level of Severity is unknown.  It is quite possible for
          someone with Acrophobia to climb a mountain with no
          problems, but panic sitting atop a twenty feet wall.
          Phobias are irrational.
        </p>
        <p>
          The list is compiled by specialized physicians but also by
          Savorya Shek P'var.  A prevalence is not given, nor is the
          chance of multiple disorders given.  The list is considered
          harmful, if it were to leak into the public.  Translations
          are available for physicians not versed in scholarly
          tongues but sufficient funds.
        </p>
        <ul class="explain">
          <li>Absent Minded Acrophobia (Fear of Heights)</li>
          <li>Aichmophobia (Fear of Sharp Blades, etc.)</li>
          <li>Algophobia (Fear of Pain)</li>
          <li>Astraphobia (Fear of Thunder/Lightning)</li>
          <li>Ballistophobia (Fear of Missiles)</li>
          <li>Bulimia (Eating Mania)</li>
          <li>Claustrophobia (Fear of Confined Spaces)</li>
          <li>Cynophobia (Fear of Dogs)</li>
          <li>Dyslexia (Learning/Reading Disorder)</li>
          <li>Entomophobia (Fear of Insects/Spiders/etc.)</li>
          <li>Gamblamania (Gambling Mania)</li>
          <li>Heliophobia (Fear of Sun/Daylight)</li>
          <li>Gephyrophobia (Fear of Crossing Bridges)</li>
          <li>Hemophobia (Fear of Blood)</li>
          <li>Hydrophobia (Fear of Water/Drowning)</li>
          <li>Hypochondria (Imagined Illnesses)</li>
          <li>Ivashuphobia (Fear of Ivashu)</li>
          <li>Kleptomania (Compulsion To Steal)</li>
          <li>Megalomania (Exaggerated Self-Worth)</li>
          <li>Mysophobia (Fear of Dirt/Filth)</li>
          <li>Multiple Personalities *</li>
          <li>Musophobia (Fear of Mice/Rats)</li>
          <li>Necrophobia (Fear of Corpses)</li>
          <li>Nyctophobia (Fear of Darkness/Night)</li>
          <li>Ophidiophobia (Fear of Snakes)</li>
          <li>Ornithophobia (Fear of Birds)</li>
          <li>Paranoia/Persecution Complex</li>
          <li>Psychopathy (Cannot Tell Right From Wrong)</li>
          <li>Pvaraphobia (Fear of Magic/Wizards)</li>
          <li>Pyromania (Fascination With Fire)</li>
          <li>Pyrophobia (Fear of Fire)</li>
          <li>Sadism (Pleasure Inflicting Pain)</li>
          <li>Sex Mania/Deviancy</li>
          <li>Theophobia (Fear of Divine Retribution)</li>
          <li>Toxicophobia (Fear of Being Poisoned)</li>
          <li>Violent Temper (Loses Control)</li>
          <li>Xenophobia (Fear of Strangers)</li>
          <li>Yaelaphobia (Fear of The Moon)</li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          * The person may change personality in stressful situations,
          based on his Will.  The primary personality is neurotic and
          totally unaware of the secondary personality. The latter, on
          the other hand, is aware of the primary personality and
          often takes desperate actions to try and overcome the
          neurosis of that personality.
        </p>
        <h4 id="deity">Deity</h4>
        <p>
          Gods or goddesses may be worshiped (however laxly) by any
          person.  While people may respect and acknowledge the
          existence of any number of deities, they usually only follow
          one, although it is possible to change religion.  The
          religion a person may encounter depend on a lot of
          circumstances and depends on the birthplace.  Available
          choices are presented in other Hârnworld publications, which
          also consider culture and social class.  Most people tend to
          follow the deity of their parents or guardians.
        </p>
        <p>
          While there are chivalrous worshipers of Morgath and corrupt
          Laranians, people tend to be more satisfied if their morals
          matches that of their deity.  Churches and clerics, unaware
          of an individual’s true morality, may be fooled.
        </p>
        <p>
          People may faithfully ascribe to two or more religions,
          provided the deities are not diametrically opposed.  Some
          miscreants may try to subvert an opposing religion, but this
          is not faithful.  Some rare people may consider themselves
          godless.  Divine intervention is another word for miracle.
          However, the acts of deities should never be confused with
          spells, which are the acts of mages.
        </p>
        <h3 id="occupations3">Occupations</h3>
        <p>
          An occupation largely determines the skills a person learns
          during adolescense and the opportunities that follow, at
          least initially.  Occupation is not necessarily a life
          commitment.  Jobs can change during a life, although this
          might involve lengthy re-training.  The occupations
          available depend mainly on Social Class, although birthplace
          and natural talent (attributes) may open or close some
          doors.  Some vocations (Knight and Herald) are only
          available to high-born individuals; some require exceptional
          natural talent.  Birthplace is also relevant; a person
          born in land-locked Kaldor may have a hard time running away
          to the sea.
        </p>
        <p>
          Determining the chances for the occupation of a random
          individual is hard, since no such census data is available.
          The outcome would largely depend on Social Class, which
          depends on the occupation of one’s parents. Some
          children follow the same occupation or choose another at GM
          discretion. The eldest born survivor, especially if a
          favorite, would be expected to follow the family
          occupation. Later born offspring have more choice,
          especially if unpopular. As a reference, the occupations a
          person can choose in Hârnic society are listed, with average
          income and years of apprenticeship.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th colspan="3">Guilded</th>
            <th colspan="3">Unguilded</th>
            <th colspan="3">Military</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Alchemist</td><td>7</td><td>~</td>
            <td>Animal Trainer</td><td>3</td><td>72d</td>
            <td>Archer/SB</td><td>4</td><td>48d</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Apothecary</td><td>6</td><td>60d</td>
            <td>Beggar</td><td>1</td><td>~</td>
            <td>Clansman/UF</td><td>4</td><td>~</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Astrologer</td><td>4</td><td>~</td>
            <td>Cartographer/Artist</td><td>5</td><td>84d</td>
            <td>Clansman/LF</td><td>4</td><td>24d</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Chandler</td><td>4</td><td>54d</td>
            <td>Cook</td><td>3</td><td>30d</td>
            <td>Guard/MF</td><td>4</td><td>48d</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Charcoaler</td><td>3</td><td>54d</td>
            <td>Farmhand</td><td>4</td><td>24d</td>
            <td>Guard/HF</td><td>4</td><td>72d</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Clothier</td><td>6</td><td>60d</td>
            <td>Fisherman</td><td>5</td><td>48d</td>
            <td>Guardian/MF</td><td>4</td><td>48d</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Courtesan</td><td>3</td><td>~</td>
            <td>Gladiator</td><td>4</td><td>~</td>
            <td>Guardsman/LF</td><td>4</td><td>24d</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Embalmer</td><td>7</td><td>48d</td>
            <td>Herdsman</td><td>2</td><td>24d</td>
            <td>Guardsman/MF</td><td>4</td><td>48d</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Glassworker</td><td>7</td><td>66d</td>
            <td>Hunter/Trapper</td><td>5</td><td>42d</td>
            <td>Horsebow/LH</td><td>4</td><td>96d</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Harper</td><td>7</td><td>42d</td>
            <td>Laborer/Porter</td><td>1</td><td>42d</td>
            <td>Huscarl/MF</td><td>4</td><td>48d</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Herald</td><td>5</td><td>78d</td>
            <td>Longshoreman</td><td>1</td><td>42d</td>
            <td>Huscarl/LH</td><td>4</td><td>96d</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Hideworker</td><td>5</td><td>60d</td>
            <td>Prostitute/Pimp</td><td>1</td><td>~</td>
            <td>Infantry/LF</td><td>4</td><td>24d</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Innkeeper</td><td>5</td><td>60d</td>
            <td>Ratter</td><td>3</td><td>60d</td>
            <td>Infantry/MF</td><td>4</td><td>48d</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Jeweller</td><td>7</td><td>66d</td>
            <td>Sage/Tutor</td><td>5</td><td>84d</td>
            <td>Knight/MH</td><td>4</td><td>192d</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Lexigrapher</td><td>5</td><td>66d</td>
            <td>Scribe</td><td>5</td><td>66d</td>
            <td>Knight/HH</td><td>4</td><td>288d</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Litigant</td><td>7</td><td>72d</td>
            <td>Servant</td><td>3</td><td>24d</td>
            <td>Legionaire/LF</td><td>4</td><td>24d</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Locksmith</td><td>6</td><td>60d</td>
            <td>Teamster</td><td>2</td><td>72d</td>
            <td>Legionaire/MF</td><td>4</td><td>48d</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Mason</td><td>7</td><td>96d</td>
            <td>Thatcher</td><td>4</td><td>54d</td>
            <td>Legionaire/SB</td><td>4</td><td>48d</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Mercantyler</td><td>6</td><td>~</td>
            <td>Toymaker</td><td>5</td><td>48d</td>
            <td>Militia/UF</td><td>4</td><td>~</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Metalsmith</td><td>6</td><td>72d</td>
            <th colspan="3">Cleric</th>
            <td>Patrician (Knight)</td><td>4</td><td>192d</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Miller/Millwright</td><td>6</td><td>84d</td>
            <td>Cleric/Agrik</td><td>7</td><td>~</td>
            <td>Ranger/LF</td><td>4</td><td>24d</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Miner</td><td>6</td><td>84d</td>
            <td>Cleric/Halea</td><td>7</td><td>~</td>
            <td>Ranger/UF</td><td>4</td><td>~</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Ostler</td><td>5</td><td>78d</td>
            <td>Cleric/Ilvir</td><td>7</td><td>~</td>
            <td>Yeoman/LB</td><td>4</td><td>72d</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Perfumer</td><td>6</td><td>66d</td>
            <td>Cleric/Larani</td><td>7</td><td>~</td>
            <td>Yeoman/LF</td><td>4</td><td>24d</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Physician</td><td>7</td><td>72d</td>
            <td>Cleric/Morgath</td><td>7</td><td>~</td>
            <td>Yeoman/SB</td><td>4</td><td>48d</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Pilot</td><td>9</td><td>~</td>
            <td>Cleric/Naveh</td><td>7</td><td>~</td>
            <th colspan="3">Shek-P'var</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Potter</td><td>6</td><td>60d</td>
            <td>Cleric/Peoni</td><td>7</td><td>~</td>
            <td>Shek-Pvar/Fyvria</td><td>7</td><td>~</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Salter</td><td>4</td><td>48d</td>
            <td>Cleric/Sarajin</td><td>7</td><td>~</td>
            <td>Shek-Pvar/Jmorvi</td><td>7</td><td>~</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Seaman</td><td>5</td><td>48d</td>
            <td>Cleric/Hyn-Aelori</td><td>7</td><td>~</td>
            <td>Shek-Pvar/Lyahvi</td><td>7</td><td>~</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Shipwright</td><td>7</td><td>90d</td>
            <td>Cleric/Rydequeln</td><td>7</td><td>~</td>
            <td>Shek-Pvar/Odivshe</td><td>7</td><td>~</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Tentmaker</td><td>5</td><td>72d</td>
            <td>Cleric/Shea-Al-Aecori</td><td>7</td><td>~</td>
            <td>Shek-Pvar/Peleahn</td><td>7</td><td>~</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Thespian</td><td>7</td><td>~</td>
            <td>Cleric/Siem</td><td>7</td><td>~</td>
            <td>Shek-Pvar/Savorya</td><td>7</td><td>~</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Thief (Lia-Kavair)</td><td>3</td><td>~</td>
            <td></td><td></td><td></td>
            <td></td><td></td><td></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Timberwright</td><td>6</td><td>78d</td>
            <td></td><td></td><td></td>
            <td></td><td></td><td></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Weaponcrafter</td><td>7</td><td>108d</td>
            <td></td><td></td><td></td>
            <td></td><td></td><td></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Woodcrafter</td><td>7</td><td>66d</td>
            <td></td><td></td><td></td>
            <td></td><td></td><td></td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          <em>Guilded Occupations:</em> Wages given are for Bonded
          Masters; room and board may also be provided.  The employer
          would bear the additional cost of providing materials and
          supplies, but tools are owned by the master.  A skilled
          mason-architect building a new castle, or an exquisite sword
          craftsman, could earn fees up to six times higher, but such
          incomes are rare.  Apprentices receive room &#0038; board
          and sometimes get pocket money from generous masters.
          Journeymen receive 30-60% of a master's wages, depending on
          experience, plus room and board.  Freemasters have variable
          incomes because demand for their services can vary.  See:
          HârnPlayer, page 15.
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>Unguilded Occupations:</em> Wages given are for average
          experienced workers; others might earn more/less depending
          on skills.  Wages are dependent on the availability of
          labor.  They also tend to be higher in summer and lower in
          winter.
        </p>
        <p>
          Occupational rating is on the typical five-star scale.  When
          completing an apprenticeship, a person is assumed to have
          advanced to *** (three stars) through his training.  The
          occupation of the parent will usually convey a * (one star)
          rating.  Attributes play a role in selecting a suitable
          profession.  There are practical and common sense limits.  A
          warrior with a sufficiently high Aura can certainly learn
          spells, but doing so requires years learning the mysteries
          and ways of magic.
        </p>
        <h3 id="equip">Equipment &#0038; Funds</h3>
        <p>
          A simple peasant may possess little more the clothes worn, a
          knapsack containing their worldly possessions, credentials
          when appropriate, and a money-belt.  Most travel afoot, but
          nobles require a horse.  A person's wealth is largely
          dependent on family wealth, which is relative to social
          status.  The census data compiled by the crowns provide the
          following table and shows three levels of wealth within each
          social class. The value given amounts to what a person is
          assumed to possess when becoming of age, i.e. a responsible
          subject of the souvereign.  This wealth may be used on items
          from the Price List on HârnPlayer and the Weapon and Armour
          tables.  Estrangement can also influence funds.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Social Class</th><th>Poor</th><th>Average</th><th>Rich</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Serf</td><td>40d</td><td>80d</td><td>160d</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Unguilded</td><td>60d</td><td>120d</td><td>240d</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Guilded</td><td>90d</td><td>180d</td><td>360d</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Noble</td><td>600d</td><td>1200d</td><td>2400d</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          Squires are traditionally equipped by their lord when
          knighted.  This includes weapons, armour, and a good steed.
          Family wealth above does not include this.  Very few Hârnic
          folk own property.  Rural freemen and serfs rent cottages
          and land from the lord.  City homes are mostly owned by a
          few wealthy folk and rented to poorer citizens.  Only
          established urban guildsmen can hope to buy a private home.
          Most rural households own a few sheep or goats, perhaps a
          cow.  Some families raise pigs which are prolific breeders.
          Wealthier households own oxen and rent them for village work
          in exchange for food and labor.  Only the wealthiest of
          peasants can afford to keep a bull or a horse.
        </p>
        <p>
          Clothes should suit a person’s station.  A tunic, leggings,
          hat, and sandals are bare essentials.  Some folk wear a robe
          or gown instead of a tunic.  Travelers normally have a
          knapsack containing portable tools of their trade.  A
          weaponcrafter, for example, must own hammers and tongs, but
          carrying an anvil is unlikely.  Nearly everyone carries some
          fire-making tools (tinderbox, or flint and steel) and a
          strip of cloth for a towel, bandage, or arm-sling.  A
          waterskin is also essential.
        </p>
        <p>
          Nearly everyone owns a knife or dagger.  Clubs, bows,
          hatchets, slings, and staves are also common.  Other weapons
          are expensive and “Bearing Arms” in HârnPlayer should be
          consulted.  Few young adults can afford good armour.
          Military individuals are mostly equipped by their unit, but
          knights on feudal service must bring their own weapons,
          armour, and steed.
        </p>
        <p>
          Proving identity can be difficult on Hârn.  A travelling
          person should have papers to prove guild rank (if any)
          and/or a letter of introduction from a prominent person such
          as a lord of the manor, or a cleric or sheriff, etc.  Many
          guilds issue a badge or tattoo to prove rank. The expensive
          weapons and armour carried by knights speak for themselves.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="occupation1">Occupations</h1>
        <h3 id="cleric">Cleric</h3>
        <p>
          People interested in a clerical career must visit a temple
          or abbey to be interviewed by the Master of Acolytes, or
          find a priest to sponsor the application.  An appropriate
          Morality and a minimum Ritual knowledge are generally
          required, but a large donation to temple coffers may
          overcome a deficiency in talent.  Acolyte training takes
          seven years.  The church is a popular career for the second
          (or later) sons of nobility, or for devout characters of
          lesser birth.  The complex mysteries of church doctrine are
          described in <em>Religion</em>.
        </p>
        <p>
          Each church has holy scriptures written in a particular
          language and script: Churches teach this language and script
          to all Acolytes.  Three churches perform their ceremonies
          and rituals in a private (secret) language in addition to
          their church language.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Church</th><th>Language</th><th>Script</th><th>Temple Tongue</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Agrik</td><td>Azeryani</td><td>Zerin</td><td>Surikal</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Halea</td><td>Karuia</td><td>Zerin</td><td></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Ilvir</td><td>Old Jarinese</td><td>Khruni</td><td>Ivashi</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Larani</td><td>Emela</td><td>Khruni</td><td></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Morgath</td><td>Azeri</td><td>Nuvesarl</td><td>Ormauk</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Naveh</td><td>Besha</td><td>Neramic</td><td></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Peoni</td><td>Emela</td><td>Khruni</td><td></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Sarajin</td><td>Ivinian</td><td>Runic</td><td></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Save-K’nor</td><td>Azeri</td><td>Tianta</td><td></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Siem</td><td>Sindarin</td><td>Selenian</td><td></td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          Newly ordained clerics start play knowing some Ritual
          Invocations.  All Common invocations rated at Circle II are
          taught to clerics.  Clerics may learn other invocations.
          Also see Religion.  Clerics usually complete their training
          with little of material value.  Acolytes are unpaid and the
          simple monastic life they lead in training does not
          encourage the accumulation of worldly goods.  Newly ordained
          clerics typically own a wool robe, linen tunic and hose,
          leather sandals or boots, a dagger or staff, a simple ring
          denoting their status, and a purse of 6-36 pence.
        </p>
        <h3 id="shekpvar">Shek-P'var</h3>
        <p>
          Shek-Pvar belong to one of six ancient and esoteric
          sub-orders (convocations).  Each convocation stresses on
          certain Pvaric principles because some conflict with others.
          Most Hârnic Shek-Pvar reside in Melderyn.  Each convocation
          has its own chantries.  Chantries vary in quality according
          to a five-star scale.  The best are difficult to find and
          enter.  A high Aura is required, but most applicants can
          improve their chance of acceptance if they have the right
          family connections, sufficient funds to bestow, or an
          appropriate recommendation.
        </p>
        <ul class="explain">
          <li><em>Lyahvi:</em> Wind, Magnification, Visual Illusions</li>
          <li><em>Peleahn:</em> Fireballs, Volcanos, Movement Enhancement</li>
          <li><em>Jmorvi:</em> Weapon Creation, Prospecting/Mining, Lockboxes</li>
          <li><em>Fyvria:</em> Healing, Horticulture, Necromancy, Earthquakes</li>
          <li><em>Odivshe:</em> Waves, Precipitation, Movement Reduction</li>
          <li><em>Savorya:</em> Divination, Written Works, Memory Suppression</li>
          <li><em>Neutral:</em> Counter-Magic, Interworld Travel, Energy Storage</li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          When Mavari learn how to attune to their element, they are
          taught to let a small amount of Principle exist within their
          Aura.  Attunement must be done slowly and carefully, and it
          takes months before sufficient Principle can reside within
          the Aura to allow spells to be cast.  Mages refer to this
          Aura-resident Principle as their Foundation.  With time and
          practice, Foundations can be increased in size to
          accommodate Principle from other convocations.  A gifted
          Mavari will sometimes join a convocation in opposition to
          his Sunsign.  This gives him an advantage when learning
          spells of other convocations in the future, although it will
          impede his early career.  A Shek-Pvar Satia-Mavari departs
          from their chantry after five to seven years apprenticeship.
        </p>
        <h3 id="military">Military</h3>
        <p>
          A military career provides good weapon skills, useful social
          contacts, and a good opportunity for advancement in society.
          Of course, it might also be dangerous.  Only individuals
          with good Strength, Stamina, and Will should consider this
          vocation.  The sunsigns Ahnu, Angberelius, and Aralius are
          favored for warriors.
        </p>
        <ul class="explain">
          <li>
            <em>Unarmoured Foot [UF]</em> Unarmoured foot are most
            often found in Militia formations.  Such troops wear
            ordinary clothing and may be equipped with homemade
            weapons.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Light Foot [LF]</em> Typical light footmen wear
            incomplete leather and are equipped with a spear, shield,
            and a knife or dagger.  Light foot are the fundamental
            troop type, and form the bulk of most standing armies.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Medium Foot [MF]</em> Medium Foot have better weapons,
            most likely a spear, shortsword, shield, and better
            armour, perhaps some scale or mail.  They are nearly
            always better trained and more experienced.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Heavy Foot [HF]</em> The only permanent heavy foot
            found on Hârn are elite High Guard units within the
            dwarven army of Azadmere.  Heavy foot carry heavy weapons
            like a battleaxe and are armoured with mail &#0038; quilt.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Unarmoured Horse [UH]</em> Lightly armed troops used
            primarily for intelligence gathering, courier service, and
            light skirmishing.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Light Horse [LH]</em> A light cavalryman is usually
            equipped with a lance or spear, shield, shortsword and
            mostly leather armour.  He can be used in the same role as
            unarmoured horse, or used en masse in battle.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Medium Horse [MH]</em> Riders are well-armoured in
            scale/mail with a good assortment of weapons.  In feudal
            societies, medium horsemen are invariably knights or
            squires.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Heavy Horse [HH]</em> The heavy cavalryman has
            well-padded mail from head to foot and may have
            strategically located plate.  He carries lance, sword, and
            shield, and usually other weapons as well.  Heavy horsemen
            are almost always noble and are primarily used as shock
            cavalry on the battlefield.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Shortbow [SB]</em> A light footman equipped with a
            shortbow, and bearing light melee weapons and a
            roundshield or buckler.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Longbow [LB]</em> A light footman equipped with a
            longbow.  Longbowmen require years of training and are
            quite rare.  They are well paid.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          Because of the pervasive military influence of the Azeryan
          Empire, the Azeri names for military ranks are in common use
          throughout Northwestern Lythia.
        </p>
        <p>
          Five enlisted ranks are in general use.  These are rarely
          filled by nobles, who would consider them beneath their
          station.  <em>Molak:</em> the common soldier.  Status and
          remuneration vary according to special skills and unit type.
          <em>Arkalin:</em> commands a manus of five men; himself and
          four Molaks.  <em>Melbrin:</em> commands a decad of ten men;
          himself, one Arkalin, and eight Molaks.  <em>Molarin:</em>
          commands a company of twenty men; himself, one Melbrin, two
          Arkalins, and sixteen Molaks.  A cavalry Molarin commands a
          squadron.  <em>Armolarin:</em> the most senior Molarin in a
          centad.  He is the principal liaison between officers and
          men, and is often the “real” commander of a Centad.
        </p>
        <p>
          Officers are gentlemen.  A commoner rising to officer rank
          is also invariably knighted.  There is widespread belief
          that leaders must be noble, although there is no law to that
          effect.  Five officer ranks exist. <em>Hulhurin:</em> junior
          staff officer, and deputy commander of a Centad.  May also
          command an auxiliary company.  <em>Hethrin:</em> commander
          of a Centad, or a Cohort staff officer.  <em>Kurlin:</em>
          senior staff officer, and deputy commander of a Cohort.
          <em>Berheth:</em> commander of a Cohort.  <em>Tharin:</em>
          commander of a Legion, which has two or more Cohorts.
        </p>
        <p>
          Light horse units have the same ranks as infantry officers,
          except there is no Decad command.  Medium and Heavy horse
          units differ at Manus and Squadron level.
          <em>Chalisir:</em> any trooper in a medium or heavy horse
          unit.  A manus will be commanded by a senior Chalisir.
          <em>Kephiri:</em> commander of a Squadron of medium or heavy
          horse.
        </p>
        <p>
          Most units let individuals enlist at age 16, and discourage
          those over 30.  Interested individuals must contact a unit.
          The recruiting officer will ask about the person’s
          background, and military experience.  A recommendation from
          someone in the unit might be helpful, and some Knight units
          (including the Khuzdul High Guard) require applicants to be
          noble.
        </p>
        <p>
          Having completed four years of service, one may now elect to
          continue his military career or muster-out of the army to
          follow some other occupation.  Guard and legionnaire units
          require a one year contract at the end of which a
          Re-enlistment Incentive may be offered to sign up for
          another twelve months.  Irregular units have less formal
          contracts, most likely just a handshake or an oath, but the
          effect is the same.
        </p>
        <p>
          Military wages are traditionally paid quarterly, but are
          listed monthly for comparison with other incomes.
          Considering the danger, wages are low, but armies offer
          various other benefits, and sometimes deliver them.  These
          include food and shelter, and the opportunity to collect
          booty.  The wage table gives monthly base pay.  Elite units
          may get more, although some elite units in which men serve
          for honor may get less.  It is not unusual for a soldier to
          work long stretches followed by long furloughs.  Armies are
          generous with (unpaid) leave in peacetime.  All foot units
          know the ranks Molak, Arkalin, Melbrin, Molarin, and
          Armolarin.  The pay listed is for Molaks, every next rank
          has a pay increase of 1/4 over the previous rank on the
          Molak’s base.  E.g. a Longbow Melbrin earns a monthly 108d.
          Light Horse units have the ranks Molak, Arkalin, Molarin,
          and Armolarin and progress 96d, 120d, 180d, and 216d.
          Medium and Heavy Horse units only have the ranks of Chalasir
          and Kephiri, of which the Kephiri earn +96d monthly over the
          base pay for Chalasirs.
        </p>
        <p>
          Traditionally, a soldier may keep 2/3 of booty collected,
          giving 1/3 to the next highest rank, who gives 1/3 to the
          next highest rank, and so on.  High ranking officers can get
          very rich with this scheme.  Cash bonuses are sometimes
          given for long, distinguished service, or as a re-enlistment
          incentive.  There is no typical amount, although a bonus
          would rarely exceed a month's pay.
        </p>
        <p>
          Standing armies typically offer land grants to soldiers
          after twenty years service.  Monetary pensions are rare, but
          “half-pay for life” might be awarded to a soldier who has
          distinguished himself in some way.  When a soldier is maimed
          in the course of duty, he is discharged with a lump sum
          bonus rather than a pension.  The amount is two to twelve
          months pay, depending on the nature of the injury and wealth
          of the unit.  Few armies provide survivor benefits.  A bonus
          of about six month's pay might be provided to a widow in
          exceptional cases.  More commonly, the deceased's comrades
          will make a collection.
        </p>
        <p>
          A cohort, ideally, consists of two centads of light foot,
          one of medium foot and one of light footbowmen (shortbow or
          longbow).  In addition, there are often auxiliary units,
          such as companies of engineers (sappers), artillery (siege
          engines), light cavalry (scouts), medical, ostlers,
          weaponcrafters, etc..  In practice a Cohort may contain from
          two to six Centads, each consisting of two to eight
          Companies.  The economic realities of manning, equipping,
          and supporting military units have always overwhelmed the
          neat organizational plans of staff officers.  Each centad
          ideally has 100 men, grouped into 5 companies, lead by a
          Hethrin.  Each company consists of 2 decads and each decad
          has 2 manus.
        </p>
        <p>
          Some states, like Azeryan, group their cohorts into legions.
          The ideal Azeryani legion consists of four cohorts plus
          various auxiliary or reserve units attached to the legion
          HQ.  On Hârn, legions exist only in the Thardic Republic
          where they tend to be little more than large cohorts.
        </p>
        <p>
          Full strength cavalry cohorts are rare.  It is simply too
          expensive to maintain such units in peacetime.  The cohort
          shown, which exists only in the dreams of Lord Marshals,
          contains one centad of regular light horse, two centads of
          feudal medium horse, and one centad of feudal heavy horse.
          From mid-spring to mid-autumn, one or two squadrons of each
          feudal centad might be manned by knights doing their
          military service.  Other squadrons would be inactive until a
          military emergency arises.  Feudal units might be virtually
          devoid of personnel in winter.  Formally., a squadron
          consists of 10 riders, and is split into two manus.  Most
          cavalry tends to be deployed in small units of squadron or
          centad strength and massed only for battle.  There are, of
          course, exceptions, such as the large bodies of horse
          defending Shorkyne and Trierzon's borders.  Imperial cavalry
          tends to be mostly light.  Azeryan, for example, uses
          cavalry in a supporting role (scouts and skirmishers), as
          does Tharda.  This is mostly due to the lack of a feudal
          societal class.  The Azeryani do, however, hire foreign
          knights to serve in some special forces.  Logistical
          problems are different for cavalry units.  Auxiliary forces,
          weaponcrafters, ostlers, transport, engineers, and the like
          are all slower than cavalry, and tend to get left behind.
          Units, even small ones, may have their own "field
          households" (messes) in tow. These too, may straggle.
        </p>
        <h3 id="physician">Physician</h3>
        <p>
          Healing is a widely-practiced art.  Clerics of Peoni have
          considerable medical expertise.  Nearly all lay-folk,
          especially in rural areas, have some understanding of herbal
          remedies.  Most warriors know emergency treatments for
          battlefield wounds.
        </p>
        <p>
          Those who practice the healing arts full-time generally
          belong to the Society of Physicians, a loosely-organized
          guild.  The Society does not care much about preserving its
          monopoly, and makes little attempt to maintain standards.
          Some masters are incompetent quacks, while others are
          highly-skilled surgeons.  However, a physician who maims or
          kills too many patients will soon encounter difficulties
          from outraged friends and relatives.
        </p>
        <p>
          Master physicians may take on as many apprentices as they
          wish.  There are no journeymen in the Society, nor bonded
          masters in the normal sense; masters may take employment as
          they see fit.  Many masters are associated with the church
          of Peoni, and some dabble in the arcane arts.  Most
          physicians confine themselves to the treatment of minor
          ailments.  Fees vary dramatically, sometimes according to
          the skill brought to bear, but mostly according to
          reputation.  Fees typically range from 3d for fairly basic
          first aid to 240d for “major” surgery.  Medicines, provided
          by the Apothecaries’ Guild, and hospital care (rare) can
          double or triple fees.
        </p>
        <p>
          When people get sick or wounded, they are advised to get the
          best first aid available, and then seek someone with a
          decent Physician Mastery as soon as possible.  Carrying a
          good supply of bandages and herbal remedies is always a good
          idea.  Hârnic doctors are far more competent than their
          medieval Terran colleagues.  They know, for example, it’s a
          good idea to keep open wounds and surgical instruments as
          clean as possible, although they do not know why.  One
          theory has to do with fiery, invisible elementals which can
          be driven off with hot water.  If no doctor is available any
          friend can administer treatment and self-treatment is always
          possible (modified by Will at GM discretion).
        </p>
        <p>
          Esoteric Medical Treatments exist. <em>Spells:</em> For
          information on magical healing, see HârnMaster
          Magic. <em>Rituals:</em> For information on divine and
          cleric healing, see Religion. <em>Psionics:</em> For
          information on Psionic healing, see Psionics.
        </p>
        <ul class="explain">
          <li>
            <em>Amputate:</em> Surgical amputation is the only
            treatment for Grievous Frost and may be used to halt
            infection spreading. The afflicted body part is removed,
            but a new Serious or Grievous wound is created according
            to the operation’s success.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Bleeder:</em> Treatment must be continued until
            bleeding stops.  The patient may die under treatment.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Clean and Dress:</em> Takes a few minutes and requires
            water and bandages.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Compress:</em> Apply cold compress for several
            minutes.  Herbal remedies and balms reduce swelling.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Splint:</em> Setting bone and splinting.  Takes
            several minutes.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Surgery:</em> Includes cleaning and dressing the
            wound.  Takes up to an hour.  Requires sharp knives, and a
            needle and thread for sutures.  Anesthetic is highly
            recommended (patients tend to struggle and whimper
            otherwise) and disinfectants are a good idea too.  Such
            items may be purchased from good apothecaries and improve
            Treatment.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Warming:</em> Gentle warming (blanket, healthy
            person’s flesh, etc.) of the injury for a few hours.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="psi">Psionics</h1>
        <p>
          Psionic talents are native, psychic abilities some people
          possess, but may be unaware of.  Since it requires years of
          practice to properly employ Psionic talents, they are within
          the sphere of the Guild of Arcane Lore.  Those endowed may
          notice some of the odd effects produced by their latent
          Psionic abilities to level * (one the five-star scale).
          Some learn of their ability when another person with a
          developed talent is able to sense and inform them of its
          presence.  Some talents are never discovered and remain
          dormant forever.  Individuals who wish to became a mage are
          more likely to be accepted as an apprentice if they have an
          active Psionic talent.
        </p>
        <p>
          Psionic Talents at one star are dormant.  Anyone with a
          dormant talent is unaware of its existence.  No conscious
          development of dormant talents is possible.  However,
          exposure to powerful Psionic events or artifacts may
          stimulate a dormant talent.  Once the talent exceeds *, it
          becomes known to the person possessing it.  A dormant talent
          may reveal its nature with Psionic Episodes.  In later parts
          of the dormant stage, frequent Psionic episodes can lead to
          apprehensions that the person is insane, and may cause
          well-meaning observers to attempt cures or confinement.
          This can be awkward when the person does not know the cause
          of the problem.
        </p>
        <p>
          Once a talent develops past the dormant stage, it may be
          developed more or less normally.  The individual must
          meditate (not sleep!) for at least 8 hours of a day to gain
          new insights.  Anyone with an active Psionic talent can
          attempt to use it at anytime, provided the character is
          conscious.  Using Psionic talents is tiring, regardless,
          whether or not the attempt is successful.  Fatigue can also
          be accumulated after a Psionic episode.  Particularly
          stressing invocations may cause the invoker to fall
          unconscious and also suffers Psionic Blindness, the complete
          inability to use any Psionic talent, for several hours.
          Sometimes unpredictable and/or unanticipated results may
          occur when invoking a Psionic talent.  Possibilities for
          misfires are given in the talent descriptions.  Psionic
          episodes occur randomly but are more likely, when a talent
          is used often or for extended periods of time.
        </p>
        <p>
          Medium, Prescience, and Sensitivity are talents which may be
          stimulated by appropriate phenomena, which is called passive
          triggering.  Medium may be triggered by the presence of
          ethereals, Prescience by imminent danger, and Sensitivity by
          a Psionic or magical residue/effect.  If the stimulus is
          weak, the character is less likely to be alerted.  When
          passive triggering occurs, the owner is given minimal
          information.  If the character wants more information, the
          talent must be used actively (with fatigue being a
          consequence).
        </p>
        <p>
          Two people with the same Psionic talent may wish to pool
          their efforts in invoking the talent.  This may be done if
          skin contact is established by grasping hands, etc. and skin
          contact is maintained during the time spent invoking the
          talent.  Under unknown circumstances ritual procedure may
          need to be followed in order to form the necessary “fusion”
          between invokers.  This will become known to the affected
          invokers instinctively.
        </p>
        <p>
          The following talents are known by the guild.  No percentages
          are given, because talents are too rare to gather sufficient
          statistics.  While Psionics are more instinctive than
          spells, concepts such as Spellfire Timing, Modeling,
          Detection, Noise, and Foci, all have application.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <td><a href="#charm">Charm</a></td>
            <td><a href="#clairvoyance">Clairvoyance</a></td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h4 id="charm">Charm</h4>
        <ul class="explain">
          <li>
            <em>Psionic Episodes:</em> Brief hallucinations or
            illusions, headaches in nearby persons, sudden dizziness,
            people having bad luck or unusual clumsiness in the
            invoker’s presence.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Misfire:</em> The invoker, or a random person/animal
            nearby, suffers the talent’s effect.  Sometimes the
            invoker gets a severe headache instead.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          A Psionic talent to influence the mind of another person
          (victim).  The usual effect is to “freeze” the victim in
          place for a limited period of time. In order to invoke the
          talent successfully, eye contact between the invoker and the
          victim is necessary, but only for a momentary glance. The
          maximum distance at which effective eye contact can occur is
          approximately 10 yards.  The effect remains in place until
          the attacker stops gazing at the victim.
        </p>
        <h4 id="clairvoyance">Clairvoyance</h4>
        <ul class="explain">
          <li>
            <em>Psionic Episodes:</em> Vivid dreams of faraway people
            and things.  Dizziness, disorientation, confusion,
            headaches, sleepwalking, blurred vision, or mirage-like
            hallucinations can also occur.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Misfire:</em> False or random information is given to
            the clairvoyant.  Sometimes, severe headaches that cause
            temporary blindness occurs.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          The ability to visualize events currently occurring at a
          remote location.  A target may sense the attention of a
          clairvoyant.  The psychic enters a trance and after the
          first minute gets a clear image of some object, person, or
          location that he is familiar with.  The image may be moving
          and is of the current state.  Sensory perception is normal
          but with narrow focus on the object.  Clairvoyance may be
          used in either of two ways: <em>Near:</em> The clairvoyant
          enters a trance to transfer their point of perception to a
          location.  The location must be familiar to the clairvoyant.
          <em>Far:</em> The clairvoyant enters a trance sand attempts
          to focus on a specific, remote person or object whose
          location may not be known.  The clairvoyant does this by
          visualizing the person’s face (or by describing the object).
          There are no range restrictions, but there is also no chance
          to listen or smell.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="reli">Religion</h1>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="ritual">Rituals</h1>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="comb">Combat</h1>
      </div>
      <!--
        <p>
          Conversion of Skills.  The actual formula is <em>level =
          log<sub>10</sub>(19&#160;*&#160;skill/100/(1&#160;-&#160;skill/100))</em> in
          the range <em>5&#160;-&#160;95</em>.  Beyond <em>95</em>, the formula
          is <em>3.5 log<sub>10</sub>(x&#160;-&#160;94)&#160;+&#160;25.4</em>. Below <n5/>
          the regression is <em>1:1</em>. as shown in the table.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>0</th><th>1</th><th>2</th><th>3</th><th>4</th>
            <th>5</th><th>6</th><th>7</th><th>8</th><th>9</th>
            <th>10</th><th>11</th><th>12</th><th>13</th><th>14</th>
            <th>15</th><th>16</th><th>17</th><th>18</th><th>19</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>-5</td><td>-4</td><td>-3</td><td>-2</td><td>-1</td>
            <td>0</td><td>1</td><td>2</td><td>2</td><td>3</td>
            <td>3</td><td>4</td><td>4</td><td>5</td><td>5</td>
            <td>5</td><td>6</td><td>6</td><td>6</td><td>6</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>20</th><th>21</th><th>22</th><th>23</th><th>24</th>
            <th>25</th><th>26</th><th>27</th><th>28</th><th>29</th>
            <th>30</th><th>31</th><th>32</th><th>33</th><th>34</th>
            <th>35</th><th>36</th><th>37</th><th>38</th><th>39</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>7</td><td>7</td><td>7</td><td>8</td><td>8</td>
            <td>8</td><td>8</td><td>8</td><td>9</td><td>9</td>
            <td>9</td><td>9</td><td>10</td><td>10</td><td>10</td>
            <td>10</td><td>10</td><td>10</td><td>11</td><td>11</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>40</th><th>41</th><th>42</th><th>43</th><th>44</th>
            <th>45</th><th>46</th><th>47</th><th>48</th><th>49</th>
            <th>50</th><th>51</th><th>52</th><th>53</th><th>54</th>
            <th>55</th><th>56</th><th>57</th><th>58</th><th>59</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>11</td><td>11</td><td>11</td><td>12</td><td>12</td>
            <td>12</td><td>12</td><td>12</td><td>12</td><td>13</td>
            <td>13</td><td>13</td><td>13</td><td>13</td><td>13</td>
            <td>14</td><td>14</td><td>14</td><td>14</td><td>14</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>60</th><th>61</th><th>62</th><th>63</th><th>64</th>
            <th>65</th><th>66</th><th>67</th><th>68</th><th>69</th>
            <th>70</th><th>71</th><th>72</th><th>73</th><th>74</th>
            <th>75</th><th>76</th><th>77</th><th>78</th><th>79</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>15</td><td>15</td><td>15</td><td>15</td><td>15</td>
            <td>15</td><td>16</td><td>16</td><td>16</td><td>16</td>
            <td>16</td><td>17</td><td>17</td><td>17</td><td>17</td>
            <td>18</td><td>18</td><td>18</td><td>18</td><td>19</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>80</th><th>81</th><th>82</th><th>83</th><th>84</th>
            <th>85</th><th>86</th><th>87</th><th>88</th><th>89</th>
            <th>90</th><th>91</th><th>92</th><th>93</th><th>94</th>
            <th>95</th><th>96</th><th>97</th><th>98</th><th>99</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>19</td><td>19</td><td>19</td><td>20</td><td>20</td>
            <td>20</td><td>21</td><td>21</td><td>21</td><td>22</td>
            <td>22</td><td>23</td><td>23</td><td>24</td><td>25</td>
            <td>26</td><td>26</td><td>27</td><td>28</td><td>28</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>100</th><th>101</th><th>102</th><th>103</th><th>104</th>
            <th>105</th><th>106</th><th>107</th><th>108</th><th>109</th>
            <th>110</th><th>111</th><th>112</th><th>113</th><th>114</th>
            <th>115</th><th>116</th><th>117</th><th>118</th><th>119</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>28</td><td>28</td><td>29</td><td>29</td><td>29</td>
            <td>29</td><td>29</td><td>29</td><td>29</td><td>30</td>
            <td>30</td><td>30</td><td>30</td><td>30</td><td>30</td>
            <td>30</td><td>30</td><td>30</td><td>30</td><td>30</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          Conversion of Attributes. The actual formula is <em>level&#160;=&#160;2&#160;*&#160;(attribute&#160;-&#160;10.5)</em>.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>1</th><th>2</th><th>3</th><th>4</th><th>5</th>
            <th>6</th><th>7</th><th>8</th><th>9</th><th>10</th>
            <th>11</th><th>12</th><th>13</th><th>14</th><th>15</th>
            <th>16</th><th>17</th><th>18</th><th>19</th><th>20</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>-19</td><td>-17</td><td>-15</td><td>-13</td><td>-11</td>
            <td>-9</td><td>-7</td><td>-5</td><td>-3</td><td>-1</td>
            <td>1</td><td>3</td><td>5</td><td>7</td><td>9</td>
            <td>11</td><td>13</td><td>15</td><td>17</td><td>19</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
      </div>
        <p>
          Where multiple scalable dimensions are given, a certain
          skill level only applies to one, i.e. of multiple dimensions
          shall be increased, multiple skill levels must be available.
          Specialties apply as per "original" rules, in particular at
          higher levels, for each skill.  The source for the skill names
          is <em>Harnmaster 3</em>.
        </p>
        <h3 id="learn">Learning</h3>
        <p>
          Learning is modelled by succeeding an active roll with level
          <n0/> against a passive level of the current skill.  Note that
          rolling 10 non-stop events can be shortened into rolling a
          <n1/> with a <d10/>.  Learning is not applicable to attributes.
        </p>
        <p>          
          Such rolls may be made once a month in which the skill was used
          reasonably often. Usually only three such rolls apply. A
          <em>combined</em> roll with the <em>SB</em> is made, with a bonus
          for equal skill of <n5/> (see the main page on <em>Combination</em>).
          A teacher can also be combined with his own skill - <n10/> and a
          bonus (row index) of <n5/>.  This assumes that the teacher is
          available almost always during that time.
        </p>
        <p>
          <b>Example:</b> Suppose your skill is at <n5/>, your teacher has a
          skill of <n12/> and your SB is a <n3/>.  According to the rules, we
          should first take the highest of the three parameters to be
          combined into a single skill roll.  That is <n3/> and <n2/>
          (<n12/>&#160;-&#160;<n10/>).  The third is <n0/>.  (Remember your active level
          is <n0/> in this case.)  Taking the difference of
          the first two, we have a column index of <n1/> into the combination
          table and we read in the fifth row a <n5/>, which will be added to <n3/>
          (the higher of the two numbers) to yield an <n8/>. To add in the 
          third (<n0/>), we take the difference again (<n8/>) as column index
          and find in the fifth row a <n2/> that is added to the previous
          result (<n8/>) for a total of <n10/>.  That is the active skill
          level to roll against your current skill level (<n5/>) to improve.
          We are pitting a <n10/> against a <n5/> with roughly an 80% chance
          of success and upon success the skill level is increased to <n6/>.
        </p>
        <p>
          If a more pragmatic approach is desired, use the following "reversed"
          table for finding the addition.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Difference</th><td>0-1</td><td>2-3</td><td>4-6</td><td>7-10</td><td>11-19</td><td>20+</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Bonus</th><td>5</td><td>4</td><td>3</td><td>2</td><td>1</td><td>0</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h4 id="special">Specialization</h4>
        <p>
          Skills listed as specialization are treated as <em>Decomposition</em>
          from the main rules. Learning (q.v.) should be applied to the
          main/average skill. If so desired, specializations may be learned
          separately, but the restrictions on decomposition applies and the
          number of rolls for learning each month. 
        </p>
        <h4 id="develop">Character (PC) Development</h4>
        <p>
          Averages (expected values) should be generously applied during
          character creation. Assume learning start at the age of 10 years.
          The following table shows the time it takes to reach a certain skill
          level.  For instance, since the typical teacher has a level of <n20/>
          that would mean rolling with a <n10/> against a passive level of <n0/>,
          i.e. at +<n10/> without SB adjustment.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th></th>
            <th>+10</th><th>+9</th><th>+8</th><th>+7</th><th>+6</th><th>+5</th><th>+4</th><th>+3</th><th>+2</th><th>+1</th><th>0</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>1</th><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>2</td><td>2</td><td>2</td><td>2</td><td>2</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>2</th><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>4</td><td>4</td><td>5</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>3</th><td>4</td><td>4</td><td>4</td><td>4</td><td>4</td><td>5</td><td>5</td><td>5</td><td>6</td><td>7</td><td>9</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>4</th><td>5</td><td>5</td><td>6</td><td>6</td><td>6</td><td>6</td><td>7</td><td>8</td><td>9</td><td>11</td><td>13</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>5</th><td>7</td><td>7</td><td>7</td><td>7</td><td>8</td><td>8</td><td>9</td><td>10</td><td>12</td><td>15</td><td>18</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>6</th><td>8</td><td>8</td><td>9</td><td>9</td><td>10</td><td>11</td><td>12</td><td>14</td><td>17</td><td>20</td><td>25</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>7</th><td>10</td><td>10</td><td>11</td><td>11</td><td>12</td><td>13</td><td>15</td><td>18</td><td>22</td><td>27</td><td>34</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>8</th><td>11</td><td>12</td><td>12</td><td>13</td><td>15</td><td>17</td><td>20</td><td>24</td><td>29</td><td>36</td><td>45</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>9</th><td>13</td><td>14</td><td>15</td><td>16</td><td>18</td><td>21</td><td>25</td><td>31</td><td>38</td><td>47</td><td>58</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>10</th><td>15</td><td>16</td><td>18</td><td>20</td><td>23</td><td>27</td><td>32</td><td>39</td><td>48</td><td>60</td><td>75</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>11</th><td>17</td><td>19</td><td>21</td><td>24</td><td>28</td><td>34</td><td>41</td><td>50</td><td>62</td><td>77</td><td>96</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>12</th><td>20</td><td>22</td><td>25</td><td>30</td><td>35</td><td>42</td><td>51</td><td>63</td><td>79</td><td>98</td><td>122</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>13</th><td>24</td><td>27</td><td>31</td><td>36</td><td>44</td><td>53</td><td>65</td><td>80</td><td>99</td><td>124</td><td>155</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>14</th><td>28</td><td>32</td><td>38</td><td>45</td><td>54</td><td>66</td><td>82</td><td>101</td><td>126</td><td>157</td><td>196</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>15</th><td>34</td><td>39</td><td>46</td><td>56</td><td>68</td><td>83</td><td>103</td><td>127</td><td>158</td><td>198</td><td>247</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>16</th><td>40</td><td>48</td><td>57</td><td>69</td><td>85</td><td>104</td><td>129</td><td>160</td><td>199</td><td>249</td><td>311</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>17</th><td>49</td><td>58</td><td>70</td><td>86</td><td>105</td><td>130</td><td>162</td><td>201</td><td>250</td><td>311</td><td>391</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>18</th><td>60</td><td>72</td><td>87</td><td>107</td><td>132</td><td>163</td><td>202</td><td>252</td><td>314</td><td>393</td><td>491</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>19</th><td>73</td><td>89</td><td>108</td><td>133</td><td>164</td><td>204</td><td>254</td><td>316</td><td>394</td><td>493</td><td>616</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>20</th><td>90</td><td>110</td><td>134</td><td>166</td><td>205</td><td>255</td><td>318</td><td>396</td><td>494</td><td>617</td><td>772</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>21</th><td>111</td><td>136</td><td>167</td><td>207</td><td>257</td><td>319</td><td>398</td><td>496</td><td>619</td><td>722</td><td>967</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>22</th><td>137</td><td>168</td><td>208</td><td>258</td><td>320</td><td>399</td><td>497</td><td>621</td><td>775</td><td>969</td><td>...</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>23</th><td>170</td><td>209</td><td>259</td><td>322</td><td>400</td><td>499</td><td>602</td><td>777</td><td>970</td><td>...</td><td>...</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>24</th><td>211</td><td>261</td><td>323</td><td>402</td><td>500</td><td>624</td><td>778</td><td>972</td><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>25</th><td>262</td><td>325</td><td>403</td><td>502</td><td>625</td><td>780</td><td>974</td><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>26</th><td>326</td><td>404</td><td>503</td><td>627</td><td>781</td><td>976</td><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>27</th><td>406</td><td>504</td><td>628</td><td>783</td><td>976</td><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>28</th><td>506</td><td>629</td><td>784</td><td>978</td><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>29</th><td>631</td><td>785</td><td>979</td><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>30</th><td>787</td><td>981</td><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td><td>...</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          Extending the table is relatively easy for the mathematically
          inclined. Denote the row <em>index</em> by <em>i</em> and let
          <em>j</em> be the bonus (or penalty). Then each field in the
          table is caclulated as
        </p>
        <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
          <munderover><mo>&#8721;</mo><mn>k = 1</mn><mn>j</mn></munderover>
          <mfrac>
            <mrow><mn>(5/4)</mn><mi>(9/4)</mi></mrow>
            <mrow><mn>9/4</mn><mo>−</mo><msup><mi>(4/5)</mi><mn>k</mn></msup></mrow>
          </mfrac>
          <mn> + </mn>
          <munderover><mo>&#8721;</mo><mn>k = 0</mn><mn>i - j - 1</mn></munderover>
          <mn>(9/4)</mn><mo></mo><msup><mi>(5/4)</mi><mn>k</mn></msup>
        </math>
        <p>
          This is a ready-made calculation of "generous" use of expected values mentioned above.
        </p>
        <p>
          For career development, take the sum of the number of all SBs
          (e.g. SB/2 and SB/3 would be 5) for a career.  Now take the
          duration of learning for that career in months (e.g. 4 years) and
          multiply by <n3/> (e.g. <em>144</em>), which is the number of
          rolls. This number should be distributed among the skills according
          to the multiplicity among the skills (e.g. <em>2/5</em> for
          <em>58</em> and <em>3/5</em> for <em>86</em>). Any base addtion,
          such as scripts, count as <n1/> SB for every <n20/> points, including
          any fractions thereof.
        </p>
        <h4>Extended Example:</h4> 
        <p>
          Assume that the PC in question has an SB of <n1/>
          in all phyiscal attributes and -<n1/> in all other cases. His sunsign 
          is Ulandus.
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>Family Skills:</em> Assume that the PC stays with his
          family until the age of 14.  Assume his parents are Animal Trainers.
          The PCs is exposed to the skills according to his interest and can
          decide on how to distribute <em>4&#160;*&#160;12&#160;*&#160;3&#160;=&#160;144</em> rolls. Let's assume the 
          PCs puts all into Animal Craft. His net SB is
          <em>(1&#160;-&#160;1&#160;-&#160;1)/3&#160;+&#160;1/2</em>, which we round to <n0/>.  He has no teacher in this
          phase, he just picks things up as they gain his interest. Adding his own
          starting skill of <n0/> to <n0/> through the table, gives a <n5/>.  This
          means that the PCs gains <em>17</em> after <em>131</em> rolls.  The
          remaining <em>13</em> rolls are lost, can be rolled
          individually, or spread among the other available family skills.<br/>
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>Automatic skills:</em> An NN would have these skills at
          <n10/> in this setting.  We make this provision, assuming that it fits
          with the general skill intention.  Note that generally NN should have a
          <n0/>, so adding <n10/> is actually only making learning more difficult
          From the previous example we infer that NN would get a bonus of <n5/>,
          which gives him 27 rolls. Our PC has an SB of 
          <em>(1&#160;+&#160;1&#160;+&#160;1)/3&#160;+&#160;2/2</em>, which is <n2/>. Adding this to the <n0/>
          skill level, we get <n6/> as total. This gives us 23 rolls needed to reach
          <n10/>. The remaining 4 rolls can only be used individually. 
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>Occupational skills:</em> Our PC chooses to be an Apothecary, a profession with
          an apprenticeship of 6 years.  That means a total of <em>6&#160;*&#160;12&#160;*&#160;3&#160;=&#160;216</em>
          rolls.  Script being in the selection of skills counts as <em>1&#160;+&#160;70/20&#160;=&#160;4&#160;1/2</em> 
          SB. For Herblore this means the PC gets <em>216&#160;*&#160;4&#160;/&#160;(14&#160;1/2)&#160;=&#160;60</em>
          (rounded) rolls. His SB is <em>(-1&#160;-1&#160;-1)/3&#160;+&#160;3/2&#160;=&#160;1</em>,
          rounded up in favor of the PC.  This time a teacher will provide a bonus
          of <n10/>.  Adding this together with the (starting) skill level of <n0/>, this
          yields a <n12/>.  We extend the table above to get to a skill level of
          <em>18</em> with <em>57</em> rolls.  As always, the remaining <n3/> rolls can be used
          individually, can be redistributed with other skills, or forfeited. 
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>Optional skills:</em> Any number of years can be used to improve
          other skills in the manner above.  A teacher of skill level <n20/> can
          be assumed, unless a guilded profession is required for the skill and
          the PC is not member of that guild.  Then probably no teacher is available,
          which can mean that a learning <em>penalty</em> of <n10/> may be applied,
          if reality cannot be assumed as "teacher".  A teacher applies to veteran
          points and militia duty, which are treated in the same way as regular
          acquisition of optional skills..
        </p>
        <h3 id="know">Knowledge</h3>
        <p>
          The description is based on the <em>expected</em> outcome,
          i.e. simply read the result rolled as index row in the table.
        </p>
        <ul class="explain">
          <li>
            <b>Level 0:</b> NN barely knows that a domain for such
            knowledge exists.  With some luck, he can guess whether a
            general topic belongs to that domain or not.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 5:</b> A single topic, one of the most obvious
            ones has been heard of and can be applied, but without
            guaranteed success.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 10:</b> With this level, the basic concepts are
            known, the more esoteric concepts have been heard of but
            cannot be applied.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 15:</b> Most concepts are known and many can be
            applied with a high degree of certainty. There are still
            areas which can be polished.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 20:</b> All concepts of the domain are known and
            can be applied with confidence.  There are only a few
            topics escaping the grasps of this expert.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 25:</b> All of the domain is understood with ease.
            It is hard to find unknown territory, although it exists.
            Improvement of the art can be conducted.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 30:</b> Mastery of the subject matter as far as
            humanly possible.  Genuine research or creation of new
            substance is possible.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <h4 id="folklore">Folklore</h4>
        <p>
          Specializations are <em>Barbarians, Recent History, History,
          Antiquity, Off-Harn, Creatures</em>, which should be treated as separate
          skills.
        </p>
        <h3 id="com">Communication</h3>
        <p>
          The description is based on the <em>expected</em> outcome,
          i.e. simply read the result rolled as index row in the table.
          When refering to patterns in the table, this applies to
          instruments (melodies and the like) for music skills as well
          as words (word order, flection, ...). Every communication skill
          has such pattern, by which communication is encoded and decoded.
        </p>
        <ul class="explain">
          <li>
            <b>Level 0:</b> NN barely knows that a domain for such
            communication exists.  Instinctively, he is wrong as often
            as he is right when judging others.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 5:</b> A single pattern, one of the most obvious
            ones can be applied, but without guaranteed success.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 10:</b> With this level, basic patterns are
            known, the more esoteric patterns have been heard of but
            cannot be applied.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 15:</b> Most patterns are known and many can be
            applied with a high degree of certainty. There are still
            areas which can be polished.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 20:</b> All patterns of the domain are known and
            can be applied with confidence.  There are only a few
            topics escaping the grasps of this expert.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 25:</b> All of the domain is communicated with ease.
            It is hard to find unknown territory, although it exists.
            Improvement of the art can be conducted.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 30:</b> Mastery of the subject matter as far as
            humanly possible.  Genuine research or creation of new
            patterns is possible.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <h4 id="intrigue">Intrigue</h4>
        <p>
          Specializations are <em>Politics, Streetwise, Rural, Social
          Class</em>, which should be treated as separate skills.
        </p>
        <h3 id="SkillExanplea">Examples</h3>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th></th>
            <th>0</th>
            <th>10</th>
            <th>20</th>
            <th>30</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Acting</th>
            <td>Play self</td>
            <td>Play archetype</td>
            <td>Play individual</td>
            <td>Play original</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Lovecraft</th>
            <td>Instinctive</td>
            <td>Experienced</td>
            <td>Professional</td>
            <td>Elite/exotic</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Musician</th>
            <td>Simple, children songs</td>
            <td>General, ritual songs</td>
            <td>Artistic songs</td>
            <td>Unique songs</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Oratory</th>
            <td>Speech</td>
            <td>People listen to you</td>
            <td>People consider you</td>
            <td>People cannot deny you</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Rhetoric</th>
            <td>Speech</td>
            <td>People listen to you</td>
            <td>People consider you</td>
            <td>People cannot deny you</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Singing</th>
            <td>Simple, child's songs</td>
            <td>General, ritual songs</td>
            <td>Artistic songs</td>
            <td>Unique songs</td>
          </tr>
          <tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="6"></th></tr><tr></tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Acrobatics (I)</th>
            <td>No tricks</td>
            <td>Simple tricks</td>
            <td>Complex tricks</td>
            <td>Original tricks</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Acrobatics (II)</th>
            <td>1x speed</td>
            <td>2x</td>
            <td>3x</td>
            <td>4x</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Climbing (I)</th>
            <td>30°</td>
            <td>60°</td>
            <td>90°</td>
            <td>120°</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Climbing (II)</th>
            <td>1/4 m/s</td>
            <td>1/2 m/s</td>
            <td>1 m/s</td>
            <td>2 m/s</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Dancing</th>
            <td>Rhythmic Move</td>
            <td>Simple, folk dance</td>
            <td>Complex, ritual dance</td>
            <td>Original dance</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Jumping (I)</th>
            <td>0,5 m ▲</td>
            <td>1 m ▲</td>
            <td>1.5 m ▲</td>
            <td>2 m ▲</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Jumping (II)</th>
            <td>8 m ▶</td>
            <td>2 m ▶</td>
            <td>4 m ▶</td>
            <td>6 m ▶</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Skiing</th>
            <td>0.5 m/s</td>
            <td>1.5 m/s</td>
            <td>2 m/s</td>
            <td>3 m/s</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Swimming (I)</th>
            <td>0.1 m/s</td>
            <td>0.6 m/s</td>
            <td>1 m/s</td>
            <td>1.5 m/s</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Swimming (II)</th>
            <td>Dive 5s</td>
            <td>Dive 15s</td>
            <td>Dive 30s</td>
            <td>Dive 60s</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Swimming (III)</th>
            <td>Bft 1</td>
            <td>Bft 3</td>
            <td>Bft 5</td>
            <td>Bft 7</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Throwing</th>
            <td>10 m</td>
            <td>30 m</td>
            <td>60m</td>
            <td>100 m</td>
          </tr>
          <tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="6"></th></tr><tr></tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Agriculture (I)</th>
            <td>10% yield</td>
            <td>30% yield</td>
            <td>100% yield</td>
            <td>150% yield</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Agriculture (II)</th>
            <td>1 kind</td>
            <td>3 kind</td>
            <td>6 kind</td>
            <td>12 kind</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Alchemy</th>
            <td>1 compound</td>
            <td>3 compounds</td>
            <td>10 compounds</td>
            <td>30 compounds</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Animalcraft (I)</th>
            <td>1 trick</td>
            <td>3 tricks</td>
            <td>10 tricks</td>
            <td>30 tricks</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Animalcraft (II)</th>
            <td>INT 6</td>
            <td>INT 5</td>
            <td>INT 4</td>
            <td>INT 3</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Astrology (I)</th>
            <td>1 in 10 correct</td>
            <td>1 in 6 correct</td>
            <td>1 in 3 correct</td>
            <td>Always correct</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Astrology (II)</th>
            <td>360 days</td>
            <td>60 days</td>
            <td>10 days</td>
            <td>2 days</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Brewing</th>
            <td>1 recipe</td>
            <td>3 recipes</td>
            <td>10 recipes</td>
            <td>30 recipes</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Ceramics (I)</th>
            <td>Quality -1</td>
            <td>Quality 0</td>
            <td>Quality 1.5</td>
            <td>Quality 3</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Ceramics (II)</th>
            <td>0 recipes</td>
            <td>1 recipe</td>
            <td>3 recipes</td>
            <td>10 recipes</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Cookery</th>
            <td>1 recipe</td>
            <td>3 recipes</td>
            <td>10 recipes</td>
            <td>30 recipes</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Drawing</th>
            <td>Simple strokes</td>
            <td>Draw/Paint</td>
            <td>Different Styles</td>
            <td>Forgery possible</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Embalming</th>
            <td>1x decay speed</td>
            <td>1/3x decay speed</td>
            <td>1/10x decay speed</td>
            <td>1/60x decay speed</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Engineering (I)</th>
            <td>Quality -1</td>
            <td>Quality 0</td>
            <td>Quality 1.5</td>
            <td>Quality 3</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Engineering (I)</th>
            <td>0 recipes</td>
            <td>1 recipe</td>
            <td>3 recipes</td>
            <td>10 recipes</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Fishing (I)</th>
            <td>10% yield</td>
            <td>30% yield</td>
            <td>100% yield</td>
            <td>150% yield</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Fishing (II)</th>
            <td>1 kind</td>
            <td>3 kind</td>
            <td>6 kind</td>
            <td>12 kind</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Fletching</th>
            <td>10% yield</td>
            <td>30% yield</td>
            <td>60% yield</td>
            <td>100% yield</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Folklore (I)</th>
            <td>Top myth</td>
            <td>Great myths</td>
            <td>Most myths</td>
            <td>All myths</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Folklore (II)</th>
            <td>10% known</td>
            <td>30% known</td>
            <td>60% known</td>
            <td>100% known</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Foraging (I)</th>
            <td>10% yield</td>
            <td>30% yield</td>
            <td>100% yield</td>
            <td>150% yield</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Foraging (II)</th>
            <td>1 kind</td>
            <td>3 kind</td>
            <td>6 kind</td>
            <td>12 kind</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Heraldry (I)</th>
            <td>1 active</td>
            <td>3 active</td>
            <td>10 active</td>
            <td>30 active</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Heraldry (II)</th>
            <td>10% passive</td>
            <td>30% passive</td>
            <td>60% passive</td>
            <td>100% passive</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Herblore (I)</th>
            <td>1 active</td>
            <td>3 active</td>
            <td>10 active</td>
            <td>30 active</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Herblore (II)</th>
            <td>10% passive</td>
            <td>30% passive</td>
            <td>60% passive</td>
            <td>100% passive</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Hidework (I)</th>
            <td>Quality -1</td>
            <td>Quality 0</td>
            <td>Quality 1.5</td>
            <td>Quality 3</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Hidework (II)</th>
            <td>0 recipes</td>
            <td>1 recipe</td>
            <td>3 recipes</td>
            <td>10 recipes</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Jewelcraft (I)</th>
            <td>Quality -1</td>
            <td>Quality 0</td>
            <td>Quality 1.5</td>
            <td>Quality 3</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Jewelcraft (II)</th>
            <td>0 recipes</td>
            <td>1 recipe</td>
            <td>3 recipes</td>
            <td>10 recipes</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Law (I)</th>
            <td>Ignore</td>
            <td>Notice</td>
            <td>Consideration</td>
            <td>Involvement</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Law (II)</th>
            <td>Local</td>
            <td>Feudal</td>
            <td>Guild</td>
            <td>Religion</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Masonry</th>
            <td>1 recipe</td>
            <td>3 recipes</td>
            <td>10 recipes</td>
            <td>30 recipes</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Mathematics</th>
            <td>Single digits</td>
            <td>Multiple digits</td>
            <td>Abstractions</td>
            <td>Unique Insights</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Metalcraft (I)</th>
            <td>Quality -1</td>
            <td>Quality 0</td>
            <td>Quality 1.5</td>
            <td>Quality 3</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Metalcraft (II)</th>
            <td>0 recipes</td>
            <td>1 recipe</td>
            <td>3 recipes</td>
            <td>10 recipes</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Milling (I)</th>
            <td>10% yield</td>
            <td>30% yield</td>
            <td>100% yield</td>
            <td>150% yield</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Milling (II)</th>
            <td>1 kind</td>
            <td>3 kind</td>
            <td>6 kind</td>
            <td>12 kind</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Perfumery</th>
            <td>1 compound</td>
            <td>3 compounds</td>
            <td>10 compounds</td>
            <td>30 compounds</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Physician</th>
            <td>HR-0</td>
            <td>HR-1</td>
            <td>HR-2</td>
            <td>HR-3</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Piloting</th>
            <td>10% yield</td>
            <td>30% yield</td>
            <td>60% yield</td>
            <td>100% yield</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Riding (I)</th>
            <td>Walk</td>
            <td>Trot</td>
            <td>Gallop</td>
            <td>Jump</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Riding (II)</th>
            <td>2 hrs</td>
            <td>4 hrs</td>
            <td>6 hrs</td>
            <td>8 hrs</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Ritual</th>
            <td>1 second</td>
            <td>1 minute</td>
            <td>1 hour</td>
            <td>5 days</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Runecraft (I)</th>
            <td>1 in 10 correct</td>
            <td>1 in 6 correct</td>
            <td>1 in 3 correct</td>
            <td>Always correct</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Runecraft (II)</th>
            <td>360 days</td>
            <td>60 days</td>
            <td>10 days</td>
            <td>2 days</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Seamanship</th>
            <td>Coracle</td>
            <td>Dingy</td>
            <td>Two-Master</td>
            <td>Any ship</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Shipwright</th>
            <td>Coracle</td>
            <td>Dingy</td>
            <td>Two-Master</td>
            <td>Any ship</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Survival</th>
            <td>Local conditions</td>
            <td>Familiar conditions</td>
            <td>Related conditions</td>
            <td>Any conditions</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Tarotry (I)</th>
            <td>1 in 10 correct</td>
            <td>1 in 6 correct</td>
            <td>1 in 3 correct</td>
            <td>Always correct</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Tarotry (II)</th>
            <td>360 days</td>
            <td>60 days</td>
            <td>10 days</td>
            <td>2 days</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Textilcraft</th>
            <td>1 recipe</td>
            <td>3 recipes</td>
            <td>10 recipes</td>
            <td>30 recipes</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Timbercraft (I)</th>
            <td>10% yield</td>
            <td>30% yield</td>
            <td>60% yield</td>
            <td>100% yield</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Timbercraft (II)</th>
            <td>1 kind</td>
            <td>3 kind</td>
            <td>6 kind</td>
            <td>12 kind</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Tracking</th>
            <td>Local conditions</td>
            <td>Familiar conditions</td>
            <td>Related conditions</td>
            <td>Any conditions</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Weaponcraft (I)</th>
            <td>Quality -1</td>
            <td>Quality 0</td>
            <td>Quality 1.5</td>
            <td>Quality 3</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Weaponcraft (II)</th>
            <td>0 recipes</td>
            <td>1 recipe</td>
            <td>3 recipes</td>
            <td>10 recipes</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Weatherlore (I)</th>
            <td>20% accurate</td>
            <td>30% accurate</td>
            <td>60%</td>
            <td>100%</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Weatherlore (II)</th>
            <td>4 hrs</td>
            <td>8 hrs</td>
            <td>24 hrs</td>
            <td>1 week</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Woodcraft (I)</th>
            <td>Quality -1</td>
            <td>Quality 0</td>
            <td>Quality 1.5</td>
            <td>Quality 3</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Woodcraft (II)</th>
            <td>0 recipes</td>
            <td>1 recipe</td>
            <td>3 recipes</td>
            <td>10 recipes</td>
          </tr>
          <tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="6"></th></tr><tr></tr>
          <tr>
            <th><em>Appraisal Error</em></th>
            <td>100% (0 - &#8734;)</td>
            <td>60% (0.4 - 2.5)</td>
            <td>20% (0.8 - 1.25)</td>
            <td>6% (0.94 - 106)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th><em>Stars</em></th>
            <td>-1</td>
            <td>&#9733;</td>
            <td>&#9733; &#9733; &#9733;</td>
            <td>&#9733; &#9733; &#9733; &#9733; &#9733;</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th><em>Enhancement</em></th>
            <td>1/10</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>2</td>
            <td>3</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th><em>Quality</em></th>
            <td>0</td>
            <td>+2</td>
            <td>+3</td>
            <td>+4</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h3 id="key">Attributes</h3>
        <h4 id="str">Move</h4>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Level</th><td>-18</td><td>-16</td><td>-14</td><td>-12</td>
            <td>-10</td><td>-8</td><td>-6</td><td>-4</td><td>-2</td>
            <td>0</td><td>2</td><td>4</td><td>6</td><td>8</td>
            <td>10</td><td>12</td><td>14</td><td>16</td><td>18</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Sprint (m/s)</th><td>2.2</td><td>2.4</td><td>2.6</td><td>2.8</td>
            <td>3</td><td>3.2</td><td>3.4</td><td>3.6</td><td>3.8</td>
            <td>4</td><td>4.4</td><td>4.8</td><td>5.2</td><td>5.6</td>
            <td>6</td><td>6.6</td><td>7.4</td><td>8.2</td><td>9</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          Humans can accelerate and decalerate as 3 m/s each second.
          Turning options are in parts of a full circle (centered around
          the direction of travel).  E.g. at 3 m/s this means 60&#176;
          off the direction of travel on either side per second.  For the
          sake of playability variance in this should be suppressed,
          although a 20% spread (for a <n10/> level difference) with Agility
          modification could be apprpriate.
        </p>
        <h4 id="str">Strength</h4>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Level</th><td>-18</td><td>-16</td><td>-14</td><td>-12</td>
            <td>-10</td><td>-8</td><td>-6</td><td>-4</td><td>-2</td>
            <td>0</td><td>2</td><td>4</td><td>6</td><td>8</td>
            <td>10</td><td>12</td><td>14</td><td>16</td><td>18</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Lift (kg)</th><td>11</td><td>13</td><td>15</td><td>17</td>
            <td>20</td><td>22</td><td>26</td><td>30</td><td>34</td>
            <td>40</td><td>44</td><td>52</td><td>60</td><td>68</td>
            <td>80</td><td>88</td><td>104</td><td>120</td><td>136</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h4 id="hear">Hearing</h4>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Level</th><td>-18</td><td>-16</td><td>-14</td><td>-12</td>
            <td>-10</td><td>-8</td><td>-6</td><td>-4</td><td>-2</td>
            <td>0</td><td>2</td><td>4</td><td>6</td><td>8</td>
            <td>10</td><td>12</td><td>14</td><td>16</td><td>18</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Distance (m)</th><td>0.75</td><td>0.94</td><td>1.2</td><td>1.5</td>
            <td>1.9</td><td>2.4</td><td>3</td><td>3.8</td><td>4.8</td>
            <td>6</td><td>7.6</td><td>9.5</td><td>12</td><td>15.1</td>
            <td>19</td><td>24</td><td>30</td><td>38</td><td>48</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          The description is based on the <em>expected</em> outcome,
          i.e. simply read the result rolled as index row in the table.
        </p>
        <ul class="explain">
          <li>
            <b>Level -20:</b> Rural Silence / Distance &#215; 1/10
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level -10:</b> Whisper / Distance &#215; 1/3
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 0:</b> Low speech / Distance &#215; 1
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 20:</b> Normal Speech / Distance &#215; 3
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 40:</b> Carts, Wagons, Combat / Distance &#215; 10
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 60:</b> Smith, Stonequarry, Skirmish / Distance &#215; 30
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 80:</b> Thunder / Distance &#215; 100
          </li>
        </ul>
        <h4 id="eye">Eyesight</h4>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Level</th><td>-18</td><td>-16</td><td>-14</td><td>-12</td>
            <td>-10</td><td>-8</td><td>-6</td><td>-4</td><td>-2</td>
            <td>0</td><td>2</td><td>4</td><td>6</td><td>8</td>
            <td>10</td><td>12</td><td>14</td><td>16</td><td>18</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Resolution (mm/m = m/km)</th><td>5.5</td><td>5.0</td><td>4.5</td><td>4.0</td>
            <td>3.6</td><td>3.2</td><td>2.9</td><td>2.6</td><td>2.3</td>
            <td>2.0</td><td>1.8</td><td>1.6</td><td>1.4</td><td>1.2</td>
            <td>1.0</td><td>0.9</td><td>0.8</td><td>0.7</td><td>0.6</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          Typical modifications are made for <em>contrast (+), movement (+),
          distraction (-), border of visual field (-)</em>
        </p>
        <svg:svg width="620" height="620">
          <svg:g transform="translate(310 310)">
            <svg:circle cx="0" cy="0" r="305" stroke="#000" stroke-width="2" fill="#009a31"/>
            <svg:text x="-124" y="0" fill="#fff" transform="scale(2.4)">-5</svg:text>
            <svg:text x="101" y="0" fill="#fff" transform="scale(2.4)">-5</svg:text>
            <svg:circle cx="0" cy="0" r="244" stroke="#000" stroke-width="2" fill="#19a644"/>
            <svg:text x="-124" y="0" fill="#fff" transform="scale(1.92)">-4</svg:text>
            <svg:text x="101" y="0" fill="#fff" transform="scale(1.92)">-4</svg:text>
            <svg:circle cx="0" cy="0" r="195" stroke="#000" stroke-width="2" fill="#48bd68"/>
            <svg:text x="-124" y="0" fill="#fff" transform="scale(1.536)">-3</svg:text>
            <svg:text x="101" y="0" fill="#fff" transform="scale(1.536)">-3</svg:text>
            <svg:circle cx="0" cy="0" r="156" stroke="#000" stroke-width="2" fill="#77d58c"/>
            <svg:text x="-124" y="0" fill="#fff" transform="scale(1.2288)">-2</svg:text>
            <svg:text x="101" y="0" fill="#fff" transform="scale(1.2288)">-2</svg:text>
            <svg:circle cx="0" cy="0" r="125" stroke="#000" stroke-width="2" fill="#a6ebb0"/>
            <svg:text x="-124" y="0" fill="#fff" transform="scale(1)">-1</svg:text>
            <svg:text x="101" y="0" fill="#fff" transform="scale(1)">-1</svg:text>
            <svg:circle cx="0" cy="0" r="100" stroke="#000" stroke-width="2" fill="#ceffce"/>
          </svg:g>
          <svg:g transform="translate(310 310) scale(0.33)">
            <svg:circle cx="0" cy="0" r="305" stroke="#444" stroke-width="2" fill="#009a31"/>
            <svg:text x="-120" y="0" fill="#fff" transform="scale(2.4)">0</svg:text>
            <svg:text x="105" y="0" fill="#fff" transform="scale(2.4)">0</svg:text>
            <svg:circle cx="0" cy="0" r="244" stroke="#444" stroke-width="2" fill="#19a644"/>
            <svg:text x="-120" y="0" fill="#fff" transform="scale(1.92)">1</svg:text>
            <svg:text x="105" y="0" fill="#fff" transform="scale(1.92)">1</svg:text>
            <svg:circle cx="0" cy="0" r="195" stroke="#444" stroke-width="2" fill="#48bd68"/>
            <svg:text x="-120" y="0" fill="#fff" transform="scale(1.536)">2</svg:text>
            <svg:text x="105" y="0" fill="#fff" transform="scale(1.536)">2</svg:text>
            <svg:circle cx="0" cy="0" r="156" stroke="#444" stroke-width="2" fill="#77d58c"/>
            <svg:text x="-120" y="0" fill="#fff" transform="scale(1.2288)">3</svg:text>
            <svg:text x="105" y="0" fill="#fff" transform="scale(1.2288)">3</svg:text>
            <svg:circle cx="0" cy="0" r="125" stroke="#444" stroke-width="2" fill="#a6ebb0"/>
            <svg:text x="-120" y="0" fill="#fff" transform="scale(1)">4</svg:text>
            <svg:text x="105" y="0" fill="#fff" transform="scale(1)">4</svg:text>
            <svg:circle cx="0" cy="0" r="100" stroke="#444" stroke-width="2" fill="#ceffce"/>
          </svg:g>
          <svg:g transform="translate(310 310) rotate(22.5)">
            <svg:path d="M-310 0 L310 0" stroke="#fff" stroke-width="2" transform="rotate(0)"/>
            <svg:path d="M-310 0 L310 0" stroke="#fff" stroke-width="2" transform="rotate(45)"/>
            <svg:path d="M-310 0 L310 0" stroke="#fff" stroke-width="2" transform="rotate(90)"/>
            <svg:path d="M-310 0 L310 0" stroke="#fff" stroke-width="2" transform="rotate(135)"/>
          </svg:g>
          <svg:text x="284" y="316" fill="#000">1</svg:text>
          <svg:text x="290" y="300" fill="#000">2</svg:text>
          <svg:text x="305" y="294" fill="#000">3</svg:text>
          <svg:text x="320" y="300" fill="#000">4</svg:text>
          <svg:text x="327" y="316" fill="#000">5</svg:text>
          <svg:text x="320" y="332" fill="#000">6</svg:text>
          <svg:text x="305" y="338" fill="#000">7</svg:text>
          <svg:text x="290" y="332" fill="#000">8</svg:text>
        </svg:svg>
        <h3 id="misc">Miscellaneous</h3>
        <p>
          The following skills are simply opposed to each other.
          Time domain factors are 1/2 or 2 respectively and
          100% = 1 minute per 2 level steps.
        </p>
        <ul class="explain">
          <li>
            Lockcraft <b>vs.</b> Lockcraft
          </li>
          <li>
            Legerdemain, Stealth <b>vs.</b> Awareness, Smell, Taste,
            Touch, and Eyesight
          </li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          Enhancement and quality should be considered separate
          dimensions for craft skills.
        </p>
        <p>
          Situational modifiers may apply, usually through reasonable
          estimates of the situation at hand.  Remember that addition
          rules for conflict resolution from the generic section of
          the rules may apply.
        </p>
        <ul class="explain">
          <li>
            <em>Load</em>: Divide the load in pounds by 10 and and
            subtract strength.  If this exceeds zero, subtract this
            from any physical or combat skill.
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>Piety</em>: Serves as skill for specific magic/religious
            rituals.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <h4 id="piety">Piety</h4>
        <ul class="explain">
          <li>
            <b>Level 0:</b> NN knows that the reigion exist but cannot
            separate it from other convocations.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 5:</b> Lip service payed to the religion and ability
            to separate it from other major faiths.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 10:</b> The main tenants of the religion are known
            and followed on individual level. Sects or heresies are not
            considered.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 15:</b> The religion is quoted often and other faiths
            routinely treated underhanded. Proselytizing is rarely attempted.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 20:</b> At this level the adherent is actively seeking
            to further the tenants of the religion outside of his immediate
            domain. Distinction between inner-religion minutiae are important.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 25:</b> Heresy is abhorred more than other religions.
            Support for the religion takes precendents over other interests
            almost always.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 30:</b> The adherent is a prophet for the religion and
            accepts otherwise serious consequences for following details of
            his faith. May invent rituals and the like.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="combat">Combat</h1>
        <h3 id="com-time">Time</h3>
        <p>
          Several factors determine how long it takes to bring a combat skill to bear.
          A premature roll can be made, by taking a penalty that matches the premature
          time to the ijury dimension.  Note that such a time interval is used looking
          for openings, keeping ones own balance, etc. and must be actively chosen.
          A point in time cannot be chosen, let alone decided upon on the spur of a moment
          The active level is determined by adding <em>Initiative</em> and the
          <em>Combat skill</em> used to attack through row <n10/>. The passive
          level is determined by <em>Dodge</em> and the <em>Combat skill</em> used to
          block or parry; also through row <n10/>.  The Dodge skill may be <n0/> but
          Agility may be added through row <n3/>.
        </p>
        <p>
          The A/D numbers are used as additional modifiers (divided by five).
          Using a weapon or a combination in the wrong hand implies a penalty of-<n2/>.
          In general, most bonusses and penalties apply to the Time dimension.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Level</th><td>-19</td><td>-18</td><td>-17</td><td>-16</td><td>-15</td><td>-14</td><td>-13</td><td>-12</td><td>-11</td><td>-10</td>
            <td>-9</td><td>-8</td><td>-7</td><td>-6</td><td>-5</td><td>-4</td><td>-3</td><td>-2</td><td>-1</td><td>0</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Time(s)</th><td>110</td><td>100</td><td>98</td><td>90</td><td>84</td><td>80</td><td>74</td><td>68</td><td>64</td><td>60</td>
            <td>56</td><td>52</td><td>49</td><td>45</td><td>42</td><td>40</td><td>37</td><td>34</td><td>32</td><td>30</td>
          </tr>
          <tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="21"></th></tr><tr></tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Level</th><td>1</td><td>2</td><td>3</td><td>4</td><td>5</td><td>6</td><td>7</td><td>8</td><td>9</td><td>10</td>
            <td>11</td><td>12</td><td>13</td><td>14</td><td>15</td><td>16</td><td>17</td><td>18</td><td>19</td><td>20</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Time(s)</th><td>28</td><td>26</td><td>25</td><td>23</td><td>21</td><td>20</td><td>19</td><td>17</td><td>16</td><td>15</td>
            <td>15</td><td>14</td><td>14</td><td>13</td><td>12</td><td>12</td><td>12</td><td>11</td><td>11</td><td>10</td>
          </tr>
          <tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="21"></th></tr><tr></tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Level</th><td>21</td><td>22</td><td>23</td><td>24</td><td>25</td><td>26</td><td>27</td><td>28</td><td>29</td><td>30</td>
            <td>31</td><td>32</td><td>33</td><td>34</td><td>35</td><td>36</td><td>37</td><td>38</td><td>39</td><td>40</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Time(s)</th><td>10</td><td>9</td><td>9</td><td>8</td><td>8</td><td>7</td><td>7</td><td>7</td><td>6</td><td>6</td>
            <td>6</td><td>6</td><td>5</td><td>5</td><td>5</td><td>5</td><td>5</td><td>4</td><td>4</td><td>4</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          Aborted actions will be resolved as if intended that way.
          For playability reasons partial effects will not be applied
          until the action is completed.
        </p>
        <h3 id="Injury">Injury</h3>
        <p>
          The weapon and armour B/E/P values each are subtracted
          from each other individually, and the results are all added
          to the injury dimension. Using certain aspects of the weapon are
          a choice on part of the attacker, the defender usually 
          cannot choose to ignore parts of his bonus.
        </p>
        <p>
          The time dimension can be increased in order to reduce or increase
          the injury dimension.
        </p>
        <p>
          Wounds are treated individually for recovery (see below). Injury
          is applied directly as penalty to the active side of any skill
          or attribute roll on part of the individual injured.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Level</th><td>-19</td><td>-18</td><td>-17</td><td>-16</td><td>-15</td><td>-14</td><td>-13</td><td>-12</td><td>-11</td><td>-10</td>
            <td>-9</td><td>-8</td><td>-7</td><td>-6</td><td>-5</td><td>-4</td><td>-3</td><td>-2</td><td>-1</td><td>0</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Injury</th><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>4</td><td>4</td><td>4</td><td>4</td><td>5</td><td>5</td><td>5</td>
            <td>5</td><td>6</td><td>6</td><td>7</td><td>7</td><td>8</td><td>8</td><td>9</td><td>9</td><td>10</td>
          </tr>
          <tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="21"></th></tr><tr></tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Level</th><td>1</td><td>2</td><td>3</td><td>4</td><td>5</td><td>6</td><td>7</td><td>8</td><td>9</td><td>10</td>
            <td>11</td><td>12</td><td>13</td><td>14</td><td>15</td><td>16</td><td>17</td><td>18</td><td>19</td><td>20</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Injury</th><td>11</td><td>11</td><td>12</td><td>13</td><td>14</td><td>15</td><td>16</td><td>17</td><td>19</td><td>20</td>
            <td>21</td><td>22</td><td>23</td><td>24</td><td>25</td><td>26</td><td>27</td><td>28</td><td>29</td><td>30</td>
          </tr>
          <tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="21"></th></tr><tr></tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Level</th><td>21</td><td>22</td><td>23</td><td>24</td><td>25</td><td>26</td><td>27</td><td>28</td><td>29</td><td>30</td>
            <td>31</td><td>32</td><td>33</td><td>34</td><td>35</td><td>36</td><td>37</td><td>38</td><td>39</td><td>40</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Injury</th><td>31</td><td>32</td><td>33</td><td>34</td><td>35</td><td>36</td><td>37</td><td>38</td><td>39</td><td>40</td>
            <td>41</td><td>42</td><td>43</td><td>44</td><td>45</td><td>46</td><td>47</td><td>48</td><td>49</td><td>50</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h3 id="armour">Impediments</h3>
        <p>
          All impediments affect all types of activity.  Use the wound/damage
          (being negative) as passive level, and use either <em>Stamina</em>
          (live objects) or <em>Quality</em> (dead objects) as active.  Add any
          attending physician through <n10/>.  Healing is only possible during 
          rest.  Dead objects do not heal but are repaired.
        </p>
        <h4 id="heal">Healing</h4>
        <p>
          A roll is made every time the wound turns into a new penalty (until it
          reaches zero). The result row shows the number of days to wait, before
          one point is removed. If finer granularity in the table below is desired:
          the day value of 5 is halved for every 10 points of wound increase.
        </p>
        <p>
          Sometimes wounds are dire enough that life leaves the body.
          This is simulated by rolling against a difficulty of <em>-45</em>
          every day. Without modifiers, this gives you a life-expectancy
          of upward of 50 years and normally this is not rolled at all. But wounds
          are added to the skill of <n0/>, making it more likely to happen.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Wound</th><td>19</td><td>18</td><td>17</td><td>16</td><td>15</td><td>14</td><td>13</td><td>12</td><td>11</td>
            <td>10</td><td>9</td><td>8</td><td>7</td><td>6</td><td>5</td><td>4</td><td>3</td><td>2</td><td>1</td><td>0</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Days</th><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>2</td><td>2</td><td>2</td><td>2</td><td>2</td><td>2</td>
            <td>2</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>4</td><td>4</td><td>4</td><td>4</td><td>5</td><td>5</td>
          </tr>
          <tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="21"></th></tr><tr></tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Wound</th><td>-1</td><td>-2</td><td>-3</td><td>-4</td><td>-5</td><td>-6</td><td>-7</td><td>-8</td><td>-9</td>
            <td>-10</td><td>-11</td><td>-12</td><td>-13</td><td>-14</td><td>-15</td><td>-16</td><td>-17</td><td>-18</td><td>-19</td><td>-20</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Days</th><td>5</td><td>6</td><td>6</td><td>7</td><td>7</td><td>8</td><td>8</td><td>9</td><td>9</td>
            <td>10</td><td>11</td><td>13</td><td>15</td><td>17</td><td>20</td><td>23</td><td>26</td><td>30</td><td>35</td><td>40</td>
          </tr>
          <tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="21"></th></tr><tr></tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Wound</th><td>-21</td><td>-22</td><td>-23</td><td>-24</td><td>-25</td><td>-26</td><td>-27</td><td>-28</td><td>-29</td>
            <td>-30</td><td>-31</td><td>-32</td><td>-33</td><td>-34</td><td>-35</td><td>-36</td><td>-37</td><td>-38</td><td>-39</td><td>-40</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Days</th><td>46</td><td>53</td><td>61</td><td>70</td><td>80</td><td>92</td><td>106</td><td>121</td><td>139</td>
            <td>160</td><td>184</td><td>211</td><td>243</td><td>279</td><td>320</td><td>368</td><td>422</td><td>485</td><td>577</td><td>640</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          To improve <em>pragmatics</em> for kill rolls, we first only roll the active roll, but roll against <em>50</em>
          and the second measure, we roll at the same time as the wound level is modified, but with a modifier for
          the number of days spent.  Since a kill during any day of the healing period is a kill, row five of the combination
          table, as should be for the maximum. The following table is calculates everything for convenience.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Days</th><td>1</td><td>2</td><td>3</td><td>4</td><td>5</td><td>6</td><td>7</td><td>8</td><td>9</td>
            <td>10-11</td><td>12-13</td><td>14-15</td><td>16-17</td><td>18-20</td><td>21-23</td><td>24-27</td><td>28-30</td><td>31-35</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Addition</th><td>0</td><td>5</td><td>8</td><td>10</td><td>11</td><td>13</td><td>14</td><td>15</td><td>16</td>
            <td>17</td><td>18</td><td>19</td><td>20</td><td>21</td><td>22</td><td>23</td><td>24</td><td>25</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          A further <em>pragmatics</em> improvement, particularly for hefty wounds, is to simply take
          the day value from the table and not spread it through additional dice rolling. Or consider taking 
          the result of one die roll for several healing rolls.
        </p>
        <h4>Extended Example:</h4>
        <p>
          Suppose our character starts out with a wound of <em>-20</em> at day <n1/>, has a Stamina of <n6/> and a physician
          with a skill of <em>19</em> constantly attends him.  Through the combination table (row <n10/>), this gives a bonus
          of <em>+24</em>.  A heal roll of <em>+3</em> gives a total of <em>+ 3 + 24 - 20 = 7</em>.  The kill roll equals
          +<em>14</em> against <em>-30</em>, which is obviously successful. This mean after <n3/> days the wound total
          is reduced by <n1/> to <em>19</em>. On day <n4/>, another roll is made under the same conditions and <em>-4</em> 
          yields a total of <em>- 4 + 24 - 19 = 1</em>, which means <n5/> additional days, so the character will reduce his
          wounds to <em>18</em> on day <n9/>. However, on day <n4/> a kill roll <n7/> is made against <em>-31</em>, this roll 
          is modified by +<n3/> for the number of days.  We track the complete process in the following table.  (An asterisk
          marks the kill rolls that should <em>not</em> have been skipped; all others could have been according to the
          pragmatics above.)
        </p>
        <table class="bsp">
          <tr>
            <th>Day</th><th>Wounds</th><th>Heal/roll</th><th>Heal/total</th><th>Heal/days</th><th>Kill/add</th><th>Kill/roll</th><th>Kill/total</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>1</td><td>20</td><td>+3</td><td>7</td><td>3</td><td>8</td><td>+14</td><td>-8</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>4</td><td>19</td><td>-4</td><td>1</td><td>5</td><td>11</td><td>+3</td><td>-17</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>9</td><td>18</td><td>+2</td><td>8</td><td>3</td><td>8</td><td>+6</td><td>-18</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>12</td><td>17</td><td>-15</td><td>-8</td><td>9</td><td>16</td><td>+6</td><td>-11</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>21</td><td>16</td><td>+5</td><td>13</td><td>2</td><td>5</td><td>+5</td><td>-24</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>23</td><td>15</td><td>-8</td><td>1</td><td>5</td><td>11</td><td>+1</td><td>-23</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>28</td><td>14</td><td>-4</td><td>6</td><td>3</td><td>8</td><td>+1</td><td>-27</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>31</td><td>13</td><td>+1</td><td>12</td><td>2</td><td>5</td><td>+8</td><td>-24</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>33</td><td>12</td><td>+3</td><td>15</td><td>2</td><td>5</td><td>+5</td><td>-28</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>35</td><td>11</td><td>-3</td><td>10</td><td>2</td><td>5</td><td>+3</td><td>-31</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>37</td><td>10</td><td>-1</td><td>13</td><td>2</td><td>5</td><td>+15</td><td>-20</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>39</td><td>9</td><td>-2</td><td>13</td><td>2</td><td>5</td><td>+1</td><td>-35</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>41</td><td>8</td><td>+5</td><td>21</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>+3</td><td>-39</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>42</td><td>7</td><td>+1</td><td>18</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>+5</td><td>-38</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>43</td><td>6</td><td>-7</td><td>11</td><td>2</td><td>5</td><td>+7</td><td>-32</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>45</td><td>5</td><td>-9</td><td>10</td><td>2</td><td>5</td><td>+1</td><td>-39</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>47</td><td>4</td><td>-7</td><td>13</td><td>2</td><td>5</td><td>+12</td><td>-29</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>49</td><td>3</td><td>+2</td><td>23</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>+1</td><td>-46</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>50</td><td>2</td><td>+11</td><td>33</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>+9</td><td>-39</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>51</td><td>1</td><td>+1</td><td>24</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>+1</td><td>-48</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>52</td><td>0</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h4>Infections</h4>
        <p>
          An infection is a new wound at the same level as the original wound, except physician skill is at <em>-10</em> when treating it.
          Healing rate is measured in watches instead of days, but the kill rolls increasse in frequency as well.
        </p>
        <h4>Weapon/Armor Damage</h4>
        <p>
          An additional roll is made, any time a strike is delivered
          regardless of whether noticable injury was caused.  Subtract
          active from passive quality.  Don't forget to roll a second
          time with rolls reversed.  If both weapons and/or multiple
          pieces of armor are concerned, you can use the
          composition/decomposition rule.
        </p>
        <p>
          Damage applies to the appropriate B/E/P value directly until
          <n0/> is reached. Quality rating is also affected through row <n5/>
          on the passive side.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Level</th><td>-19</td><td>-18</td><td>-17</td><td>-16</td><td>-15</td><td>-14</td><td>-13</td><td>-12</td><td>-11</td> <td>-10</td>
            <td>-9</td><td>-8</td><td>-7</td><td>-6</td><td>-5</td><td>-4</td> <td>-3</td><td>-2</td><td>-1</td><td>0</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Damage</th><td>9</td><td>8</td><td>7</td><td>6</td><td>5</td><td>5</td><td>4</td><td>4</td><td>3</td><td>3</td>
            <td>2</td><td>2</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0 (0.2)</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          Impediments below add HR penalty as max component.
          HR as percentage is rolled once per unit time for +1 % or -1 % in HR.
          For diesase and infection this unit is one day.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Level</th>
            <td>-30</td>
            <td>-20</td>
            <td>-10</td>
            <td>0</td>
            <td>10</td>
            <td>20</td>
            <td>30</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Injury</th>
            <td>-1</td>
            <td>-3</td>
            <td>-6</td>
            <td>-10</td>
            <td>-20</td>
            <td>-40</td>
            <td>-80</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Time</th>
            <td>80s</td>
            <td>56s</td>
            <td>40s</td>
            <td>28s</td>
            <td>20s</td>
            <td>14s</td>
            <td>10s</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Type</th>
            <th>Level 0</th>
            <th>Level 10</th>
            <th>Recovery</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Sleep</th>
            <td>16 h</td>
            <td>48 h</td>
            <td>+ 1 / h</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Thirst</th>
            <td>6 h</td>
            <td>24 h</td>
            <td>+ 1 / pt</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Hunger</th>
            <td>24 h</td>
            <td>5 days</td>
            <td>+ 1 / 2 oz</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Air</th>
            <td>10 sec</td>
            <td>60 sec</td>
            <td>+ 1 / sec</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
      </div>
    </div>
    -->
    </div>
  </body>
</html>
