<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="main.xsl"?>
<html xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">
  <head>
    <title>Harn RPG Rules</title>
    <meta charset="UTF-8" />
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="https://fonts.googleapis.com/css?family=Merriweather"/>
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="main.css"/>
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="gf.css"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <div class="main">
      <div class="title">Harn RPG Rules</div>

      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="char">Character</h1>
        <h3 id="char-1">Pages 1-6, 13-14</h3>
        <p>
          The attributes remain in place as
          Harnworld requires them. In other words, without them,
          a character is incomplete in the setting. They are also not
          transformed in any way. Generation of values can be used as
          suggested.
        </p>
        <h3 id="char-2">Pages 7-8, 10</h3>
        <p>
          The attributes described are translated (linearly) into
          the range -15 to 15. <em>Moraliy</em> is dropped.  Generation
          of values can be used as suggested.
        </p>
        <h3 id="char-3">Pages 9, 11-12</h3>
        <p>
          Table results from these page are used purely in their descriptive sense.
          Whether they retroractively have any effect on other attributes
          is a choice that can be made during character creation and according
          to the severity or interpretation of the result that you want to portait.
          <em>Piety</em> is turned into a skill (q.v.) for each deity. For a single
          deity the value can be chosen or generated as suggested. All others are 0
          initially.
        </p>
        <h4 id="piety">Piety</h4>
        <ul class="explain">
          <li>
            <b>Level 0:</b> NN knows that the reigion exist but cannot
            separate it from other convocations.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 5:</b> Lip service payed to the religion and ability
            to separate it from other major faiths.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 10:</b> The main tenants of the religion are known
            and followed on individual level. Sects or heresies are not
            considered.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 15:</b> The religion is quoted often and other faiths
            routinely treated underhanded. Proselytizing is rarely attempted.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 20:</b> At this level the adherent is actively seeking
            to further the tenants of the religion outside of his immediate
            domain. Distinction between inner-religion minutiae are important.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 25:</b> Heresy is abhorred more than other religions.
            Support for the religion takes precendents over other interests
            almost always.
          </li>
          <li>
            <b>Level 30:</b> The adherent is a prophet for the religion and
            accepts otherwise serious consequences for following details of
            his faith. May invent rituals and the like.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <h3 id="char-4">Page 15</h3>
        <p>
          The occupations of the table on this page serve as skills and the listed
          "old" skills serve only as descriptive values.
        </p>
        <h3 id="char-5">Page 16</h3>
        <p>
          <em>Automatic</em> skills are determined accoridng to the appropriate 
          skill section (q.v.) and <em>Occupation</em> skills work as transformed
          for the previous page. They open as 20 for the chosen occupation.
          <em>Family</em> skills for parents in the same occupation add 2 points,
          while for a different occupation they add 5.  (This is effectively
          <em>Row-5-addition</em> of a 0 skill level.) <em>Optional</em> skills are
          as they exist, but new skills may be "invented"; the scope is at GM discretion.
          Any reasoonable skill can be improved by 5 for each option point through
          <em>Row-5-addition</em>. Militia skills are explained elsewhere as are psionics.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="deter">Skill Determination</h1>
        <p>
          Available skills are listed below and are deteremined
          by Harnworld professions and some additional properties
          associated with the setting.  Situations which require 
          rolls are announced by the GM with a general description
          of what needs to be resolved.  Players will then argue,
          which skills could be applicable and the GM will
          give a corresponding percentage of how much they apply.
        </p>
        <p>
          For example, an assessemnt of the correct political relation
          between to rival noble families may be Herald/75% and
          Knight/50%, and Mercantyler/25%.
        </p>
        <p>
          Now roll for all applicable skills you have a value in.
          (Remember that a base 0 always applies.)  In the example
          above, the mercantyler has a 1 in 4 chance of using his
          mercantyler skill, say 12, and a 3 in 4 chance of using his knight 
          skill 0. All skills which were succeessfully rolled for are added up
          through row 3 from the main rules additions table (repeated here).
          The end result is the skill to roll against.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Skill Difference</th><td>0-1</td><td>2-3</td><td>4-9</td><td>10+</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Addition</th><td>3</td><td>2</td><td>1</td><td>0</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
      </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</html>
