<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="main.xsl"?>
<html xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">
  <head>
    <title>Rules for Science Fiction</title>
    <meta charset="UTF-8" />
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="https://fonts.googleapis.com/css?family=Merriweather"/>
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="main.css"/>
    <link rel="stylesheet" media="print" href="mainp.css"/>
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="scifi.css"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <div class="main">
      <div class="title">Rules for Science Fiction</div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="rules">Basic Rules</h1>
        <p>
          This is a set of rules, which represent the aspects
          typically encountered in a SciFi generic setting akin to
          Star Trek, Dark Matter, or Firefly.  It is not intended for
          very realistic setting such as Expanse nor for Space Fantasy
          like Star Wars.  Also see <a href="main.xml">Main Rule</a>
          for the generic details.
        </p>
        <h3 id="overview">Overview</h3>
        <p>
          Many values are taken from Harnmaster (various versions) and
          fan publication such as Gunmaster from Bill Gant (various
          versions) but adapted to the setting.  The intention was to
          benefit from predetermined, balanced values.  For example,
          when comparing firearms with melee weapons, balanced effects
          are possibly play-tested.
        </p>
        <h4>Skill Testing</h4>
        <p>
          Skill testing is a micro-negotiation.  The GM describes the
          task and the dimensions available.  The character in
          question names the skills he thinks are most appropriate.
          The GM then names the diffculty for each of the skills and
          how they can potentially be combined.
        </p>
        <p>
          Then n5 is rolled, adding skill value (SV).  The task
          difficulty value is subtracted from the roll and if the net
          result is non-negative, the skill has been successfully
          employed; if the roll is negative, the attempt has failed.
        </p>
        <p>
          For example, if a PC declares the intent to perform a
          gymnastic feat, he would suggest to the GM that &#8220;I
          have the Acrobatics skill&#8221;.  The GM would then tell
          the player &#8220;this has a difficulty of 15.&#8221; In
          cases where success or failure may not be obvious, the GM
          should make the roll secretly and record the relevant skill
          of the PCs beforehand.
        </p>
        <p>
          To determine the degree of success or failure, use the
          dimensions.
        </p>
        <p>
          When two characters use skills against each other, each
          character makes a p5 skill roll appropriate to the skill in
          question and the results are compared to give a net result.
          The character with the higher result wins the challenge.  If
          both characters achieve the same success level, this is a
          stalemate.  If a tie is not appropriate to the situation,
          toss a coin.
        </p>
        <h4>Star Scale</h4>
        <p>
          The star-scale is often used to simplify evaluation.
        </p>
        <table style="width:75%">
          <tr>
            <th>Stars</th>
            <td>&#9733;</td>
            <td>&#9733;&#9733;</td>
            <td>&#9733;&#9733;&#9733;</td>
            <td>&#9733;&#9733;&#9733;&#9733;</td>
            <td>&#9733;&#9733;&#9733;&#9733;&#9733;</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>SV</th>
            <td>5-15</td>
            <td>15-25</td>
            <td>25-35</td>
            <td>35-45</td>
            <td>45-55</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h3 id="five-add">5-Addition</h3>
        <p>
          A convenience table for the 5-addition of zeroes.  Rounding
          is to one fractional digit only.  Multiples of 2 are left
          out; every doubling means a +5.
        </p>
        <table style="width:80%">
          <tr>
            <th>Number</th>
            <td>3</td>
            <td>5</td>
            <td>7</td>
            <td>9</td>
            <td>11</td>
            <td>13</td>
            <td>15</td>
            <td>17</td>
            <td>19</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Result</th>
            <td>7.9</td>
            <td>11.6</td>
            <td>14</td>
            <td>15.8</td>
            <td>17.3</td>
            <td>18.5</td>
            <td>19.5</td>
            <td>20.4</td>
            <td>21.2</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h3 id="dim-link">Dimension Links</h3>
        <table class="links" style="width:75%">
          <tr>
            <td><a href="#di-acc">Accuracy</a></td>
            <td><a href="#di-c1i">Climbing</a></td>
            <td><a href="#di-co1">Combat</a></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><a href="#di-sta">Healing</a></td>
            <td><a href="#di-ini">Initiative</a></td>
            <td><a href="#di-kno">Knowledge</a></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><a href="#di-mov">Move</a></td>
            <td><a href="#di-spe">Speed</a></td>
            <td><a href="#di-yie">Yield</a></td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h3 id="dim">Dimensions</h3>
        <p>
          The following shows example dimensions.  Finding the
          appropriate dimension depends on the concrete circumstances.
          Consider what would be appropriate for an untrained
          individual (SV 0) and what is expected (the average result)
          for a sufficiently educated person (SV 20).  Interpret the
          results inbetween and outside of the bounds accordingly.
        </p>
        <h5 id="di-acc">Accuracy</h5>
        <p>
          Judging the values of goods produced or performances
          delivered.  Also see the <a href="main.xml">Main Rule</a>
        </p>
        <table style="width:80%">
          <tr>
            <th>Dimension</th>
            <th>0</th>
            <th>10</th>
            <th>20</th>
            <th>30</th>
            <th>40</th>
          </tr>
          <tr class="text">
            <td>Error</td>
            <td>50% - 200%</td>
            <td>80% - 125%</td>
            <td>90% - 110%</td>
            <td>95% - 105%</td>
            <td>97% - 103%</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h5 class="skill" id="di-cli">Climbing</h5>
        <p>
          Climbing Speed is 1/4 walking speed at success. Speed can be
          increased by 1/4 for a -10 penalty, or decreased
          accordingly, but negative speeds are not allowed.  E.g. for
          a +10, one can opt to simply try and cling to a holding to
          not fall down.  A failure results in a fall, usually evenly
          distributed among the total climb.
        </p>
        <h5 class="skill" id="di-co1">Combat</h5>
        <p>
          One dimension is the time, which it takes to achieve the
          wound level zero on the defender.  The wound level is a
          separate dimension; you can use trajectories.  Once a
          (rolled) progression has reached its goal, a new skill roll
          is made.  It is therefore possible to play 4-second
          round-based combat.  The weapon table show the base time it
          takes to attack once.  This is multiplied by the number in
          the table.
        </p>
        <p>
          The <em>wounds</em> are the result of the <em>value</em>
          calculation divided by 5, e.g. a 35 value result is 7
          wounds.  Wounds only apply, if the attack/defense + n5
          result is positive.  Negative wounds may result from cover
          and other circumstances but are not applied.
        </p>
        <p>
          The fractional parts for the higher values in the time
          dimension mean that multiple attacks &#8220;connect&#8221;
          at the same time.  This is to avoid combat in split seconds.
        </p>
        <table style="width:90%">
          <tr>
            <th>Dimension</th>
            <th>-30</th>
            <th>-20</th>
            <th>-10</th>
            <th>0</th>
            <th>10</th>
            <th>20</th>
            <th>30</th>
            <th>40</th>
          </tr>
          <tr class="num">
            <td>Time</td>
            <td>8</td>
            <td>4</td>
            <td>2</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>1/2</td>
            <td>1/4</td>
            <td>1/8</td>
            <td>1/16</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          Weapons list the minimal recovery time, i.e. reload time.
        </p>
        <p>
          For grappling, wounds are treated as penalty to any physical
          activity that instead of damage to heal.  Such wounds are
          immediately reduced to zero, once the grapple is no longer
          maintained.
        </p>
        <h5 class="skill" id="di-sta">Healing</h5>
        <p>
          Healing time is given for one wound point.  Note that a
          reduction in the effective wound points causes re-evaluation
          of the effective healing rate, but should be ignored for
          playability.
        </p>
        <p>
          Wounds are the (individual) task levels, but the wounds
          themselves adversely affect healing individually and the
          time unit is days.  Add half the skill value of a medic
          present when determining the healing rate.  Healing rate can
          be improved with during the healing process in the same
          manner.
        </p>
        <table style="width:75%">
          <tr>
            <th>Dimension</th>
            <th>-20</th>
            <th>-15</th>
            <th>-10</th>
            <th>-5</th>
            <th>0</th>
            <th>5</th>
            <th>10</th>
            <th>15</th>
            <th>20</th>
          </tr>
          <tr class="num">
            <td>Time</td>
            <td>4</td>
            <td>3</td>
            <td>2</td>
            <td>3/2</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>3/4</td>
            <td>1/2</td>
            <td>3/8</td>
            <td>1/4</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h5 class="skill" id="di-ini">Initiative</h5>
        <p>
          Initiative reflects battle experience, discipline, and
          morale.  Initiative determines the speed in which characters
          can assess a stressful situation.  Characters take the time
          listed before they can act.  An ambush gives a penalty.
          During the time a character is &#8220;frozen&#8221; this
          way, he is trying to understand the situation he is in and
          assesses the options he has.  He is <em>cautious</em> during
          that time.  General awareness issues are not covered by
          Initiative.  Battle-hardened characters may come into the
          fractional range.  Fractions can be used to determine who
          goes first.
        </p>
        <p>
          The situation in combat changes constantly.  One action is
          assumed to take 4 seconds, going prematurely incurs the
          usual 5-subtraction penalty.  (Acting every 8 seconds can
          occasionally lend a bonus.)
        </p>
        <p>
          For round-based combat, Initiative usually simply determines
          the order of activity.  Changing the order or acting twice
          by accepting penalties should be avoided, as it can quickly
          lead to escalation, the avoidance of which is precisely the
          reason round-based combat is used.
        </p>
        <table style="width:90%">
          <tr>
            <th>Dimension</th>
            <th>-20</th>
            <th>-15</th>
            <th>-10</th>
            <th>-5</th>
            <th>0</th>
            <th>5</th>
            <th>10</th>
            <th>15</th>
            <th>20</th>
            <th>25</th>
            <th>30</th>
            <th>35</th>
            <th>40</th>
          </tr>
          <tr class="num">
            <td>Time</td>
            <td>20</td>
            <td>15</td>
            <td>10</td>
            <td>6</td>
            <td>4</td>
            <td>3</td>
            <td>2</td>
            <td>1.5</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>0.6</td>
            <td>0.4</td>
            <td>0.3</td>
            <td>0.2</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h5 class="skill" id="di-kno">Knowledge</h5>
        <p>
          This dimension can also be used as knowledge about
          knowledge, i.e. how sure is the character that his
          reproduction of the knowledge is correct.
        </p>
        <div class="explain">
          <p>
            <em>-10:</em> Knowing that the domain can provide
            knowledge is shaky.
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>0:</em> Character knows the domain for such knowledge
            exists and can separate it from different domains.
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>10:</em> The basic concepts are known, advanced
            concepts have been heard of but cannot be applied.
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>20:</em> Most concepts of the domain are known and can
            be applied.  The character is less confident with fringe
            concepts.
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>30:</em> The domain is understood with ease.
            Improvement of the art is possible.
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>40:</em> Mastery of the domain as far as humanly
            possible.  Improvement of the art is a normal task.
          </p>
        </div>
        <h5 class="skill" id="di-mov">Move</h5>
        <p>
          Consider load and acceleration for unusually fast movers (or
          abusers).
        </p>
        <table style="width:90%">
          <tr>
            <th>Dimension</th>
            <th>-60</th>
            <th>-50</th>
            <th>-40</th>
            <th>-30</th>
            <th>-20</th>
            <th>-10</th>
            <th>0</th>
            <th>10</th>
            <th>20</th>
            <th>30</th>
            <th>40</th>
            <th>50</th>
            <th>60</th>
          </tr>
          <tr class="num">
            <td>Speed (m/s)</td>
            <td>5/16</td>
            <td>7/16</td>
            <td>5/8</td>
            <td>7/8</td>
            <td>5/4</td>
            <td>7/4</td>
            <td>5/2</td>
            <td>7/2</td>
            <td>5</td>
            <td>7</td>
            <td>10</td>
            <td>15</td>
            <td>20</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h5 class="skill" id="di-spe">Speed</h5>
        <p>
          This is used to determine how quick short reactive actions
          are made.  Those are actions that need to be completed
          within a few seconds, usually in combat.  If an action
          extends beyond 100% duration when attempting to be quick, it
          fails.
        </p>
        <table style="width:90%">
          <tr>
            <th>Dimension</th>
            <th>20</th>
            <th>25</th>
            <th>30</th>
            <th>35</th>
            <th>40</th>
          </tr>
          <tr class="num">
            <td>Speed</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>3/4</td>
            <td>1/2</td>
            <td>3/8</td>
            <td>1/4</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h5 class="skill" id="di-yie">Yield</h5>
        <p>
          <em>Yield</em> is used for various creation or harvesting
          tasks.  <em>Yield</em> can usually be compensated by
          spending more time but in some cases a minimum result must
          be achieved or time cannot be consecutively be spent,
          &#8220;ruining&#8221; the result.
        </p>
        <p>
          As example: 2 time units with with SV 5 yields 3.
        </p>
        <table style="width:80%">
          <tr>
            <th>Dimension</th>
            <th>-20</th>
            <th>-15</th>
            <th>-10</th>
            <th>-5</th>
            <th>0</th>
            <th>5</th>
            <th>10</th>
            <th>15</th>
            <th>20</th>
          </tr>
          <tr class="num">
            <td>Yield</td>
            <td>1/4</td>
            <td>3/8</td>
            <td>1/2</td>
            <td>3/4</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>3/2</td>
            <td>2</td>
            <td>3</td>
            <td>4</td>
          </tr>
          <tr class="num">
            <td>Time</td>
            <td>4</td>
            <td>3</td>
            <td>2</td>
            <td>3/2</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>3/4</td>
            <td>1/2</td>
            <td>3/8</td>
            <td>1/4</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h5/>
        <h3 id="skills">Skills</h3>
        <p>
          Skills can be specialized.  Specialization has the advantage
          of reducing the task level in a specific domain, which
          general skill would not do.  For example specializing in a
          specific melee weapon such as a sword, would reduce the task
          of fighting against an opponent more susceptible to such
          attacks compared to general melee weapons.
        </p>
        <h3 id="tasks">Tasks</h3>
        <p>
          For a task multiple skills may be applicable.  Usually they
          can be 5-added but the difficulty may also be different for
          their application.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="combat">Combat</h1>
        <p>
          At the beginning of each combat the players and GM should
          jointly decide which action options they want to allow and
          which will simply be abstracted by a set penalty/bonus by
          the GM.  This can speed up combat tremendously.  If tactical
          options outside of combat are affected by the decision, the
          GM should inform the players of that.  For instance, if
          vehicle combat is too tedious today, than the PCs might just
          as well disembark already to allow for smoother combat
          resolution.
        </p>
        <p>
          In order to simulate larger combats with many participants,
          the usual 5-Addition can be used.  It does not provide as
          many tactical options as individual combat does, but greatly
          reduces time spent.  Both time and wound dimension should be
          scaled linearly with the number of particpipants.  E.g. a
          wound of 5 after 30 seconds would scale to a total of 50
          points after 5 minutes for 10 people or to 500 points after
          50 minutes for 100 people.  The points should be distributed
          in reasonable batches on the participants on each side, the
          smallest batch size being the wounds rolled.  People can be
          hit multiple times.
        </p>
        <h3 id="co-links">Combat Links</h3>
        <table class="links" style="width:90%">
          <tr>
            <td><a href="#co-aim">Aiming</a></td>
            <td><a href="#co-block">Evade</a></td>
            <td><a href="#co-blood">Bloodloss</a></td>
            <td><a href="#co-sleep">Deprivation</a></td>
            <td><a href="#co-engage">Engagement</a></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><a href="#co-grapple">Grapple/Tangle</a></td>
            <td><a href="#co-grope">Grope</a></td>
            <td><a href="#co-melee">Melee</a></td>
            <td><a href="#co-missile">Missile</a></td>
            <td><a href="#co-move">Move</a></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><a href="#co-prep">Preparation</a></td>
            <td><a href="#co-push">Push</a></td>
            <td><a href="#co-rise">Rise/Fumble/Stumble</a></td>
            <td><a href="#co-shock">Shock</a></td>
            <td><a href="#co-wounds">Wounds</a></td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h5 id="co-aim">Aiming</h5>
        <p>
          For every reduction of the target zone by 50%
          (exponentially) shoot at -5.  A miss by 5 points randomly
          assigned to the five equally sized surrounding fields of the
          <em>aim plane</em>.  Note that this gives a 20% chance of
          hitting the other 50% of the target zone.  This can be
          applied repeatedly to either understand how wildly off a
          shot was or when firing at a wall of enemies.
        </p>
        <p>
          For the purpose of attitude to an attacker, normal humans
          are considered a &#8220;block&#8221; of 100% by 50% by 25%.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-block">Evade</h5>
        <p>
	  Skills to evade do not include any mental skills or missile
	  skills.  Unarmed, melee weapons, strength are all applicable.
	  If the same skill is used for multiple, simultaneous
	  actions, it is at +5, compensating some of the penalty
	  for multiple actions.
        </p>
        <p>
          Any combination of Dodging, Blocking, and Parrying an attack
          is a single action and called <em>Evade</em>.  Evade is not
          assumed at the same time an attack is contemplated by the
          defender himself.  Evade is a 4 second Combat activity.
          Calculate separate, synchronous applications accordingly,
          i.e. a second defense causes a -5 penalty to both parries, a
          third causes a -7.9 to all and so on.  The same is true for
          combining attacks and defenses at the same time.
        </p>
        <p>
          Evade is at a penalty of Initiative divided by the travel
          time of a missile.  Example: An arrow shot at a distance of
          100m travels one second.  If the Initiative is 1s, that is a
          -1 to Evade, an Initiative of 5s has a -5.  A bullet flying
          at 600m/s puts Evade at -6 and -30 respectively.  This
          penalty cannot reduce Evade to less than 0.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-blood">Bloodloss</h5>
        <p>
          Damage taken increases with every complete multiple of 5
          injury level above 10 every 4s.  For example, a 16-20 point
          injury causes 2 points per 4 seconds, or 1 point of
          bloodloss every 1 second.  This number is lost until
          treatment is applied. Treat the final sum as a separate
          injury.  Some wounds will not cause bloodloss (e.g. Frost)
          including wounds to inanimate objects.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-sleep">Deprivation</h5>
        <p>
          <em>Sleep</em>: Every 24 hours without sleep take 5 wounds,
          which cummulate into a single wound.  Observe Incapacitating
          and Destroyed.  These heal at 1 per hour of sleep.
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>Air</em> Every minute without air take 5 wounds, which
          cummulate into a single wound.  Observe Incapacitating and
          Destroyed.  These heal at 1 per second of fresh air.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-engage">Engagement</h5>
        <p>
          Every character has an <em>Engagement Zone</em> of 1.5m radius
          about his center (that does not extend into blocked areas).
          The Engagement Zone of a conscious, prone character is only half
          that.  Unconscious characters have no Engagement Zones but
          may constitute obstacles.  A character may be (melee)
          attacked upon entering an enemy&#8217;s Engagement Zone
          until he leaves that zone.  This entering or leaving may be
          active or passive.  It is possible to be engaged with an
          arbitrary number of enemies at a time.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-grapple">Grapple/Tangle</h5>
        <p>
          Use Unarmed skill when no weapon is involved.  Multiple
          grapples are allowed , but keep track of the grappled
          weapons of all opponents, they can no longer be used to full
          potential.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-grope">Grope</h5>
        <p>
          Use Fine motor skill.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-melee">Melee Attack</h5>
        <p>
          Hitting the wrong target can happen in melee combat.
          Anybody within an engagement zone is subject to an
          (unintentional) attack with SV 0.  This can be added to the
          benefit of other attackers as per multiple attacks above or
          resolved individually with the goal of 0 damage.  A
          character who is attacking (or being attacked by) a prone
          enemy increases Attack/Defense SV with that character by 5.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-missile">Missile Attack</h5>
        <p>
          Count everything within 30 degrees firing arc as a single
          target with task level 0.  To simplify calculations, weapons
          list range categories to hit single humans sized targets and
          Evade is allowed for them.  However, firing into a group
          uses Aiming and 5-addition.  This increase can be used
          purposefully and can be quite devastating when firing at
          advancing troops.  On the other hand, a miss is calculated
          before the damage calculation applies and even a group hit
          allows the individual hit to use Evade - but against the
          &#8220;spread&#8221; roll. It also follows that for a single
          target, at double the listed weapon range, the attacker
          receives a -5.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-move">Move</h5>
        <p>
          Subtract attacker vs defender speed in m/s, when attacking
          during a move (or the second before and after).  For missile
          attacks use speed perpendicular to the direction of the
          attack.  If attacking <em>during</em> a move subtract a
          percentage of 20 correspording to the percentage of a
          maximal move during the period.  The same is valid for Evade
          during a Move.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-prep">Preparation</h5>
        <p>
          A 4 second round can be spent to prepare an activity, which
          shall happen at a dedicated instance.  The conditions must
          be evaluated in less than a second.  Use Initiative at +20
          or alternativly the activity at +5.  Active conditions such
          as suppressive fire are notwithstanding.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-push">Push</h5>
        <p>
          The push attempt must be in the direction the attacker is
          facing and the attacker must follow.  The defender has a
          choice to evade into a semi-circle of up to 120 degrees,
          assuming no obstacles.  Instead of Injury points, meters
          (pushed) are used.  The defender is forced to deduct the
          move from his action allowance, regardless of whether he
          resists or not.  A resist deducts from the distance forced
          and can even be used as a counter-push.  The pushed
          character may opt to fall prone instead at any time, for
          instance to avoid falling of a cliff.  Any remaining
          distance is forfeit.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-rise">Rise/Fumble/Stumble</h5>
        <p>
          Use <em>Gross motor</em> skill for any of these situations.
          The result of the latter two is a stumble or a fumble, while
          the first is the <em>Combat</em> dimension time it takes to
          escape the prone condition. 
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-shock">Shock</h5>
        <p>
          Any new wound of at least 1 point results in a Shock chance.
          Use accumulated injury and fatigue as difficulty for a roll
          against 20.  Failure is measured in the Yield Dimension as
          minutes.  Multiple Shock rolls per round can be 5-added.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-wounds">Wounds</h5>
        <p>
          Combatants who sustain Serious or Grievous wounds may die
          during the healing routine.  On the other hand, various
          types of medicine or prosthetics can improve healing
          greatly.  For descriptive purposes, wounds are called
          <em>Minor</em>, <em>Serious</em>, <em>Grievous</em>,
          <em>Incapacitating</em>, and <em>Destroyed</em> in steps of
          5.
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>Incapacitating:</em>. The system affected cannot be used
          but still be healed.
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>Destroyed:</em> The system affected lost its integrity
          and cannot be healed.  For living beings this means instant
          death.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="tables">Tables</h1>
        <p>
          The following table contains examples for the for formulas
          given here and signal the readily available variants.
        </p>
        <div class="explain">
          <p>
            <em>Skill:</em> A short weapon is any weapon smaller than
            50cm x 20cm x 10cm in every direction. A weapon smaller
            than 1/4 of that in every direction can be used as
            Unarmed.  Any object used as weapon but not built for the
            purpose will give penalties, typically -5.
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>Weight/BEP:</em> A melee weapon will have 8 BEP for a
            weight of 2.5 kg.  Every decrease of 1 BEP leads to half
            of the original weight, the corresponding is true for
            increases.  Remember that a weapon stills to be controlled
            during combat.  This is uncommon for weapons beyond 2kg,
            as the skill is usually not trained on those extreme
            weapons.  Weapons that are easier to manufacture generally
            (or are dual purposed, e.g. can also be thrown) deal less
            damage.
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>Guns</em> Remember that only 1 or two handed weapons
            are allowed.  The units used are found in the table.  BEP
            shall equal nozzle velocity times Amunition weight, while
            BEP times the number of hands used shall equal 8 times the
            gun weight.  Range shall always be 20m for (single) hand
            guns and 40m for rifles.  Ammunition weight shall be 10
            times the difference of the firing rate and the number of
            free hands (0 or 1).
          </p>
        </div>
        <p>
          The weight of one clip case is included in the weapon
          weight.  Energy weapons scale arbitrarily, while guns use
          only whole numbers, i.e. individual projectiles.  Also note
          that armor and BEP are applied after skill damage (and only
          if the net skill application is positive).
        </p>
        <p>
          Restricted energy weapons can be used with other,
          appropriate skills.  Unlisted artillerie generally does not
          distinguish between energy or projectile.
        </p>
        <p>
          Explosives such as grenades lose 1 point of damge per meter
          squared away  from ground zero, e.g. a BEP 50 grenade is effectively
          harmless at 7m distance.  Skill cannot increase damage, only precision.
          Energy weapons may be used with an explosive cone, assuming a
          &#188;m<sup>2</sup> ground zero at aim distance.  For example,
          firing at 4m<sup>2</sup> gives -16 BEP.  Using eccentric cones
          requires configuration time. 
        </p>
        <h3 id="weapons">Weapons</h3>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Weapon</th>
            <th>Skill</th>
            <th>Weight</th>
            <th>Hand</th>
            <th>BEP</th>
            <th>Range</th>
            <th>Rate</th>
            <th>Clip</th>
            <th>Ammo</th>
            <th>Nozzle</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Unarmed</td>
            <td>Unarmed</td>
            <td>-</td>
            <td>2</td>
            <td>2</td>
            <td>-</td>
            <td>4s</td>
            <td>-</td>
            <td>-</td>
            <td>-</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Dagger</td>
            <td>Short Weapon</td>
            <td>300g</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>5</td>
            <td>5m</td>
            <td>4s</td>
            <td>-</td>
            <td>-</td>
            <td>-</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Sword</td>
            <td>Long Weapon</td>
            <td>1.3kg</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>7</td>
            <td>-</td>
            <td>4s</td>
            <td>-</td>
            <td>-</td>
            <td>-</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Club</td>
            <td>Long Weapon</td>
            <td>1.2kg</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>6</td>
            <td>-</td>
            <td>4s</td>
            <td>-</td>
            <td>-</td>
            <td>-</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Axe</td>
            <td>Long Weapon</td>
            <td>1.1kg</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>6</td>
            <td>5m</td>
            <td>4s</td>
            <td>-</td>
            <td>1kg</td>
            <td>6m/s</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Bow</td>
            <td>Bows</td>
            <td>1.5kg</td>
            <td>2</td>
            <td>8</td>
            <td>20m</td>
            <td>6s</td>
            <td>20</td>
            <td>80g</td>
            <td>100m/s</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Light Pistol</td>
            <td>Gun</td>
            <td>1kg</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>6</td>
            <td>20m</td>
            <td>2s</td>
            <td>20</td>
            <td>10g</td>
            <td>600m/s</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Heavy Pistol</td>
            <td>Gun</td>
            <td>2kg</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>18</td>
            <td>20m</td>
            <td>3s</td>
            <td>10</td>
            <td>20g</td>
            <td>900m/s</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Light Rifle</td>
            <td>Gun</td>
            <td>4kg</td>
            <td>2</td>
            <td>12</td>
            <td>40m</td>
            <td>2s</td>
            <td>30</td>
            <td>20g</td>
            <td>600m/s</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Heavy Rifle</td>
            <td>Gun</td>
            <td>6kg</td>
            <td>2</td>
            <td>24</td>
            <td>40m</td>
            <td>4s</td>
            <td>20</td>
            <td>40g</td>
            <td>600m/s</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Machine Gun</td>
            <td>Mounted</td>
            <td>25kg</td>
            <td>2</td>
            <td>36</td>
            <td>40m</td>
            <td>1s</td>
            <td>120</td>
            <td>40g</td>
            <td>900m/s</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Grenade Launcher</td>
            <td>Carried</td>
            <td>3kg</td>
            <td>2</td>
            <td>50</td>
            <td>40m</td>
            <td>12s</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>500g</td>
            <td>100m/s</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Energy Weapon</td>
            <td>Energy weapon</td>
            <td>2.5/(kW/s)</td>
            <td>2</td>
            <td>10/kW</td>
            <td>50m</td>
            <td>1s</td>
            <td>see below</td>
            <td>see below</td>
            <td>Light</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h3 id="protection">Protection</h3>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Material</th>
            <th>Kg (1x1x0.01)</th>
            <th>BEP</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Rock</td>
            <td>3</td>
            <td>25</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Wood</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>8</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Water</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>1</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Plaststeel</td>
            <td>3</td>
            <td>25</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Glas</td>
            <td>1.5</td>
            <td>10</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Metal</td>
            <td>2</td>
            <td>4</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h3 id="equipment">Other Equipment</h3>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Name</th>
            <th>Usage</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Scope</td>
            <td>+5 Aiming</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Aimlock</td>
            <td>Targetlock at 20/4s</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Teargas</td>
            <td>As Grenade but Fatigue only</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Flashbang</td>
            <td>Blind/-20 &#38; +1/s</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Silencer</td>
            <td>-10 Noise</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Vision Enhancer</td>
            <td>Reduce darkness or fog penalties</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Earbeads</td>
            <td>Comms, range 1kWh/km<sup>2</sup></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Energy</td>
            <td>4MWs/1kg</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
      </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</html>
