<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="main.xsl"?>
<html xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">
  <head>
    <title>Rules for Science Fiction</title>
    <meta charset="UTF-8" />
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="https://fonts.googleapis.com/css?family=Merriweather"/>
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="main.css"/>
    <link rel="stylesheet" media="print" href="mainp.css"/>
    <link rel="stylesheet" href="harn.css"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <div class="main">
      <div class="title">Rules for Science Fiction</div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="rules">Basic Rules</h1>
        <p>
          This is a set of rules, which represent the aspects
          typically encountered in a SciFi generic setting.  Akin to
          Star Trek, Dark Matter, or Firefly.  It is not intended for
          very realistic setting such as Expanse nor for Space Fantasy
          like Star Wars.  Also see <a href="main.xml">Main Rule</a>
          for the generic details.
        </p>
        <h3 id="overview">Overview</h3>
        <p>
	  Many values are taken from Harnmaster (various versions) and
	  fan publication such as Gunmaster from Bill Gant (various
	  versions but adapted to these rules.  The intention was to
	  benefit from the relationship of the values.  For example,
	  when comparing firearms with melee weapons.
        </p>
        <h4>Skill Testing</h4>
        <p>
          Skill testing is a micro-negotiation.  The GM describes the
          task and the dimensions available.  The character in
          question names the skills he thinks are most appropriate.
          The GM then names the diffculty for each of the skills and
          how they can potentially be combined. 
        </p>
        <p>
          Now n5 is rolled, adding skill value (SV).  The task
          difficulty value is subtracted from the roll and if the net
          result is non-negative, the skill has been successfully
          employed; if the roll is negative, the attempt has failed.
        </p>
        <p>
          For example, if a PC declares the intent to perform a
          gymnastic feat, he would suggest to the GM that &#8220;I
          have the Acrobatics skill&#8221;.  The GM would then tell
          the player &#8220;this has a difficulty of 15.&#8221; In
          cases where success or failure may not be obvious, the GM
          should make the roll secretly and record the relevant skill
          of the PCs beforehand.
        </p>
        <p>
          To determine the degree of success or failure, use the
          dimensions.
        </p>
        <p>
          When two characters use skills against each other, each
          character makes a p5 skill roll appropriate to the skill in
          question and the results are compared to give a net result.
          The character with the higher result wins the challenge.  If
          both characters achieve the same success level, this is a
          stalemate.  If a tie is not appropriate to the situation,
          toss a coin.
        </p>
        <h4>Star Scale</h4>
        <p>
          The star-scale is often used to simplify evaluation.
        </p>
        <table style="width:75%">
          <tr>
            <th>Stars</th>
            <td>&#9733;</td>
            <td>&#9733;&#9733;</td>
            <td>&#9733;&#9733;&#9733;</td>
            <td>&#9733;&#9733;&#9733;&#9733;</td>
            <td>&#9733;&#9733;&#9733;&#9733;&#9733;</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>SV</th>
            <td>5-15</td>
            <td>15-25</td>
            <td>25-35</td>
            <td>35-45</td>
            <td>45-55</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h3 id="five-add">5-Addition</h3>
        <p>
          A convenience table for the 5-addition of zeroes.  Rounding
          is to one fractional digit only.  Multiples of 2 are left
          out; every doubling means a +5.
        </p>
        <table style="width:80%">
          <tr>
            <th>Number</th>
            <td>3</td>
            <td>5</td>
            <td>7</td>
            <td>9</td>
            <td>11</td>
            <td>13</td>
            <td>15</td>
            <td>17</td>
            <td>19</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>Result</th>
            <td>7.9</td>
            <td>11.6</td>
            <td>14</td>
            <td>15.8</td>
            <td>17.3</td>
            <td>18.5</td>
            <td>19.5</td>
            <td>20.4</td>
            <td>21.2</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h3 id="dim-link">Dimension Links</h3>
        <table class="links" style="width:75%">
          <tr>
            <td><a href="#di-acc">Accuracy</a></td>
            <td><a href="#di-co1">Climbing</a></td>
            <td><a href="#di-co1">Combat</a></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><a href="#di-des">Descriptive</a></td>
            <td><a href="#di-sta">Healing</a></td>
            <td><a href="#di-ini">Initiative</a></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><a href="#di-kno">Knowledge</a></td>
            <td><a href="#di-mov">Move</a></td>
            <td><a href="#di-yie">Yield</a></td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h3 id="dim">Dimensions</h3>
        <p>
          The following shows example dimensions.  Finding the
          appropriate dimension depends on the concrete circumstances.
          Consider what would be appropriate for an untrained
          individual (SV 0) and what is expected (the average result)
          for a sufficiently educated persion (SV 20).  Interpret the
          results inbetween and outside of the bounds accordingly.
        </p>
        <h5 id="di-acc">Accuracy</h5>
        <p>
          Judging the values of goods produced or performances
          delivered.  Also see the <a href="main.xml">Main Rule</a>
        </p>
        <table style="width:80%">
          <tr>
            <th>Dimension</th>
            <th>0</th>
            <th>10</th>
            <th>20</th>
            <th>30</th>
            <th>40</th>
          </tr>
          <tr class="text">
            <td>Error</td>
            <td>50% - 200%</td>
            <td>80% - 125%</td>
            <td>90% - 110%</td>
            <td>95% - 105%</td>
            <td>97% - 103%</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h5 class="skill" id="di-cli">Climbing</h5>
        <p>
          Climbing Speed is 1/4 walking speed at success. Speed can be
          increased by 1/4 for a -10 penalty, or decreased accordingly, but
          negative speeds are not allowed.  E.g. for a +10, one can
          opt to simply try and cling to a holding to not fall down.
          A failure results in a fall, usually evenly distributed
          among the total climb.
        </p>
        <h5 class="skill" id="di-co1">Combat</h5>
        <p>
          One dimension is the time (in seconds), which it takes to
          achieve the wound level zero on the defender.  The wound
          level is a separate dimension; you can use trajectories.
          Once a (rolled) progression has reached its goal, a new
          skill roll is made.  It is therefore possible to play
          10-second round-based combat.
        </p>
        <p>
          The <em>wounds</em> are the result of the <em>value</em>
          calculation divided by 5, e.g. a 35 value result is 7
          wounds.
        </p>
        <p>
          The fractional parts for the higher values in the time
          dimension mean that multiple attacks &#8220;connect&#8221;
          at the same time.  This is to avoid combat in split seconds.
        </p>
        <table style="width:90%">
          <tr>
            <th>Dimension</th>
            <th>-30</th>
            <th>-20</th>
            <th>-10</th>
            <th>0</th>
            <th>10</th>
            <th>20</th>
            <th>30</th>
            <th>40</th>
          </tr>
          <tr class="num">
            <td>Time</td>
            <td>80</td>
            <td>40</td>
            <td>20</td>
            <td>10</td>
            <td>5</td>
            <td>5/2</td>
            <td>5/4</td>
            <td>5/8</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
	  Weapons list the minimal recovery time, i.e. relaod time.
        </p>
        <p>
          For grappling, wounds are treated as penalty to any physical
          activity that instead of damage to heal.  Such wounds are
          immediately reduced to zero, once the grapple is no longer
          maintained.
        </p>
        <h5 class="skill" id="di-des">Descriptive</h5>
        <p>
          Description for various default skill applications that are not quantitative.
        </p>
        <table style="width:70%">
          <tr>
            <th>Dimension</th>
            <th>-10</th>
            <th>-0</th>
            <th>10</th>
            <th>20</th>
            <th>30</th>
            <th>40</th>
          </tr>
          <tr class="text">
            <td>Rhetoric</td>
            <td>Noise</td>
            <td>Comprehension</td>
            <td>Listening</td>
            <td>Consideration</td>
            <td>Agreement</td>
            <td>Agreement</td>
          </tr>
          <tr class="text">
            <td>Singing</td>
            <td>Imperceptible</td>
            <td>Childlike</td>
            <td>Folk</td>
            <td>Artist</td>
            <td>Original</td>
            <td>Unique</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Awareness</td>
            <td>Immediate</td>
            <td>General</td>
            <td>Movement</td>
            <td>Strangeness</td>
            <td>Distance</td>
            <td>6th sense</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Language</td>
            <td>Exists</td>
            <td>Basic</td>
            <td>Fair</td>
            <td>Fluent</td>
            <td>Faceted</td>
            <td>Mastery</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h5 class="skill" id="di-sta">Healing</h5>
        <p>
          Healing time is given for one wound point.  Note that a
          reduction in the effective wound points causes re-evaluation
          of the effective healing rate, but should be ignored for
          playability.
        </p>
        <p>
          Wounds are the (individual) task levels, but the wounds
          themselves adverse effect healing.  individually and the
          time unit is days.  Add a potential physician&#8217;s bonus
          (see below) once when determining the healing rate.  Healing
          rate can be improved with a physician present during the
          healing process in the same manner.
        </p>
        <p>
          Physicians modify with half their skill result against the
          same wound level during tending and diagnosing a patient.
          (For particularly severe cases it may be better for a doctor
          to abstain.)  This is not a trajectory.
        </p>
        <table style="width:75%">
          <tr>
            <th>Dimension</th>
            <th>-20</th>
            <th>-15</th>
            <th>-10</th>
            <th>-5</th>
            <th>0</th>
            <th>5</th>
            <th>10</th>
            <th>15</th>
            <th>20</th>
          </tr>
          <tr class="num">
            <td>Time</td>
            <td>4</td>
            <td>3</td>
            <td>2</td>
            <td>3/2</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>3/4</td>
            <td>1/2</td>
            <td>3/8</td>
            <td>1/4</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h5 class="skill" id="di-ini">Initiative</h5>
        <p>
          Initiative reflects battle experience, discipline, and
          morale.  Initiative determines the speed in which characters
          can assess a stressful situation.  Characters take the time
          listed before they can act.  An ambush gives a penalty.
        </p>
        <p>
          During the time a character is &#8220;frozen&#8221; this
          way, he is trying to understand the situation he is in and
          assesses the options he has.  He is <em>cautious</em> during
          that time.  General awareness issues are not covered by
          Initiative.
        </p>
        <p>
          Battle-hardened characters may come into the fractional
          range.  Fractions can be used to determine who goes first.
          The GM determines, whether going first impedes the action of
          another in the second that the action takes place.  This
          changes the drama of simultaneous activity, which may or may
          not be appropriate.
        </p>
        <p>
          The situation in combat changes constantly.  After one
          action, the next is given the penalty of the Penalty
          dimension, which is reduced by 1 per second, a penalty
          indicates taking premature action.  For round-based combat,
          this penalty is reduced by 10 and then halved.  (Acting every
          other round reduces the penalty by 10 once more.)
        </p>
        <p>
          (The Penalty-formula is derived from assuming a Time penalty
          of the value indicated before each round and then acting one
          round.  E.g. at value 20 this gives 13.  Since such a
          penalty would be reduced continuously, the average is
          taken.)
        </p>
        <p>
          For round-based combat, Initiative usually simply determines
          the order of activity.  Changing the order or acting twice
          by accepting penalties should be avoided, as it can quickly
          lead to escalation, the avoidance of which is precisely the
          reason round-based combat is used. Round-based numbers are
          also rounded towards the smaller absolute value, to reduce
          speculation on fractional rounding.
        </p>
        <table style="width:90%">
          <tr>
            <th>Dimension</th>
            <th>-20</th>
            <th>-15</th>
            <th>-10</th>
            <th>-5</th>
            <th>0</th>
            <th>5</th>
            <th>10</th>
            <th>15</th>
            <th>20</th>
            <th>25</th>
            <th>30</th>
            <th>35</th>
            <th>40</th>
          </tr>
          <tr class="num">
            <td>Time</td>
            <td>60</td>
            <td>45</td>
            <td>30</td>
            <td>20</td>
            <td>10</td>
            <td>8</td>
            <td>6</td>
            <td>4.5</td>
            <td>3</td>
            <td>2</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>0.8</td>
            <td>0.6</td>
          </tr>
          <tr class="num">
            <td>Penalty</td>
            <td>-35</td>
            <td>-28</td>
            <td>-20</td>
            <td>-15</td>
            <td>-10</td>
            <td>-9</td>
            <td>-8</td>
            <td>-7</td>
            <td>-7</td>
            <td>-6</td>
            <td>-6</td>
            <td>-6</td>
            <td>-5</td>
          </tr>
          <tr class="num">
            <td>Rd Penalty</td>
            <td>-12</td>
            <td>-8</td>
            <td>-5</td>
            <td>-2</td>
            <td>0</td>
            <td>0</td>
            <td>+1</td>
            <td>+1</td>
            <td>+1</td>
            <td>+2</td>
            <td>+2</td>
            <td>+2</td>
            <td>+2</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h5 class="skill" id="di-kno">Knowledge</h5>
        <p>
          This dimension can also be used as knowledge about
          knowledge, i.e. how sure is the character that his
          reproduction of the knowledge is correct.
        </p>
        <div class="explain">
          <p>
            <em>-10:</em> Knowing that the domain can provide
            knowledge is shaky.
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>0:</em> Character knows the domain for such knowledge
            exists and can separate it from different domains.
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>10:</em> The basic concepts are known, advanced
            concepts have been heard of but cannot be applied.
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>20:</em> Most concepts of the domain are known and can
            be applied.  The character is less confident with fringe
            concepts.
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>30:</em> The domain is understood with ease.
            Improvement of the art is possible.
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>40:</em> Mastery of the domain as far as humanly
            possible.  Improvement of the art is a normal task.
          </p>
        </div>
        <h5 class="skill" id="di-mov">Move</h5>
        <p>
          Consider load and acceleration for unusually fast movers (or
          abusers).
        </p>
        <table style="width:90%">
          <tr>
            <th>Dimension</th>
            <th>-60</th>
            <th>-50</th>
            <th>-40</th>
            <th>-30</th>
            <th>-20</th>
            <th>-10</th>
            <th>0</th>
            <th>10</th>
            <th>20</th>
            <th>30</th>
            <th>40</th>
            <th>50</th>
            <th>60</th>
          </tr>
          <tr class="num">
            <td>Speed (m/s)</td>
            <td>5/16</td>
            <td>7/16</td>
            <td>5/8</td>
            <td>7/8</td>
            <td>5/4</td>
            <td>7/4</td>
            <td>5/2</td>
            <td>7/2</td>
            <td>5</td>
            <td>7</td>
            <td>10</td>
            <td>15</td>
            <td>20</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h5 class="skill" id="di-yie">Yield</h5>
        <p>
          <em>Yield</em> is used for various creation or harvesting
          tasks.  <em>Yield</em> can usually be compensated by
          spending more time but in some cases a minimum result must
          be achieved or time cannot be consecutively be spent,
          &#8220;ruining&#8221; the result.
        </p>
        <p>
          As example: 2 time units with with SV 5 yields 3.
        </p>
        <table style="width:80%">
          <tr>
            <th>Dimension</th>
            <th>-20</th>
            <th>-15</th>
            <th>-10</th>
            <th>-5</th>
            <th>0</th>
            <th>5</th>
            <th>10</th>
            <th>15</th>
            <th>20</th>
          </tr>
          <tr class="num">
            <td>Yield</td>
            <td>1/4</td>
            <td>3/8</td>
            <td>1/2</td>
            <td>3/4</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>3/2</td>
            <td>2</td>
            <td>3</td>
            <td>4</td>
          </tr>
          <tr class="num">
            <td>Time</td>
            <td>4</td>
            <td>3</td>
            <td>2</td>
            <td>3/2</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>3/4</td>
            <td>1/2</td>
            <td>3/8</td>
            <td>1/4</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h5/>
        <h3 id="skills">Skills</h3>
        <p>
	  Skills can be specialized.  Specialization has the advantage
	  of reducing the task level in a specific domain, which
	  general skill would not do.  For example specializing in a
	  specific melee weapon such as a sword, would reduce the task
	  of fighting against an opponent more susceptible to such
	  attacks compared to general melee weapons.
        </p>
        <h3 id="tasks">Tasks</h3>
        <p>
          For a task multiple skills may be applicable.  Usually they
          can be 5-added but the difficulty may also be different for
          their application.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div class="container">
        <h1 id="combat">Combat</h1>
        <p>
          At the beginning of each combat the players and GM should
          jointly decide which action options they want to allow and
          which will simply be abstracted by a set penalty/bonus by
          the GM.  This can speed up combat tremendously.  If tactical
          options outside of combat are affected by the decision, the
          GM should inform the players of that.  For instance, if
          vehicle combat is too tedious today, than the PCs might just
          as well disembark already to allow for smoother combat
          resolution.
        </p>
        <p>
          In order to simulate larger combats with many participants,
          the usual 5-Addition can be used.  It does not provide as
          many tactical options as individual combat does, but greatly
          reduces time spent.  Both time and wound dimension should be
          scaled linearly with the number of particpipants.  E.g. a
          wound of 5 after 30 seconds would scale to a total of 50
          points after 5 minutes for 10 people or to 500 points after
          50 minutes for 100 people.  The points should be distributed
          in reasonable batches on the participants on each side, the
          smallest batch size being the wounds rolled.  People can be
          hit multiple times.
        </p>
        <h3 id="co-links">Combat Links</h3>
        <table class="links" style="width:90%">
          <tr>
            <td><a href="#co-move">Move</a></td>
            <td><a href="#co-engage">Engage</a></td>
            <td><a href="#co-charge">Charge</a></td>
            <td><a href="#co-push">Push</a></td>
            <td><a href="#co-rise">Rise</a></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><a href="#co-grope">Grope</a></td>
            <td><a href="#co-melee">Melee</a></td>
            <td><a href="#co-missile">Missile</a></td>
            <td><a href="#co-grapple">Grapple/Tangle</a></td>
            <td><a href="#co-block">Block/Dodge</a></td>
            <td><a href="#co-aim">Aiming</a></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><a href="#co-fumble">Fumble</a></td>
            <td><a href="#co-stumble">Stumble</a></td>
            <td><a href="#co-shock">Shock</a></td>
            <td><a href="#co-inanimate">Inanimate Damage</a></td>
            <td><a href="#co-weapdam">Weapon/Armor Damage</a></td>
            <td><a href="#co-bloodloss">Bloodloss</a></td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h5 id="co-move">Move</h5>
        <p>
          To avoid lengthy calculations, subtract 50% of the attacker
          speed in m/s, when attacking during a move.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-engage">Engage</h5>
        <p>
          Every character has an <em>Engagement Zone</em> of 1m plus
          weapon length radius about his center (that does not extend
          into blocked areas).  The Engagement Zone of a conscious,
          prone character is only half that.  Unconscious characters
          have no Engagement Zones but may constitute obstacles.  A
          character may be (melee) attacked upon entering an
          enemy&#8217;s Engagement Zone until he leaves that zone.
          This entering or leaving may be active or passive.  It is
          possible to be engaged with an arbitrary number of enemies
          at a time.  A character with a long reach weapon has an
          appropriately larger engagement zone and may therefore be
          eligible to attack before others.  This may be of importance
          for mounted Charges into a row of Pikemen.  Also note the
          restriction on using long weapons at short range.
          dimensions.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-charge">Charge</h5>
        <p>
          Every engagement along the way may attack a moving character
          (and vice versa).  Any attacker plunging into defenders with
          an attack will stop.  Such a forced stop will result in a
          fall impact for charger as if from height equal to the speed
          minus 5.  E.g. stopping at 10 m/s speed equals a fall from
          5m.  Note that the fall impact also applies the targets
          fallen into.  This is the charge bonus which can be added to
          the attack.  For opportunistic melee attacks, this is also a
          direct penalty to the Dodge skill.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-push">Push</h5>
        <p>
          The push attempt must be in the direction the attacker is
          facing and the attacker must follow.  The defender has a
          choice to evade into a semi-circle of up to 120 degrees,
          assuming no obstacles.  Instead of Injury points, meters
          (pushed) are used.  The defender is forced to deduct the
          move from his action allowance, regardless of whether he
          resists or not.  A resist deducts from the distance forced
          and can even be used as a counter-push.  The pushed
          character may opt to fall prone instead at any time, for
          instance to avoid falling of a cliff.  Any remaing distance
          is forfeit.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-rise">Rise</h5>
        <p>
          Use Acrobatics skill.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-grope">Grope</h5>
        <p>
          Use Dexterity skill.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-melee">Melee Attack</h5>
        <p>
          A rider and horse may act in unison and add their combat
          skill per 5-Addition.  Both accrue the same fatigue.
          Hitting the wrong target can happen in melee combat.
          Anybody within an engagement zone is subject to an
          (unintentional) attack with MLU 0. This can be added to the
          benefit of other attackers as per multiple attacks above or
          resolved individually with the goal of 0 damage.  A
          character who is attacking (or being attacked by) a prone
          enemy increases Attack/Defense MLU with that character by 4.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-missile">Missile Attack</h5>
        <p>
          For throwing arbitrary objects, use Throwing skill.  Since
          missile attacks are resolved with individual shots, a missed
          attack is applied only if the intended attack had no impact.
          Count all potential targets completely in an arc of 30
          degrees and +/-2 range levels of the intended target.  Use
          5-Addition of zeroes, but reduce by 5 for the missed,
          intended opponent.  If a hit is scored on the much larger
          &#8220;super-target&#8221;, roll which individual target is
          hit by distributing evenly among all the unintended targets.
          When determining hit chances and damage apply the size
          modifier from the Size table below.  At GM discretion,
          inanimate objects not participating in the skirmish may be
          counted as potential targets, particularly, if the actual
          targets are spread widely across the area.  This increase
          can be used purposefully and can be quite devastating when
          firing at advancing troops.  Dodge against missile is
          reduced by 5.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-grapple">Grapple/Tangle Attack Defense</h5>
        <p>
          Use Unarmed Combat skill when no weapon is involved.
          Multiple grapples are allowed , but keep track of the
          grappled weapons of all opponents, they can no longer be
          used to full potential.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-block">Block/Dodge</h5>
        <p>
          Dodge and Block/Parry are mostly used together through
          5-Addition.  Dodge/Parry can be used at the same time an
          attack is contemplated by the defender himself.  Parry
          is a 10 second Combat activity.  Calculate separate, synchronous
          parries accordingly, i.e. a second defense causes a -5 penalty to
          both parries, a third causes a -7.5 to all and so on.  Defenders
          may split the penalty among different attackers. 
          Dodge is unmodified for multiple opponents but at -5 for high
          velocity missile attacks.
        </p>
        <p>
          Not attacking for 10 seconds grants a +5 to (both) Dodge and 
          Parry.  Forfeiting Parry and Dodge instead grants a +5 to other
          Combat actions.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-aim">Aiming</h5>
        <p>
          The Attacker may declare one Main area as not being hit for
          a penalty of 1 to MLU.  This choice can be taken multiple
          times, but the remaining Main locations must remain (bodily)
          connected.  If all but one Main location has been
          eliminated, individual percentage points may be reduced for
          a Detail area.  This penalty can again be taken multiple
          times but the remaining Detail hit locations must be
          (bodily) connected.  The GM may restrict or penalize the
          choice of Aiming Zone if the attacker could only reach
          certain target zones with the declared attack weapon.  A
          prone attacker would find it difficult to aim high on a
          standing opponent with a melee weapon.  The Size table can
          be used, if the target is smaller than man-sized.  This
          effect does not cumulate with aiming for parts of a target
          (the main part of this paragraph).  There is no modification
          for man-sized creatures, unless the target offers a smaller
          effective target, but it may be combined with unintentional
          hitting (see above).  A prone man, for example, presents a
          target about 2 feet tall, and a crouching man about 4 feet
          tall.  Similar height adjustments may apply to other targets
          at GM discretion.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-fumble">Fumble</h5>
        <p>
          Any new wound of at least 1 point to arms results in a
          Fumble chance.  Use accumulated damage to that extremity and
          fatigue as difficulty for a Dexterity skill roll against 0.
          Failure results in dropping anything held on that arm.  If
          something is held in both hands, 5-add the difficulties and
          the two Dexterity EMLUs.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-stumble">Stumble</h5>
        <p>
          Any new wound of at least 1 point to legs results in a
          stumble chance.  Use accumulated damage to that extremity
          and fatigue as difficulty for an Agility skill roll against
          0.  Failure results in dropping prone. Each additional leg
          after the first can be 5-added.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-shock">Shock</h5>
        <p>
          Any new wound of at least 1 point results in a Shock chance.
          Use accumulated injury and fatigue as difficulty for a
          Stamina skill roll against 0.  Failure is measured in the
          Yield Dimension as minutes.  Multiple Shock rolls can be
          5-added.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-inanimate">Inanimate Damage</h5>
        <p>
          Instead of (autonomous) Healing, Repair must be applied
          externally.  Use the appropriate Craft skill instead of
          Physician.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-weapdam">Weapon/Armor Damage</h5>
        <p>
          Weapon and Armor make a Shock roll for the damage that they
          absorb, respectively deal.  Weapon Quality (WQ) is used
          instead of Stamina skill and damage is not accumulated.
          Armor works the same way, but instead if Stamina, sum up
          BEPF.  Failure means a weapon or armor breaks, which may
          potentially be repaired as above. (Regular maintenance is
          assumed, otherwise accumlate 1 point per &#8220;unrepaired
          wound&#8221; for weapons and armor for the purpose of Shock
          rolls.
        </p>
        <h5 id="co-bloodloss">Bloodloss</h5>
        <p>
          Damage taken increases with every complete multiple of 5
          injury level above 6 every 10s.  For example, a 16-20 point
          injury causes 2 points per 10 seconds, or 1 point of
          bloodloss every 5 seconds.  Some wounds will not cause
          bloodloss (e.g. Frost) including to inanimate objects or
          reduced damage, e.g. blunt trauma.
        </p>
        <h5/>
        <p style="text-align:center">
          Size Table
        </p>
        <table style="width:70%">
          <tr>
            <th>Modifier</th>
            <th>-5</th>
            <th>-4</th>
            <th>-3</th>
            <th>-2</th>
            <th>-1</th>
            <th>0</th>
            <th>+1</th>
            <th>+2</th>
            <th>+3</th>
            <th>+4</th>
            <th>+5</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Size</td>
            <td>1ft</td>
            <td>1.5ft</td>
            <td>2ft</td>
            <td>3ft</td>
            <td>4ft</td>
            <td>6ft</td>
            <td>8ft</td>
            <td>12ft</td>
            <td>16ft</td>
            <td>24ft</td>
            <td>32ft</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p style="text-align:center">
          Fall Table
        </p>
        <table style="width:70%">
          <tr>
            <th>Height (ft)</th>
            <th>0</th>
            <th>5</th>
            <th>10</th>
            <th>15</th>
            <th>20</th>
            <th>25</th>
            <th>30</th>
            <th>35</th>
            <th>40</th>
            <th>45</th>
            <th>50</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Impact (B)</td>
            <td>0</td>
            <td>0</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>3</td>
            <td>5</td>
            <td>10</td>
            <td>15</td>
            <td>25</td>
            <td>35</td>
            <td>44</td>
            <td>75</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p style="text-align:center">
          Shock Table
        </p>
        <table style="width:90%">
          <tr>
            <th>Result</th>
            <th>-1</th>
            <th>-2</th>
            <th>-3</th>
            <th>-4</th>
            <th>-5</th>
            <th>-6</th>
            <th>-7</th>
            <th>-8</th>
            <th>-9</th>
            <th>-10</th>
            <th>-11</th>
            <th>-12</th>
            <th>-13</th>
            <th>-14</th>
            <th>-15</th>
            <th>-16</th>
            <th>-17</th>
            <th>-18</th>
            <th>-19</th>
            <th>-20</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Time</td>
            <td>1s</td>
            <td>3s</td>
            <td>6s</td>
            <td>10s</td>
            <td>30s</td>
            <td>1min</td>
            <td>3min</td>
            <td>6min</td>
            <td>10min</td>
            <td>30min</td>
            <td>1h</td>
            <td>3h</td>
            <td>6h</td>
            <td>10h</td>
            <td>1day</td>
            <td>3day</td>
            <td>6days</td>
            <td>10days</td>
            <td>30days</td>
            <td>60days</td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <h3 id="wounds">Wounds</h3>
        <p>
          Combatants who sustain Serious or Grievous wounds may die
          during the healing routine.  On the other hand, various
          types of magic, miracles, Psionics, and potions can improve
          healing.
        </p>
        <p>
          When the following text says, adjacent body parts are
          affected, effects include penalties (which are not
          cumulative but take the maximum) infection chance and
          bloodloss (also not cumulative but take the maximum).  They
          are not recursive, i.e. do not imply secondary effects.
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>1-5:</em> Minor.  Wounds only have wound penalty.
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>5-10:</em> Serious. Wounds of this type also have minor
          effects on neighbouring detailed body parts at 5 points
          less.  Any activity involving these body parts are at the
          appropriate penalty.  These effect wounds do not heal
          separately.
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>11-15:</em> Grievous.  The detailed body part cannot be
          used, serious use effects on neighbouring detailed body
          parts, and minor on neighboring main parts. (This might only
          be the including main part.)  These effect wounds do not
          heal separately.  Minor effects are at 10 less than the
          Grievous, while serious are 5 less.
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>16-20:</em> Incapacitating, the main body part cannot be
          used, serious use effects on neighbouring main body parts.
          (For head this means unconsciousness and for thorax imminent
          death.)  Serious effects are at 10 less than the
          incapacitating wound itself.
        </p>
        <p>
          <em>21+:</em> Destroyed, the main body part lost its
          integrity, Grievous use effects on neighbouring main body
          parts.  (For limbs this means at least severed.  Thorax is
          split open or spinal cord severed.  For all but the
          extremities this means instant death.  For all other body
          parts, death is probably imminent due to the side effects.)
          Grievous use effects are at 10 less than the Destroyed wound
          itself.
        </p>
        <h3 id="heal-wounds">Healing</h3>
        <p>
          See the Healing dimension. An untreated wound is considered
          as being treated by a Physician with the negative
          wound-level.  E.g. a wound with 6 injury points is treated
          as if diagnosed by Physician with MLU -6.  The standard
          treatments mostly known by all still need to be applied and
          detailed, so a physician&#8217;s diagnosis is always
          necessary.  &#8220;Destroyed&#8221; wounds may be treated as
          incapacitating, with a Bonus on Diagnosis of 5.  Note that
          the usage effects on bordering regions needs to be treated
          as well.  Overtreatment is possible but has no specific
          negative impact.
        </p>
        <p>
          Bloodloss is treated as a separate injury.  Note that the
          circulatory system is incapacitated with points in excess of
          15 points as other body parts are.  The circulatory system
          itself will not turn infectious.  Treatment by physicians
          depend on the location.  Some locations are incurable by
          H&#226;rnic physicians.  For multiple bleeders only take the
          maximum in the same extremity, but add those for different
          extremities.  Incapacitating and destroying wounds have no
          additional effects over the bleeder and infection dangers.
        </p>
        <p>
          Infections, diseases, toxins, and other come in various
          forms.  Bloodloss is already explained elsewhere, but
          repeated here for reference.
        </p>
        <div class="explain">
          <p>
            <em>Bloodloss</em> Damage taken increases with every
            complete multiple of 5 injury level above 6 every 10s.
            For example, a 16-20 point injury causes 2 points per 10
            seconds, or 1 point of bloodloss every 5 seconds.  This
            number is lost every 10 seconds until the treatment
            <em>Compress</em> is applied.  Thereafter these points
            heal at 1 per day.
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>Infection</em> An open wound with more than 5 injury
            points is attacked daily with MLU of the injury points
            against Stamina (skill) until it has less than 5 points or
            is otherwise closed.  The injury points start with 1 and
            are received 1 per watch until the infection has run its
            course, i.e. the result value.  These new points are added
            to the wound as integral part.  Adjust healing rate etc
            accordingly.
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>Sleep deprivation</em> Every watch after a Stamina
            roll against -20 in hours, with a penalty of 1 per hour of
            not having slept.  For playability start rolling after 24h
            and the injury points are always 5.  The points are
            regained at the rate of 1 per hour of sleep.
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>Thirst</em> Every watch after a Stamina roll against
            -20, with a penalty of 1 for each liter of water that has
            not been drunk per day on average.  For playability start
            rolling after 3 days without water have passed.  Points
            are regained at the rate of 1 per hour.
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>Hunger</em> Every day after a Stamina roll against
            -20, with a penalty of 1 for each two pounds of food that
            have not been eaten per day on average.  For playability
            start rolling after 10 days without food have passed.
            Points are regained at the rate of 1 per hour.
          </p>
          <p>
            <em>Suffocation</em> Every minute without air a Stamina
            roll against 0 is required, with a penalty of 5 for each
            consecutive minute without air.  Points are regained at
            the rate of 1 per second once air is available again..
          </p>
        </div>
        <h3 id="effect-wounds">Effects</h3>
        <p>
          Fatigue is fully applied to all skill rolls.
        </p>
        <p>
          Any physical skill receives one half of all the wound points
          as penalty.  Any non-physical skill receives the full
          <em>head</em> wound points as penalty.  Moving receives any
          <em>leg</em> inhury fully but none of the others.
        </p>
        <p>
          Non-skill penalties such as Healing or Stumble are described
          in the appropriate sections.
        </p>
      </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</html>
